Okay, so welcome to lecture two of CS231N.
On Tuesday we, just recall, we, sort of, gave you
the big picture view of what is computer vision,
what is the history,
and a little bit of the overview of the class.
And today, we're really going to dive in, for the first time,
into the details.
And we'll start to see, in much more depth,
exactly how some of these learning algorithms
actually work in practice.
So, the first lecture of the class
is probably, sort of, the largest big picture vision.
And the majority of the lectures in this class
will be much more detail orientated,
much more focused on the specific mechanics,
of these different algorithms.
So, today we'll see our first learning algorithm
and that'll be really exciting, I think.
But, before we get to that,
I wanted to talk about a couple of administrative issues.
One, is Piazza.
So, I saw it when I checked yesterday,
it seemed like we had maybe 500 students
signed up on Piazza.
Which means that there are several hundred of you
who are not yet there.
So, we really want Piazza to be the main source
of communication between the students and the core staff.
So, we've gotten a lot of questions to the staff list
about project ideas or questions about midterm attendance
or poster session attendance.
And, any, sort of, questions like that
should really go to Piazza.
You'll probably get answers to your questions faster
on Piazza, because all the TAs are knowing to check that.
And it's, sort of, easy for emails to get lost
in the shuffle if you just send to the course list.
It's also come to my attention that some SCPD students
are having a bit of a hard time signing up for Piazza.
SCPD students are supposed to receive a
@stanford.edu email address.
So, once you get that email address,
then you can use the Stanford email to sign into Piazza.
Probably that doesn't affect those of you who are
sitting in the room right now,
but, for those students listening on SCPD.
The next administrative issue is about assignment one.
Assignment one will be up later today,
probably sometime this afternoon,
but I promise, before I go to sleep tonight,
it'll be up.
But, if you're getting a little bit antsy
and really want to start working on it right now,
then you can look at last year's version
of assignment one.
It'll be pretty much the same content.
We're just reshuffling it a little bit to make it,
like, for example, upgrading to work with Python 3,
rather than Python 2.7.
And some of these minor cosmetic changes,
but the content of the assignment will still be the same
as last year.
So, in this assignment you'll be implementing your own
k-nearest neighbor classifier,
which we're going to talk about in this lecture.
You'll also implement several different linear classifiers,
including the SVM and Softmax,
as well as a simple two-layer neural network.
And we'll cover all this content
over the next couple of lectures.
So, all of our assignments are using Python and NumPy.
If you aren't familiar with Python or NumPy,
then we have written a tutorial that you can find
on the course website to try and get you up to speed.
But, this is, actually, pretty important.
NumPy lets you write these very efficient vectorized
operations that let you do quite a lot of computation
in just a couple lines of code.
So this is super important for pretty much
all aspects of numerical computing and machine learning
and everything like that,
is efficiently implementing these vectorized operations.
And you'll get a lot of practice with this
on the first assignment.
So, for those of you who don't have a lot of experience
with Matlab or NumPy or other types of vectorized
tensor computation, I recommend that you start looking
at this assignment pretty early
and also, read carefully through the tutorial.
The other thing I wanted to talk about
is that we're happy to announce that
we're officially supported through Google Cloud
for this class.
So, Google Cloud is somewhat similar to Amazon AWS.
You can go and start virtual machines up in the cloud.
These virtual machines can have GPUs.
We're working on the tutorial for exactly how to use
Google Cloud and get it to work for the assignments.
But our intention is that you'll be able to just download
some image, and it'll be very seamless
for you to work on the assignments
on one of these instances on the cloud.
And because Google has, very generously,
supported this course,
we'll be able to distribute to each of you
coupons that let you use Google Cloud credits for free
for the class.
So you can feel free to use these for the assignments
and also for the course projects
when you want to start using GPUs and larger machines
and whatnot.
So, we'll post more details about that,
probably, on Piazza later today.
But, I just wanted to mention,
because I know there had been a couple of questions
about, can I use my laptop?
Do I have to run on corn?
Do I have to, whatever?
And the answer is that, you'll be able to run on
Google Cloud and we'll provide you some coupons for that.
Yeah, so,
those are, kind of, the major administrative issues
I wanted to talk about today.
And then, let's dive into the content.
So, the last lecture we talked a little bit
about this task of image classification,
which is really a core task in computer vision.
And this is something that we'll really focus on
throughout the course of the class.
Is, exactly,
how do we work on this image classification task?
So, a little bit more concretely,
when you're doing image classification,
your system receives some input image,
which is this cute cat in this example,
and the system is aware of some predetermined set
of categories or labels.
So, these might be, like, a dog or a cat or a truck
or a plane, and there's some fixed set of category labels,
and the job of the computer is to look at the picture
and assign it one of these fixed category labels.
This seems like a really easy problem,
because so much of your own visual system in your brain
is hardwired to doing these, sort of,
visual recognition tasks.
But this is actually a really, really hard problem
for a machine.
So, if you dig in and think about, actually,
what does a computer see when it looks at this image,
it definitely doesn't get this holistic idea of a cat
that you see when you look at it.
And the computer really is representing the image
as this gigantic grid of numbers.
So, the image might be something like 800 by 600 pixels.
And each pixel is represented by three numbers,
giving the red, green, and blue values for that pixel.
So, to the computer,
this is just a gigantic grid of numbers.
And it's very difficult to distill the cat-ness
out of this, like, giant array of thousands, or whatever,
very many different numbers.
So, we refer to this problem as the semantic gap.
This idea of a cat, or this label of a cat,
is a semantic label that we're assigning to this image,
and there's this huge gap between the semantic idea of a cat
and these pixel values that the computer is actually seeing.
And this is a really hard problem because
you can change the picture in very small, subtle ways
that will cause this pixel grid to change entirely.
So, for example, if we took this same cat,
and if the cat happened to sit still
and not even twitch, not move a muscle,
which is never going to happen,
but we moved the camera to the other side,
then every single grid, every single pixel,
in this giant grid of numbers
would be completely different.
But, somehow, it's still representing the same cat.
And our algorithms need to be robust to this.
But, not only viewpoint is one problem,
another is illumination.
There can be different lighting conditions going on
in the scene.
Whether the cat is appearing in this very dark, moody scene,
or like is this very bright, sunlit scene, it's still a cat,
and our algorithms need to be robust to that.
Objects can also deform.
I think cats are, maybe, among the more deformable
of animals that you might see out there.
And cats can really assume a lot of different, varied poses
and positions.
And our algorithms should be robust to these different
kinds of transforms.
There can also be problems of occlusion,
where you might only see part of a cat, like, just the face,
or in this extreme example, just a tail peeking out
from under the couch cushion.
But, in these cases, it's pretty easy for you, as a person,
to realize that this is probably a cat,
and you still recognize these images as cats.
And this is something that our algorithms
also must be robust to,
which is quite difficult, I think.
There can also be problems of background clutter,
where maybe the foreground object of the cat,
could actually look quite similar in appearance
to the background.
And this is another thing that we need to handle.
There's also this problem of intraclass variation,
that this one notion of cat-ness, actually spans a lot of
different visual appearances.
And cats can come in different shapes and sizes
and colors and ages.
And our algorithm, again, needs to work
and handle all these different variations.
So, this is actually a really, really challenging problem.
And it's sort of easy to forget how easy this is
because so much of your brain is specifically tuned
for dealing with these things.
But now if we want our computer programs
to deal with all of these problems, all simultaneously,
and not just for cats, by the way,
but for just about any object category you can imagine,
this is a fantastically challenging problem.
And it's, actually, somewhat miraculous
that this works at all, in my opinion.
But, actually, not only does it work,
but these things work very close to human accuracy
in some limited situations.
And take only hundreds of milliseconds to do so.
So, this is some pretty amazing, incredible technology,
in my opinion, and over the course of the rest of the class
we will really see what kinds of advancements
have made this possible.
So now, if you, kind of, think about
what is the API for writing an image classifier,
you might sit down and try to write a method in Python
like this.
Where you want to take in an image
and then do some crazy magic
and then, eventually, spit out this class label
to say cat or dog or whatnot.
And there's really no obvious way to do this, right?
If you're taking an algorithms class
and your task is to sort numbers
or compute a convex hull
or, even, do something like RSA encryption,
you, sort of, can write down an algorithm
and enumerate all the steps that need to happen
in order for this things to work.
But, when we're trying to recognize objects,
or recognize cats or images,
there's no really clear, explicit algorithm
that makes intuitive sense,
for how you might go about recognizing these objects.
So, this is, again, quite challenging,
if you think about,
if it was your first day programming
and you had to sit down and write this function,
I think most people would be in trouble.
That being said,
people have definitely made explicit attempts
to try to write, sort of, high-end coded rules
for recognizing different animals.
So, we touched on this a little bit in the last lecture,
but maybe one idea for cats is that,
we know that cats have ears and eyes and mouths and noses.
And we know that edges, from Hubel and Wiesel,
we know that edges are pretty important
when it comes to visual recognition.
So one thing we might try to do is
compute the edges of this image
and then go in and try to categorize all the different
corners and boundaries, and say that, if we have maybe
three lines meeting this way, then it might be a corner,
and an ear has one corner here and one corner there
and one corner there,
and then, kind of, write down this explicit set of rules
for recognizing cats.
But this turns out not to work very well.
One, it's super brittle.
And, two, say, if you want to start over for another
object category, and maybe not worry about cats,
but talk about trucks or dogs or fishes or something else,
then you need to start all over again.
So, this is really not a very scalable approach.
We want to come up with some algorithm, or some method,
for these recognition tasks
which scales much more naturally to all the variety
of objects in the world.
So, the insight that, sort of, makes this all work
is this idea of the data-driven approach.
Rather than sitting down and writing these hand-specified
rules to try to craft exactly what is a cat or a fish
or what have you,
instead, we'll go out onto the internet
and collect a large dataset of many, many cats
and many, many airplanes and many, many deer
and different things like this.
And we can actually use tools like Google Image Search,
or something like that,
to go out and collect a very large number of examples
of these different categories.
By the way, this actually takes quite a lot of effort
to go out and actually collect these datasets
but, luckily, there's a lot of really good, high quality
datasets out there already for you to use.
Then once we get this dataset,
we train this machine learning classifier
that is going to ingest all of the data,
summarize it in some way,
and then spit out a model
that summarizes the knowledge of how to recognize
these different object categories.
Then finally, we'll use this training model
and apply it on new images
that will then be able to recognize
cats and dogs and whatnot.
So here our API has changed a little bit.
Rather than a single function
that just inputs an image and recognizes a cat,
we have these two functions.
One, called, train, that's going to input images and labels
and then output a model,
and then, separately, another function called, predict,
which will input the model and than make predictions
for images.
And this is, kind of, the key insight
that allowed all these things to start working really well
over the last 10, 20 years or so.
So, this class is primarily about neural networks
and convolutional neural networks
and deep learning and all that,
but this idea of a data-driven approach is much more general
than just deep learning.
And I think it's useful to, sort of,
step through this process
for a very simple classifier first,
before we get to these big, complex ones.
So, probably, the simplest classifier you can imagine
is something we call nearest neighbor.
The algorithm is pretty dumb, honestly.
So, during the training step we won't do anything,
we'll just memorize all of the training data.
So this is very simple.
And now, during the prediction step,
we're going to take some new image
and go and try to find the most similar image
in the training data to that new image,
and now predict the label of that most similar image.
A very simple algorithm.
But it, sort of, has a lot of these nice properties
with respect to data-drivenness and whatnot.
So, to be a little bit more concrete,
you might imagine working on this dataset called CIFAR-10,
which is very commonly used in machine learning,
as kind of a small test case.
And you'll be working with this dataset on your homework.
So, the CIFAR-10 dataset gives you 10 different classes,
airplanes and automobiles and birds and cats and different
things like that.
And for each of those 10 categories
it provides 50,000 training images,
roughly evenly distributed across these 10 categories.
And then 10,000 additional testing images
that you're supposed to test your algorithm on.
So here's an example of applying this simple
nearest neighbor classifier to some of these test images
on CIFAR-10.
So, on this grid on the right,
for the left most column,
gives a test image in the CIFAR-10 dataset.
And now on the right, we've sorted the training images
and show the most similar training images
to each of these test examples.
And you can see that they look kind of visually similar
to the training images,
although they are not always correct, right?
So, maybe on the second row, we see that the testing,
this is kind of hard to see,
because these images are 32 by 32 pixels,
you need to really dive in there
and try to make your best guess.
But, this image is a dog and it's nearest neighbor is also
a dog, but this next one, I think is actually a deer
or a horse or something else.
But, you can see that it looks quite visually similar,
because there's kind of a white blob in the middle
and whatnot.
So, if we're applying the nearest neighbor algorithm
to this image,
we'll find the closest example in the training set.
And now, the closest example, we know it's label,
because it comes from the training set.
And now, we'll simply say that this testing image is also
a dog.
You can see from these examples that is probably not
going to work very well,
but it's still kind of a nice example to work through.
But then, one detail that we need to know is,
given a pair of images,
how can we actually compare them?
Because, if we're going to take our test image and compare it
to all the training images,
we actually have many different choices
for exactly what that comparison function should look like.
So, in the example in the previous slide,
we've used what's called the L1 distance,
also sometimes called the Manhattan distance.
So, this is a really sort of simple, easy idea
for comparing images.
And that's that we're going to just compare individual pixels
in these images.
So, supposing that our test image is maybe just a tiny
four by four image of pixel values,
then we're take this upper-left hand pixel
of the test image,
subtract off the value in the training image,
take the absolute value,
and get the difference in that pixel between the two images.
And then, sum all these up across all the pixels
in the image.
So, this is kind of a stupid way to compare images,
but it does some reasonable things sometimes.
But, this gives us a very concrete way
to measure the difference between two images.
And in this case, we have this difference of 456
between these two images.
So, here's some full Python code
for implementing this nearest neighbor classifier
and you can see it's pretty short and pretty concise
because we've made use of many of these vectorized
operations offered by NumPy.
So, here we can see that this training function,
that we talked about earlier,
is, again, very simple, in the case of nearest neighbor,
you just memorize the training data,
there's not really much to do here.
And now, at test time, we're going to take in our image
and then go in and compare using this L1 distance function,
our test image to each of these training examples
and find the most similar example in the training set.
And you can see that, we're actually able to do this
in just one or two lines of Python code
by utilizing these vectorized operations in NumPy.
So, this is something that you'll get practice with
on the first assignment.
So now, a couple questions about this simple classifier.
First, if we have N examples in our training set,
then how fast can we expect training and testing to be?
Well, training is probably constant
because we don't really need to do anything,
we just need to memorize the data.
And if you're just copying a pointer,
that's going to be constant time
no matter how big your dataset is.
But now, at test time we need to do this comparison stop
and compare our test image
to each of the N training examples in the dataset.
And this is actually quite slow.
So, this is actually somewhat backwards,
if you think about it.
Because, in practice,
we want our classifiers to be slow at training time
and then fast at testing time.
Because, you might imagine, that a classifier might go
and be trained in a data center somewhere
and you can afford to spend a lot of computation
at training time to make the classifier really good.
But then,
when you go and deploy the classifier at test time,
you want it to run on your mobile phone
or in a browser or some other low power device,
and you really want the testing time performance
of your classifier to be quite fast.
So, from this perspective, this nearest neighbor algorithm,
is, actually, a little bit backwards.
And we'll see that once we move to
convolutional neural networks,
and other types of parametric models,
they'll be the reverse of this.
Where you'll spend a lot of compute at training time,
but then they'll be quite fast at testing time.
So then, the question is,
what exactly does this nearest neighbor algorithm
look like when you apply it in practice?
So, here we've drawn, what we call the decision regions
of a nearest neighbor classifier.
So, here our training set consists of these points
in the two dimensional plane,
where the color of the point represents the category,
or the class label, of that point.
So, here we see we have five classes
and some blue ones up in the corner here,
some purple ones in the upper-right hand corner.
And now for each pixel in this entire plane,
we've gone and computed what is the nearest example
in these training data,
and then colored the point of the background
corresponding to what is the class label.
So, you can see that this nearest neighbor classifier
is just sort of carving up the space
and coloring the space according to the nearby points.
But this classifier is maybe not so great.
And by looking at this picture
we can start to see some of the problems that might come out
with a nearest neighbor classifier.
For one, this central region actually contains
mostly green points,
but one little yellow point in the middle.
But because we're just looking at the nearest neighbor,
this causes a little yellow island to appear
in this middle of this green cluster.
And that's, maybe, not so great.
Maybe those points actually should have been green.
And then, similarly we also see these, sort of, fingers,
like the green region pushing into the blue region,
again, due to the presence of one point,
which may have been noisy or spurious.
So, this kind of motivates a slight generalization
of this algorithm called k-nearest neighbors.
So rather than just looking for the single nearest neighbor,
instead we'll do something a little bit fancier
and find K of our nearest neighbors,
according to our distance metric,
and then take a vote among each of our neighbors.
And then predict the majority vote
among our neighbors.
You can imagine slightly more complex ways of doing this.
Maybe you'd vote weighted on the distance,
or something like that,
but the simplest thing that tends to work pretty well
is just taking a majority vote.
So here we've shown the exact same set of points
using this K=1 nearest neighbor classifier,
as well as K=3 and K=5 in the middle and on the right.
And once we move to K=3, you can see that that spurious
yellow point in the middle of the green cluster
is no longer causing the points near that region
to be classified as yellow.
Now this entire green portion in the middle
is all being classified as green.
You can also see that these fingers
of the red and blue regions
are starting to get smoothed out
due to this majority voting.
And then, once we move to the K=5 case,
then these decision boundaries
between the blue and red regions
have become quite smooth and quite nice.
So, generally when you're using nearest neighbors
classifiers,
you almost always want to use some value of K,
which is larger than one
because this tends to smooth out your decision
boundaries and lead to better results.
Question?
[student asking a question]
Yes, so the question is,
what is the deal with these white regions?
The white regions are where there was no majority
among the k-nearest neighbors.
You could imagine maybe doing something slightly fancier
and maybe taking a guess or randomly selecting among
the majority winners,
but for this simple example we're just coloring it white
to indicate there was no nearest neighbor
in those points.
Whenever we're thinking about computer vision
I think it's really useful to kind of flip
back and forth between several different viewpoints.
One, is this idea of high dimensional points in the plane,
and then the other is actually looking at concrete images.
Because the pixels of the image actually
allow us to think of these images as high dimensional
vectors.
And it's sort of useful to ping pong back and forth
between these two different viewpoints.
So then, sort of taking this k-nearest neighbor
and going back to the images
you can see that it's actually not very good.
Here I've colored in red and green
which images would actually be classified correctly
or incorrectly according to their nearest neighbor.
And you can see that it's really not very good.
But maybe if we used a larger value of K
then this would involve actually voting among
maybe the top three or the top five
or maybe even the whole row.
And you could imagine that that would end up being
a lot more robust to some of this noise that we see
when retrieving neighbors in this way.
So another choice we have when we're working
with the k-nearest neighbor algorithm
is determining exactly how we should be comparing
our different points.
For the examples so far we've just shown
we've talked about this L1 distance
which takes the sum of the absolute values
between the pixels.
But another common choice is the L2 or Euclidean distance
where you take the square root of the sum of the squares
and take this as your distance.
Choosing different distance metrics actually
is a pretty interesting topic
because different distance metrics
make different assumptions about the underlying
geometry or topology that you'd expect in the space.
So, this L1 distance, underneath this, this is actually
a circle according to the L1 distance
and it forms this square shape thing
around the origin.
Where each of the points on this, on the square,
is equidistant from the origin according to L1,
whereas with the L2 or Euclidean distance
then this circle is a familiar circle,
it looks like what you'd expect.
So one interesting thing to point out between these two
metrics in particular,
is that the L1 distance depends on your choice
of coordinates system.
So if you were to rotate the coordinate frame
that would actually change the L1 distance
between the points.
Whereas changing the coordinate frame in the L2 distance
doesn't matter, it's the same thing no matter what
your coordinate frame is.
Maybe if your input features, if the individual entries
in your vector have some important meaning
for your task,
then maybe somehow L1 might be a more natural fit.
But if it's just a generic vector in some space
and you don't know which of the different elements,
you don't know what they actually mean,
then maybe L2 is slightly more natural.
And another point here is that
by using different distance metrics
we can actually generalize the k-nearest neighbor
classifier to many, many different types of data,
not just vectors, not just images.
So, for example, imagine you wanted to classify pieces
of text, then the only thing you need to do
to use k-nearest neighbors
is to specify some distance function
that can measure distances between maybe two paragraphs
or two sentences or something like that.
So, simply by specifying different distance metrics
we can actually apply this algorithm very generally
to basically any type of data.
Even though it's a kind of simple algorithm,
in general, it's a very good thing to try first
when you're looking at a new problem.
So then, it's also kind of interesting to think about
what is actually happening geometrically
if we choose different distance metrics.
So here we see the same set of points on the left
using the L1, or Manhattan distance,
and then, on the right, using the familiar L2,
or Euclidean distance.
And you can see that the shapes of these decision
boundaries actually change quite a bit
between the two metrics.
So when you're looking at L1 these decision boundaries
tend to follow the coordinate axes.
And this is again because the L1 depends on our choice
of coordinate system.
Where the L2 sort of doesn't really care about the
coordinate axis, it just puts the boundaries
where they should fall naturally.
My confession is that each of these examples
that I've shown you is actually from this interactive
web demo that I built,
where you can go and play with this k-nearest neighbor
classifier on your own.
And this is really hard to work on a projector screen.
So maybe we'll do that on your own time.
So, let's just go back to here.
Man, this is kind of embarrassing.
Okay, that was way more trouble than