- Okay.
Can everyone hear me?
Okay.
Sorry for the delay.
I had a bit of technical difficulty.
Today was the first time I was trying to use my
new touch bar Mac book pro for presenting,
and none of the adapters are working.
So, I had to switch laptops at the last minute.
So, thanks.
Sorry about that.
So, today is lecture 10.
We're talking about recurrent neural networks.
So, as of, as usual, a couple administrative notes.
So, We're working hard
on assignment one grading.
Those grades will probably be out
sometime later today.
Hopefully, they can get out
before the A2 deadline.
That's what I'm hoping for.
On a related note, Assignment two is due today at 11:59 p.m.
so, who's done with that already?
About half you guys.
So, you remember, I did warn you
when the assignment went out
that it was quite long, to start early.
So, you were warned about that.
But, hopefully, you guys have some late days left.
Also, as another reminder,
the midterm will be in class on Tuesday.
If you kind of look around the lecture hall,
there are not enough seats in this room
to seat all the enrolled students in the class.
So, we'll actually be having the midterm
in several other lecture halls across campus.
And we'll be sending out some more details
on exactly where to go in the next couple of days.
So a bit of a, another bit of announcement.
We've been working on this sort of
fun bit of extra credit thing for you to play with
that we're calling the training game.
This is this cool browser based experience,
where you can go in
and interactively train neural networks
and tweak the hyper parameters during training.
And this should be a really cool interactive way
for you to practice
some of these hyper parameter tuning skills
that we've been talking about the last couple of lectures.
So this is not required,
but this, I think, will be a really useful experience
to gain a little bit more intuition
into how some of these hyper parameters work
for different types of data sets in practice.
So we're still working on getting
all the bugs worked out of this setup,
and we'll probably send out
some more instructions
on exactly how this will work
in the next couple of days.
But again, not required.
But please do check it out.
I think it'll be really fun
and a really cool thing for you to play with.
And will give you a bit of extra credit
if you do some,
if you end up working with this
and doing a couple of runs with it.
So, we'll again send out some more details about this
soon once we get all the bugs worked out.
As a reminder,
last time we were talking about CNN Architectures.
We kind of walked through the time line
of some of the various winners
of the image net classification challenge,
kind of the breakthrough result.
As we saw was the AlexNet architecture in 2012,
which was a nine layer convolutional network.
It did amazingly well,
and it sort of kick started
this whole deep learning revolution in computer vision,
and kind of brought a lot of these models
into the mainstream.
Then we skipped ahead a couple years,
and saw that in 2014 image net challenge,
we had these two really interesting models,
VGG and GoogLeNet,
which were much deeper.
So VGG was,
they had a 16 and a 19 layer model,
and GoogLeNet was, I believe,
a 22 layer model.
Although one thing that is kind of interesting
about these models
is that the 2014 image net challenge
was right before batch normalization was invented.
So at this time,
before the invention of batch normalization,
training these relatively deep models
of roughly twenty layers was very challenging.
So, in fact, both of these two models
had to resort to a little bit of hackery
in order to get their deep models to converge.
So for VGG, they had the 16 and 19 layer models,
but actually they first trained an 11 layer model,
because that was what they could get to converge.
And then added some extra random layers in the middle
and then continued training,
actually training the 16 and 19 layer models.
So, managing this training process
was very challenging in 2014
before the invention of batch normalization.
Similarly, for GoogLeNet,
we saw that GoogLeNet has these auxiliary classifiers
that were stuck into lower layers of the network.
And these were not really needed for the class to,
to get good classification performance.
This was just sort of a way to cause
extra gradient to be injected
directly into the lower layers of the network.
And this sort of,
this again was before the invention of batch normalization
and now once you have these networks
with batch normalization,
then you no longer need these slightly ugly hacks
in order to get these deeper models to converge.
Then we also saw in the 2015 image net challenge
was this really cool model called ResNet,
these residual networks
that now have these shortcut connections
that actually have these little residual blocks
where we're going to take our input,
pass it through the residual blocks,
and then add that output of the,
then add our input to the block,
to the output from these convolutional layers.
This is kind of a funny architecture,
but it actually has two really nice properties.
One is that if we just set all the weights
in this residual block to zero,
then this block is competing the identity.
So in some way,
it's relatively easy for this model
to learn not to use the layers that it doesn't need.
In addition, it kind of adds this
interpretation to L2 regularization
in the context of these neural networks,
cause once you put L2 regularization,
remember, on your,
on the weights of your network,
that's going to drive all the parameters towards zero.
And maybe your standard convolutional architecture
is driving towards zero.
Maybe it doesn't make sense.
But in the context of a residual network,
if you drive all the parameters towards zero,
that's kind of encouraging the model
to not use layers that it doesn't need,
because it will just drive those,
the residual blocks towards the identity,
whether or not needed for classification.
The other really useful property of these residual networks
has to do with the gradient flow in the backward paths.
If you remember what happens at these addition gates
in the backward pass,
when upstream gradient is coming in
through an addition gate,
then it will split
and fork along these two different paths.
So then, when upstream gradient comes in,
it'll take one path through these convolutional blocks,
but it will also have a direct connection of the gradient
through this residual connection.
So then when you look at,
when you imagine stacking many of these
residual blocks on top of each other,
and our network ends up with hundreds of,
potentially hundreds of layers.
Then, these residual connections
give a sort of gradient super highway
for gradients to flow backward
through the entire network.
And this allows it to train much easier
and much faster.
And actually allows these things to converge
reasonably well,
even when the model is potentially hundreds of layers deep.
And this idea of managing gradient flow in your models
is actually super important everywhere in machine learning.
And super prevalent in recurrent networks as well.
So we'll definitely revisit this idea of gradient flow
later in today's lecture.
So then, we kind of also saw a couple other more exotic,
more recent CNN architectures last time,
including DenseNet and FractalNet,
and once you think about these architectures
in terms of gradient flow,
they make a little bit more sense.
These things like DenseNet and FractalNet
are adding these additional shortcut
or identity connections inside the model.
And if you think about what happens
in the backwards pass for these models,
these additional funny topologies
are basically providing direct paths
for gradients to flow
from the loss at the end of the network
more easily into all the different layers of the network.
So I think that,
again, this idea of managing gradient flow properly
in your CNN Architectures
is something that we've really seen
a lot more in the last couple of years.
And will probably see more moving forward
as more exotic architectures are invented.
We also saw this kind of nice plot,
plotting performance of
the number of flops versus the number of parameters
versus the run time of these various models.
And there's some interesting characteristics
that you can dive in and see from this plot.
One idea is that VGG and AlexNet
have a huge number of parameters,
and these parameters actually come
almost entirely from the fully connected layers
of the models.
So AlexNet has something like roughly 62 million parameters,
and if you look at that last fully connected layer,
the final fully connected layer in AlexNet
is going from an activation volume of six by six by 256
into this fully connected vector of 496.
So if you imagine what the weight matrix
needs to look like at that layer,
the weight matrix is gigantic.
It's number of entries is six by six,
six times six times 256 times 496.
And if you multiply that out,
you see that that single layer
has 38 million parameters.
So more than half of the parameters
of the entire AlexNet model
are just sitting in that last fully connected layer.
And if you add up all the parameters
in just the fully connected layers of AlexNet,
including these other fully connected layers,
you see something like 59 of the 62 million
parameters in AlexNet
are sitting in these fully connected layers.
So then when we move other architectures,
like GoogLeNet and ResNet,
they do away with a lot of these large
fully connected layers
in favor of global average pooling
at the end of the network.
And this allows these networks to really cut,
these nicer architectures,
to really cut down the parameter count
in these architectures.
So that was kind of our brief recap
of the CNN architectures that we saw last lecture,
and then today,
we're going to move to
one of my favorite topics to talk about,
which is recurrent neural networks.
So, so far in this class,
we've seen, what I like to think of
as kind of a vanilla feed forward network,
all of our network architectures have this flavor,
where we receive some input
and that input is a fixed size object,
like an image or vector.
That input is fed through some set of hidden layers
and produces a single output,
like a classifications,
like a set of classifications scores
over a set of categories.
But in some context in machine learning,
we want to have more flexibility
in the types of data that our models can process.
So once we move to this idea of recurrent neural networks,
we have a lot more opportunities
to play around with the types of input and output data
that our networks can handle.
So once we have recurrent neural networks,
we can do what we call these one to many models.
Or where maybe our input is some object of fixed size,
like an image,
but now our output is a sequence of variable length,
such as a caption.
Where different captions
might have different numbers of words,
so our output needs to be variable in length.
We also might have many to one models,
where our input could be variably sized.
This might be something like a piece of text,
and we want to say what is the sentiment of that text,
whether it's positive or negative in sentiment.
Or in a computer vision context,
you might imagine taking as input a video,
and that video might have a variable number of frames.
And now we want to read this entire video
of potentially variable length.
And then at the end,
make a classification decision
about maybe what kind of activity or action
is going on in that video.
We also have a, we might also have problems
where we want both the inputs
and the output to be variable in length.
We might see something like this
in machine translation,
where our input is some, maybe, sentence in English,
which could have a variable length,
and our output is maybe some sentence in French,
which also could have a variable length.
And crucially, the length of the English sentence
might be different from the length of the French sentence.
So we need some models that have the capacity
to accept both variable length sequences
on the input and on the output.
Finally, we might also consider problems where
our input is variably length,
like something like a video sequence
with a variable number of frames.
And now we want to make a decision
for each element of that input sequence.
So in the context of videos,
that might be making some classification decision
along every frame of the video.
And recurrent neural networks
are this kind of general paradigm
for handling variable sized sequence data
that allow us to pretty naturally capture
all of these different types of setups in our models.
So recurring neural networks are actually important,
even for some problems that have a fixed size input
and a fixed size output.
Recurrent neural networks can still be pretty useful.
So in this example,
we might want to do, for example,
sequential processing of our input.
So here, we're receiving a fixed size input
like an image,
and we want to make a classification decision
about, like, what number is being shown in this image?
But now, rather than just doing a single feed forward pass
and making the decision all at once,
this network is actually looking around the image
and taking various glimpses of different parts of the image.
And then after making some series of glimpses,
then it makes its final decision
as to what kind of number is present.
So here, we had one,
So here, even though our input and outputs,
our input was an image,
and our output was a classification decision,
even this context,
this idea of being able to handle
variably length processing with recurrent neural networks
can lead to some really interesting types of models.
There's a really cool paper that I like
that applied this same type of idea
to generating new images.
Where now, we want the model to synthesize brand new images
that look kind of like the images it saw in training,
and we can use a recurrent neural network architecture
to actually paint these output images
sort of one piece at a time in the output.
You can see that,
even though our output is this fixed size image,
we can have these models that are working over time
to compute parts of the output one at a time sequentially.
And we can use recurrent neural networds
for that type of setup as well.
So after this sort of cool pitch
about all these cool things that RNNs can do,
you might wonder, like what exactly are these things?
So in general, a recurrent neural network
is this little, has this little recurrent core cell
and it will take some input x,
feed that input into the RNN,
and that RNN has some internal hidden state,
and that internal hidden state will be updated
every time that the RNN reads a new input.
And that internal hidden state
will be then fed back to the model
the next time it reads an input.
And frequently, we will want our RNN"s
to also produce some output at every time step,
so we'll have this pattern where it will read an input,
update its hidden state,
and then produce an output.
So then the question is
what is the functional form of this recurrence relation
that we're computing?
So inside this little green RNN block,
we're computing some recurrence relation,
with a function f.
So this function f will depend on some weights, w.
It will accept the previous hidden state, h t - 1,
as well as the input at the current state, x t,
and this will output
the next hidden state, or the updated hidden state,
that we call h t.
And now,
then as we read the next input,
this hidden state,
this new hidden state, h t,
will then just be passed into the same function
as we read the next input, x t plus one.
And now, if we wanted to produce some output
at every time step of this network,
we might attach some additional fully connected layers
that read in this h t at every time step.
And make that decision based
on the hidden state at every time step.
And one thing to note is that
we use the same function, f w,
and the same weights, w,
at every time step of the computation.
So then kind of the simplest function form
that you can imagine
is what we call this vanilla recurrent neural network.
So here, we have this same functional form
from the previous slide,
where we're taking in our previous hidden state
and our current input
and we need to produce the next hidden state.
And the kind of simplest thing you might imagine
is that we have some weight matrix, w x h,
that we multiply against the input, x t,
as well as another weight matrix, w h h,
that we multiply against the previous hidden state.
So we make these two multiplications
against our two states,
add them together,
and squash them through a tanh,
so we get some kind of non linearity in the system.
You might be wondering why we use a tanh here
and not some other type of non-linearity?
After all that we've said negative
about tanh's in previous lectures,
and I think we'll return a little bit to that
later on when we talk about
more advanced architectures, like lstm.
So then, this,
So then, in addition in this architecture,
if we wanted to produce some y t at every time step,
you might have another weight matrix, w,
you might have another weight matrix
that accepts this hidden state
and then transforms it to some y
to produce maybe some class score predictions
at every time step.
And when I think about recurrent neural networks,
I kind of think about, you can also,
you can kind of think of recurrent neural networks
in two ways.
One is this concept of having a hidden state
that feeds back at itself, recurrently.
But I find that picture a little bit confusing.
And sometimes, I find it clearer
to think about unrolling this computational graph
for multiple time steps.
And this makes the data flow of the hidden states
and the inputs and the outputs and the weights
maybe a little bit more clear.
So then at the first time step,
we'll have some initial hidden state h zero.
This is usually initialized to zeros for most context,
in most contexts, an then we'll have some input, x t.
This initial hidden state, h zero,
and our current input, x t,
will go into our f w function.
This will produce our next hidden state, h one.
And then, we'll repeat this process
when we receive the next input.
So now our current h one and our x one,
will go into that same f w,
to produce our next output, h two.
And this process will repeat over and over again,
as we consume all of the input, x ts,
in our sequence of inputs.
And now, one thing to note, is that
we can actually make this even more explicit
and write the w matrix in our computational graph.
And here you can see that
we're re-using the same w matrix
at every time step of the computation.
So now every time that we have this little f w block,
it's receiving a unique h and a unique x,
but all of these blocks are taking the same w.
And if you remember,
we talked about how gradient flows in back propagation,
when you re-use the same,
when you re-use the same node multiple times
in a computational graph,
then remember during the backward pass,
you end up summing the gradients
into the w matrix
when you're computing a d los d w.
So, if you kind of think about
the back propagation for this model,
then you'll have a separate gradient for w
flowing from each of those time steps,
and then the final gradient for w
will be the sum of all of those
individual per time step gradiants.
We can also write to this y t explicitly
in this computational graph.
So then, this output, h t, at every time step
might feed into some other little neural network
that can produce a y t,
which might be some class scores, or something like that,
at every time step.
We can also make the loss more explicit.
So in many cases, you might imagine producing,
you might imagine that you have some ground truth label
at every time step of your sequence,
and then you'll compute some loss,
some individual loss,
at every time step of
these outputs, y t's.
And this loss might,
it will frequently be something like soft max loss,
in the case where you have, maybe,
a ground truth label at every time step of the sequence.
And now the final loss for the entire,
for this entire training stop,
will be the sum of these individual losses.
So now, we had a scaler loss at every time step?
And we just summed them up to get our final
scaler loss at the top of the network.
And now, if you think about,
again, back propagation through this thing,
we need, in order to train the model,
we need to compute the gradient
of the loss with respect to w.
So, we'll have loss flowing from that final loss
into each of these time steps.
And then each of those time steps
will compute a local gradient on the weights, w,
which will all then be summed to give us our final
gradient for the weights, w.
Now if we have a, sort of, this many to one situation,
where maybe we want to do something like sentiment analysis,
then we would typically make that decision
based on the final hidden state of this network.
Because this final hidden state
kind of summarizes all of the context
from the entire sequence.
Also, if we have a kind of a one to many situation,
where we want to receive a fix sized input
and then produce a variably sized output.
Then you'll commonly use that fixed size input
to initialize, somehow,
the initial hidden state of the model,
and now the recurrent network will tick
for each cell in the output.
And now, as you produce your variably sized output,
you'll unroll the graph for each element in the output.
So this, when we talk about the sequence to sequence models
where you might do something like machine translation,
where you take a variably sized input
and a variably sized output.
You can think of this as a combination
of the many to one,
plus a one to many.
So, we'll kind of proceed in two stages,
what we call an encoder and a decoder.
So if you're the encoder,
we'll receive the variably sized input,
which might be your sentence in English,
and then summarize that entire sentence
using the final hidden state of the encoder network.
And now we're in this many to one situation
where we've summarized this entire variably sized input
in this single vector,
and now, we have a second decoder network,
which is a one to many situation,
which will input that single vector
summarizing the input sentence
and now produce this variably sized output,
which might be your sentence in another language.
And now in this variably sized output,
we might make some predictions at every time step,
maybe about what word to use.
And you can imagine kind of training this entire thing
by unrolling this computational graph
summing the losses at the output sequence
and just performing back propagation, as usual.
So as a bit of a concrete example,
one thing that we frequently use
recurrent neural networks for,
is this problem called language modeling.
So in the language modeling problem,
we want to read some sequence of,
we want to have our network, sort of, understand
how to produce natural language.
So in the, so this, this might happen at the character level
where our model will produce characters one at a time.
This might also happen at the word level
where our model will produce words one at a time.
But in a very simple example,
you can imagine this character level language model
where we want,
where the network will read some sequence of characters
and then it needs to predict,
what will the next character be in this stream of text?
So in this example,
we have this very small vocabulary of four letters,
h, e, l, and o, and we have this example training sequence
of the word hello, h, e, l, l, o.
So during training,
when we're training this language model,
we will feed the characters of this training sequence
as inputs, as x ts, to out input of our,
we'll feed the characters of our training sequence,
these will be the x ts that we feed in as the inputs
to our recurrent neural network.
And then, each of these inputs,
it's a letter,
and we need to figure out a way
to represent letters in our network.
So what we'll typically do is figure out
what is our total vocabulary.
In this case, our vocabulary has four elements.
And each letter will be represented by a vector
that has zeros in every slot but one,
and a one for the slot in the vocabulary
corresponding to that letter.
In this little example,
since our vocab has the four letters, h, e, l, o,
then our input sequence,
the h is represented by a four element vector
with a one in the first slot
and zero's in the other three slots.
And we use the same sort of pattern
to represent all the different letters
in the input sequence.
Now, during this forward pass
of what this network is doing,
at the first time step,
it will receive the input letter h.
That will go into the first RNN,
to the RNN cell,
and then we'll produce this output, y t,
which is the network making predictions
about for each letter in the vocabulary,
which letter does it think is most likely
going to come next.
In this example,
the correct output letter was e
because our training sequence was hello,
but the model is actually predicting,
I think it's actually
predicting o as the most likely letter.
So in this case, this prediction was wrong
and we would use softmaxt loss
to quantify our unhappiness with these predictions.
The next time step,
we would feed in the second letter
in the training sequence, e,
and this process will repeat.
We'll now represent e as a vector.
Use that input vector together
with the previous hidden state
to produce a new hidden state
and now use the second hidden state
to, again, make predictions
over every letter in the vocabulary.
In this case, because our training sequence was hello,
after the letter e,
we want our model to predict l.
In this case,
our model may have very low predictions
for the letter l, so we would incur high loss.
And you kind of repeat this process over and over,
and if you train this model with many different sequences,
then eventually it should learn
how to predict the next character in a sequence
based on the context of all the previous characters
that it's seen before.
And now, if you think about what happens at test time,
after we train this model,
one thing that we might want to do with it
is a sample from the model,
and actually use this trained neural network model
to synthesize new text
that kind of looks similar in spirit
to the text that it was trained on.
The way that this will work
is we'll typically see the model
with some input prefix of text.
In this case, the prefix is just the single letter h,
and now we'll feed that letter h
through the first time step of our recurrent neural network.
It will product this distribution of scores
over all the characters in the vocabulary.
Now, at training time, we'll use these scores
to actually sample from it.
So we'll use a softmaxt function
to convert those scores into a probability distribution
and th