- Good morning.
So, it's 12:03 so, I want to get started.
Welcome to Lecture 12, of CS-231N.
Today we are going to talk about Visualizing and Understanding
convolutional networks.
This is always a super fun lecture to give
because we get to look a lot of pretty pictures.
So, it's, it's one of my favorites.
As usual a couple administrative things.
So, hopefully your projects are all going well,
because as a reminder your milestones
are due on Canvas tonight.
It is Canvas, right?
Okay, so want to double check, yeah.
Due on Canvas tonight, we are working on
furiously grading your midterms.
So, we'll hope to have those midterms grades to you back
by on grade scope this week.
So, I know that was little confusion,
you all got registration email's for grade scope
probably in the last week.
Something like that, we start couple of questions on piazo.
So, we've decided to use grade scope to grade the midterms.
So, don't be confused, if you get some emails about that.
Another reminder is that assignment three
was released last week on Friday.
It will be due, a week from this Friday, on the 26th.
This is, an assignment three,
is almost entirely brand new this year.
So, it we apologize for taking a little bit longer than
expected to get it out.
But I think it's super cool.
A lot of that stuff, we'll talk about in today's lecture.
You'll actually be implementing on your assignment.
And for the assignment, you'll get the choice of either
Pi torch or tensure flow.
To work through these different examples.
So, we hope that's really useful experience for you guys.
We also saw a lot of activity
on HyperQuest over the weekend.
So that's, that's really awesome.
The leader board went up yesterday.
It seems like you guys are really trying to battle it out
to show off your deep learning
neural network training skills.
So that's super cool.
And we because due to the high interest
in HyperQuest and due to the conflicts with the,
with the Milestones submission time.
We decided to extend the deadline
for extra credit through Sunday.
So, anyone who does at least 12 runs on HyperQuest
by Sunday will get little bit of extra credit in the class.
Also those of you who are, at the top of leader board
doing really well, will get may be little bit
extra, extra credit.
So, I thanks for participating we got lot of
interest and that was really cool.
Final reminder is about the poster session.
So, we have the poster session will be on June 6th.
That date is finalized,
I think that, I don't remember the exact time.
But it is June 6th.
So that, we have some questions
about when exactly that poster session is
for those of you who are traveling
at the end of quarter or starting internships
or something like that.
So, it will be June 6th.
Any questions on the admin notes.
No, totally clear.
So, last time we talked.
So, last time we had a pretty
jam packed lecture, when we talked about lot of different
computer vision tasks, as a reminder.
We talked about semantic segmentation
which is this problem, where you want to sign labels
to every pixel in the input image.
But does not differentiate the
object instances in those images.
We talked about classification plus localization.
Where in addition to a class label
you also want to draw a box
or perhaps several boxes in the image.
Where the distinction here is that,
in a classification plus localization setup.
You have some fix number of objects that you are looking for
So, we also saw that this type of paradigm
can be applied to the things like pose recognition.
Where you want to regress to different numbers of joints
in the human body.
We also talked about the object detection
where you start with some fixed
set of category labels that you are interested in.
Like dogs and cats.
And then the task is to draw a boxes around
every instance of those objects
that appear in the input image.
And object detection is really distinct from
classification plus localization
because with object detection, we don't know
ahead of time, how many object instances
we're looking for in the image.
And we saw that there's this whole family of methods
based on RCNN, Fast RCNN and faster RCNN,
as well as the single shot detection methods
for addressing this problem of object detection.
Then finally we talked pretty briefly about
instance segmentation, which is kind of combining
aspects of a semantic segmentation and object detection
where the goal is to detect all the instances
of the categories we care about,
as well as label the pixels belonging to each instance.
So, in this case, we detected two dogs and one cat
and for each of those instances we wanted
to label all the pixels.
So, these are we kind of covered a lot last lecture
but those are really interesting and exciting problems
that you guys might consider to
using in parts of your projects.
But today we are going to shift gears a little bit
and ask another question.
Which is, what's really going on
inside convolutional networks.
We've seen by this point in the class
how to train convolutional networks.
How to stitch up different types of architectures
to attack different problems.
But one question that you might have had in your mind,
is what exactly is going on inside these networks?
How did they do the things that they do?
What kinds of features are they looking for?
And all this source of related questions.
So, so far we've sort of seen
ConvNets as a little bit of a black box.
Where some input image of raw pixels
is coming in on one side.
It goes to the many layers of convulsion
and pooling in different sorts of transformations.
And on the outside, we end up with some set of class scores
or some types of understandable interpretable output.
Such as class scores or bounding box positions
or labeled pixels or something like that.
But the question is.
What are all these other layers in the middle doing?
What kinds of things in the input image
are they looking for?
And can we try again intuition for.
How ConvNets are working?
What types of things in the image they are looking for?
And what kinds of techniques do we have
for analyzing this internals of the network?
So, one relatively simple thing is the first layer.
So, we've seen, we've talked about this before.
But recalled that, the first convolutional layer
consists of a filters that,
so, for example in AlexNet.
The first convolutional layer consists
of a number of convolutional filters.
Each convolutional of filter has shape 3 by 11 by 11.
And these convolutional filters gets slid
over the input image.
We take inner products between some chunk of the image.
And the weights of the convolutional filter.
And that gives us our output of the
at, at after that first convolutional layer.
So, in AlexNet then we have 64 of these filters.
But now in the first layer because we are taking
in a direct inner product between the weights
of the convolutional layer
and the pixels of the image.
We can get some since for what these filters are looking for
by simply visualizing the learned weights of these filters
as images themselves.
So, for each of those 11 by 11 by 3 filters
in AlexNet, we can just visualize that filter
as a little 11 by 11 image with a three channels
give you the red, green and blue values.
And then because there are 64 of these filters
we just visualize 64 little 11 by 11 images.
And we can repeat... So we have shown here at the.
So, these are filters taken from the prechain models,
in the pi torch model zoo.
And we are looking at the convolutional filters.
The weights of the convolutional filters.
at the first layer of AlexNet, ResNet-18,
ResNet-101 and DenseNet-121.
And you can see, kind of what all these layers
what this filters looking for.
You see the lot of things looking for oriented edges.
Likes bars of light and dark.
At various angles, in various angles and various positions
in the input, we can see opposing colors.
Like this are green and pink.
opposing colors or this orange and blue opposing colors.
So, this, this kind of connects back to what we
talked about with Hugh and Wiesel.
All the way in the first lecture.
That remember the human visual system
is known to the detect things like oriented edges.
At the very early layers of the human visual system.
And it turns out of that these convolutional networks
tend to do something, somewhat similar.
At their first convolutional layers as well.
And what's kind of interesting is that
pretty much no matter what type of architecture you hook up
or whatever type of training data you are train it on.
You almost always get the first layers of your.
The first convolutional weights of any pretty much
any convolutional network looking at images.
Ends up looking something like this
with oriented edges and opposing colors.
Looking at that input image.
But this really only, sorry what was that question?
Yes, these are showing the learned weights
of the first convolutional layer.
Oh, so that the question is.
Why does visualizing the weights of the filters?
Tell you what the filter is looking for.
So this intuition comes from sort of template matching
and inner products.
That if you imagine you have some, some template vector.
And then you imagine you compute a scaler output
by taking inner product between your template vector
and some arbitrary piece of data.
Then, the input which maximizes that activation.
Under a norm constraint on the input
is exactly when those two vectors match up.
So, in that since that, when, whenever you're taking
inner products, the thing causes an inner product
to excite maximally
is a copy of the thing you are taking an inner product with.
So, that, that's why we can actually visualize these weights
and that, why that shows us,
what this first layer is looking for.
So, for these networks the first layers always
was a convolutional layer.
So, generally whenever you are looking at image.
Whenever you are thinking about image data
and training convolutional networks,
you generally put a convolutional layer
at the first, at the first stop.
Yeah, so the question is,
can we do this same type of procedure
in the middle open network.
That's actually the next slide.
So, good anticipation.
So, if we do, if we draw this exact same
visualization for the intermediate convolutional layers.
It's actually a lot less interpretable.
So, this is, this is performing exact same visualization.
So, remember for this using the tiny ConvNets demo network
that's running on the course website
whenever you go there.
So, for that network,
the first layer is 7 by 7 convulsion 16 filters.
So, after the top visualizing the first layer weights
for this network just like we saw in a previous slide.
But now at the second layer weights.
After we do a convulsion then there's some relu
and some other non-linearity perhaps.
But the second convolutional layer,
now receives the 16 channel input.
And does 7 by 7 convulsion with 20 convolutional filters.
And we've actually,
so the problem is that you can't really visualize
these directly as images.
So, you can try, so, here if you
this 16 by, so the input is this has 16 dimensions in depth.
And we have these convolutional filters,
each convolutional filter is 7 by 7,
and is extending along the full depth
so has 16 elements.
Then we've 20 such of these convolutional filters,
that are producing the output planes of the next layer.
But the problem here is that we can't, looking at the,
looking directly at the weights
of these filters, doesn't really tell us much.
So, we, that's really done here is that,
now for this single 16 by 7 by 7 convolutional filter.
We can spread out those 167 by 7 planes of the filter
into a 167 by 7 grayscale images.
So, that's what we've done.
Up here, which is these little tiny gray scale images here
show us what is, what are the weights
in one of the convolutional filters of the second layer.
And now, because there are 20 outputs from this layer.
Then this second convolutional layer, has 2o such of these
16 by 16 or 16 by 7 by 7 filters.
So if we visualize the weights
of those convolutional filters
as images, you can see that there are some
kind of spacial structures here.
But it doesn't really give you good intuition
for what they are looking at.
Because these filters are not looking, are not connected
directly to the input image.
Instead recall that the second layer convolutional filters
are connected to the output of the first layer.
So, this is giving visualization of,
what type of activation pattern after the first
convulsion, would cause the second layer convulsion
to maximally activate.
But, that's not very interpretable
because we don't have a good sense
for what those first layer convulsions look like
in terms of image pixels.
So we'll need to develop some slightly more fancy technique
to get a sense for what is going on
in the intermediate layers.
Question in the back.
Yeah. So the question is that
for... all the visualization on this on the previous slide.
We've had the scale the weights to the zero to 255 range.
So in practice those weights could be unbounded.
They could have any range.
But to get nice visualizations we need to scale those.
These visualizations also do not take
in to account the bias is in these layers.
So you should keep that in mind
when and not take these HEPS visualizations
to, to literally.
Now at the last layer
remember when we looking at the last layer
of convolutional network.
We have these maybe 1000 class scores
that are telling us what are the predicted scores
for each of the classes in our training data set
and immediately before the last layer
we often have some fully connected layer.
In the case of Alex net
we have some 4096- dimensional features representation
of our image that then gets fed into that final
our final layer to predict our final class scores.
And one another, another kind of route
for tackling the problem of visual, visualizing
and understanding ConvNets
is to try to understand what's happening at the last layer
of a convolutional network.
So what we can do
is how to take some, some data set of images
run a bunch of, run a bunch of images
through our trained convolutional network
and recorded that 4096 dimensional vector
for each of those images.
And now go through and try to figure out
and visualize that last layer, that last hidden layer
rather than those rather than the first convolutional layer.
So, one thing you might imagine is,
is trying a nearest neighbor approach.
So, remember, way back in the second lecture
we saw this graphic on the left
where we, where we had a nearest neighbor classifier.
Where we were looking at nearest neighbors in pixels
space between CIFAR 10 images.
And then when you look at nearest neighbors
in pixel space between CIFAR 10 images
you see that you pull up images
that looks quite similar to the query image.
So again on the left column here is some CIFAR 10 image
from the CIFAR 10 data set
and then these, these next five columns
are showing the nearest neighbors in pixel space
to those test set images.
And so for example
this white dog that you see here,
it's nearest neighbors are in pixel space
are these kinds of white blobby things
that may, may or may not be dogs,
but at least the raw pixels
of the image are quite similar.
So now we can do the same type of visualization
computing and visualizing these nearest neighbor images.
But rather than computing
the nearest neighbors in pixel space,
instead we can compute nearest neighbors
in that 4096 dimensional feature space.
Which is computed by the convolutional network.
So here on the right
we see some examples.
So this, this first column shows us
some examples of images from the test set
of image that... Of the image net classification data set
and now the, these subsequent columns show us
nearest neighbors to those test set images
in the 4096, in the 4096th dimensional features space
computed by Alex net.
And you can see here that this is quite different
from the pixel space nearest neighbors,
because the pixels are often quite different.
between the image in it's nearest neighbors
and feature space.
However, the semantic content of those images
tends to be similar in this feature space.
So for example, if you look at this second layer
the query image is this elephant
standing on the left side of the image
with a screen grass behind him.
and now one of these, one of these...
it's third nearest neighbor in the tough set
is actually an elephant standing
on the right side of the image.
So this is really interesting.
Because between this elephant standing on the left
and this element stand, elephant standing on the right
the pixels between those two images
are almost entirely different.
However, in the feature space
which is learned by the network
those two images and that being very close to each other.
Which means that somehow this, this last their features
is capturing some of those semantic content of these images.
That's really cool and really exciting
and, and in general looking
at these kind of nearest neighbor visualizations
is really quick and easy way to visualize
something about what's going on here.
Yes. So the question is that
through the... the standard supervised learning procedure
for classific training, classification network
There's nothing in the loss
encouraging these features to be close together.
So that, that's true.
It just kind of a happy accident
that they end up being close to each other.
Because we didn't tell the network during training
these features should be close.
However there are sometimes people do train networks
using things called either contrastive loss
or a triplet loss.
Which actually explicitly make...
assumptions and constraints on the network
such that those last their features
end up having some metric space interpretation.
But Alex net at least was not trained specifically for that.
The question is, what is the nearest...
What is this nearest neighbor thing
have to do at the last layer?
So we're taking this image
we're running it through the network
and then the, the second to last
like the last hidden layer of the network
is of 4096th dimensional vector.
Because there's this, this is...
This is there, there are these fully connected layers
at the end of the network.
So we are doing is...
We're writing down that 4096th dimensional vector
for each of the images
and then we are computing nearest neighbors
according to that 4096th dimensional vector.
Which is computed by, computed by the network.
Maybe, maybe we can chat offline.
So another, another, another
another angle that we might have
for visualizing what's going on in this last layer
is by some concept of dimensionality reduction.
So those of you who have taken CS229 for example
you've seen something like PCA.
Which let's you take some high dimensional representation
like these 4096th dimensional features
and then compress it down to two-dimensions.
So then you can visualize that feature space more directly.
So, Principle Component Analysis or PCA
is kind of one way to do that.
But there's real another really powerful algorithm
called t-SNE.
Standing for t-distributed stochastic neighbor embeddings.
Which is slightly more powerful method.
Which is a non-linear dimensionality reduction method
that people in deep often use for visualizing features.
So here as an, just an example of what t-SNE can do.
This visualization here is, is showing
a t-SNE dimensionality reduction on the emnest data set.
So, emnest remember is this date set
of hand written digits between zero and nine.
Each image is a gray scale image
20... 28 by 28 gray scale image
and now we're... So that
Now we've, we've used t-SNE
to take that 28 times 28 dimensional features space
of the raw pixels for m-nest
and now compress it down to two- dimensions
ans then visualize each of those m-nest digits
in this compress two-dimensional representation
and when you do, when you run t-SNE
on the raw pixels and m-nest
You can see these natural clusters appearing.
Which corresponds to the, the digits of these m-nest
of, of these m-nest data set.
So now we can do a similar type of visualization.
Where we apply this t-SNE dimensionality reduction technique
to the features from the last layer
of our trained image net classifier.
So...To be a little bit more concrete here
what we've done
is that we take, a large set of images
we run them off convolutional network.
We record that final 4096th dimensional feature vector
for, from the last layer of each of those images.
Which gives us large collection
of 4096th dimensional vectors.
Now we apply t-SNE dimensionality reduction
to compute, sort of compress that 4096the dimensional
features space down into a two-dimensional feature space
and now we, layout a grid in that
compressed two-dimensional feature space
and visualize what types of images appear
at each location in the grid
in this two-dimensional feature space.
So by doing this you get some very close rough sense
of what the geometry
of this learned feature space looks like.
So these images are little bit hard to see.
So I'd encourage you to check out
the high resolution versions online.
But at least maybe on the left you can see that
there's sort of one cluster in the bottom here
of, of green things, is a different kind of flowers
and there's other types of clusters
for different types of dog breeds
and another types of animals and, and locations.
So there's sort of discontinuous semantic notion
in this feature space.
Which we can explore by looking through
this t-SNE dimensionality reduction
version of the, of the features.
Is there question?
Yeah. So the basic idea is that we're
we, we have an image
so now we end up with three different pieces
of information about each image.
We have the pixels of the image.
We have the 4096th dimensional vector.
Then we use t-SNE to convert the 4096th dimensional vector
into a two-dimensional coordinate
and then we take the original pixels of the image
and place that at the two-dimensional coordinate
corresponding to the dimensionality reduced version
of the 4096th dimensional feature.
Yeah, little bit involved here.
Question in the front.
The question is
Roughly how much variants do these two-dimension explain?
Well, I'm not sure of the exact number
and I get little bit muddy
when you're talking about t-SNE,
because it's a non-linear
dimensionality reduction technique.
So, I'd have to look offline
and I'm not sure of exactly how much it explains.
Question?
Question is, can you do the same analysis
of upper layers of the network?
And yes, you can. But no,
I don't have those visualizations here. Sorry.
Question?
The question is, Shouldn't we have overlaps
of images once we do this dimensionality reduction?
And yes, of course, you would.
So this is just kind of taking a,
nearest neighbor in our, in our regular grid
and then picking an image close to that grid point.
So, so... they, yeah.
this is not showing you the kind of density
in different parts of the feature space.
So that's, that's another thing to look at
and again at the link you, there's a couple more
visualizations of this nature that,
that address that a little bit.
Okay. So another, another thing
that you can do for some of these intermediate features
is, so we talked a couple of slides ago
that visualizing the weights of these intermediate layers
is not so interpretable.
But actually visualizing the activation maps of those
intermediate layers
is kind of interpretable in some cases.
So for, so I, again an example of Alex Net.
Remember the, the conv5 layers of Alex Net.
Gives us this 128 by...
The for...The conv5 features for any image
is now 128 by 13 by 13 dimensional tensor.
But we can think of that
as 128 different
13 by 132-D grids.
So now we can actually go and visualize
each of those 13 by 13 elements slices
of the feature map as a grayscale image
and this gives us some sense for what types of things
in the input are each of those features
in that convolutional layer looking for.
So this is a, a really cool interactive tool
by Jason Yasenski you can just download.
So it's run, so I don't have the video,
it has a video on his website.
But it's running a convolutional network
on the inputs stream of webcam
and then visualizing in real time
each of those slices of that intermediate feature map
give you a sense of what it's looking for
and you can see that, so here the input image
is this, this picture up in, settings...
of this picture of a person in front of the camera
and most of these intermediate features
are kind of noisy, not much going on.
But there's a, but there's this one highlighted
intermediate feature
where that is also shown larger here
that seems that it's activating
on the portions of the feature map
corresponding to the person's face.
Which is really interesting
and that kind of, suggests that maybe this,
this particular slice of the feature map
of this layer of this particular network
is maybe looking for human faces or something like that.
Which is kind of a nice, kind of a nice
and cool finding.
Question?
The question is, Are the black activations dead relu's?
So you got to be... a little careful with terminology.
We usually say dead relu to mean
something that's dead over the entire training data set.
Here I would say that it's a relu, that, it's not active
for this particular input.
Question?
The question is, If there's no humans in image net
how can it recognize a human face?
There definitely are humans in image net
I don't think it's, it's one of the cat...
I don't think it's one of the thousand categories
for the classification challenge.
But people definitely appear in a lot of these images
and that can be useful signal for detecting
other types of things.
So that's actually kind of nice results
because that shows that, it's sort of can learn features
that are useful for the classification task at hand.
That are even maybe a little bit different
from the explicit classification task
that we told it to perform.
So it's actually really cool results.
Okay, question?
So at each layer in the convolutional network
our input image is of three, it's like 3 by 224 by 224
and then it goes through many stages of convolution.
And then, it, after each convolutional layer
is some three dimensional chunk of numbers.
Which are the outputs from that layer
of the convolutional network.
And that into the entire three dimensional chunk of numbers
which are the output of the previous convolutional layer,
we call, we call, like an activation volume
and then one of those, one of those slices
is a, it's an activation map.
So the question is, If the image is K by K
will the activation map be K by K?
Not always because there can be sub sampling
due to pool, straight convolution and pooling.
But in general, the, the size of each activation map
will be linear in the size of the input image.
So another, another kind of useful thing we can do
for visualizing intermediate features is...
Visualizing what types of patches from input images
cause maximal activation in different,
different features, different neurons.
So what we've done here is that, we pick...
Maybe again the con five layer from Alex Net?
And remember each of these activation volumes
at the con, at the con five in Alex net gives us
a 128 by 13 by 13 chunk of numbers.
Then we'll pick one of those 128 channels.
Maybe channel 17
and now what we'll do is run many images
through this convolutional network.
And then, for each of those images
record the con five features
and then look at the...
Right, so, then, then look at the, the...
The parts of that 17th feature map
that are maximally activated over our data set of images.
And now, because again this is a convolutional layer
each of those neurons in the convolutional layer
has some small receptive field in the input.
Each of those neurons is not looking at the whole image.
They're only looking at the sub set of the image.