- Okay so welcome to CS 231N Lecture three.
Today we're going to talk about loss functions and optimization
but as usual, before we get to the main content
of the lecture, there's a couple administrative things
to talk about.
So the first thing is that assignment one has been released.
You can find the link up on the website.
And since we were a little bit late
in getting this assignment out to you guys,
we've decided to change the due date to Thursday,
April 20th at 11:59 p.m.,
this will give you a full two weeks from the assignment
release date to go and actually finish and work on it,
so we'll update the syllabus for this new due date
in a little bit later today.
And as a reminder, when you complete the assignment,
you should go turn in the final zip file on Canvas
so we can grade it and get your grades back as quickly
as possible.
So the next thing is always check out Piazza for interesting
administrative stuff.
So this week I wanted to highlight that we have several
example project ideas as a pinned post on Piazza.
So we went out and solicited example of project ideas
from various people in the Stanford community or affiliated
to Stanford, and they came up with some interesting
suggestions for projects that they might want students
in the class to work on.
So check out this pinned post on Piazza and if you want
to work on any of these projects, then feel free to contact
the project mentors directly about these things.
Aditionally we posted office hours on the course website,
this is a Google calendar, so this is something that people
have been asking about and now it's up there.
The final administrative note is about Google Cloud,
as a reminder, because we're supported by Google Cloud
in this class, we're able to give each of you an additional
$100 credit for Google Cloud to work on your assignments
and projects, and the exact details of how to redeem
that credit will go out later today, most likely on Piazza.
So if there's, I guess if there's no questions about
administrative stuff then we'll move on to course content.
Okay cool.
So recall from last time in lecture two,
we were really talking about the challenges of recognition
and trying to hone in on this idea
of a data-driven approach.
We talked about this idea of image classification,
talked about why it's hard, there's this semantic gap
between the giant grid of numbers that the computer sees
and the actual image that you see.
We talked about various challenges regarding this
around illumination, deformation, et cetera,
and why this is actually a really, really hard problem
even though it's super easy for people to do
with their human eyes and human visual system.
Then also recall last time we talked about the k-nearest
neighbor classifier as kind of a simple introduction
to this whole data-driven mindset.
We talked about the CIFAR-10 data set where you can see
an example of these images on the upper left here,
where CIFAR-10 gives you these 10 different categories,
airplane, automobile, whatnot,
and we talked about how the k-nearest neighbor classifier
can be used to learn decision boundaries
to separate these data points into classes
based on the training data.
This also led us to a discussion of the idea of cross
validation and setting hyper parameters by dividing
your data into train, validation and test sets.
Then also recall last time we talked about linear
classification as the first sort of building block
as we move toward neural networks.
Recall that the linear classifier is an example
of a parametric classifier where all of our knowledge
about the training data gets summarized
into this parameter matrix W that is set
during the process of training.
And this linear classifier recall is super simple,
where we're going to take the image and stretch it out
into a long vector.
So here the image is x and then we take that image
which might be 32 by 32 by 3 pixels, stretch it out
into a long column vector of 32 times 32
times 3 entries,
where the 32 and 32 are the height and width,
and the 3 give you the three color channels,
red, green, blue.
Then there exists some parameter matrix, W
which will take this long column vector
representing the image pixels, and convert this
and give you 10 numbers giving scores
for each of the 10 classes in the case of CIFAR-10.
Where we kind of had this interpretation
where larger values of those scores,
so a larger value for the cat class means the classifier
thinks that the cat is more likely for that image,
and lower values for maybe the dog or car class
indicate lower probabilities of those classes being present
in the image.
Also, so I think this point was a little bit unclear
last time that linear classification has this interpretation
as learning templates per class,
where if you look at the diagram on the lower left,
you think that, so for every pixel in the image,
and for every one of our 10 classes,
there exists some entry in this matrix W,
telling us how much does that pixel influence that class.
So that means that each of these rows in the matrix W
ends up corresponding to a template for the class.
And if we take those rows and unravel,
so each of those rows again corresponds
to a weighting between the values of,
between the pixel values of the image and that class,
so if we take that row and unravel it back into an image,
then we can visualize the learned template for each
of these classes.
We also had this interpretation of linear classification
as learning linear decision boundaries between pixels
in some high dimensional space where the dimensions
of the space correspond to the values of the pixel
intensity values of the image.
So this is kind of where we left off last time.
And so where we kind of stopped, where we ended up last
time is we got this idea of a linear classifier,
and we didn't talk about how to actually choose the W.
How to actually use the training data
to determine which value of W should be best.
So kind of where we stopped off at
is that for some setting of W, we can use this W
to come up with 10 with our class scores for any image.
So and some of these class scores might be better or worse.
So here in this simple example,
we've shown maybe just a training data set of three images
along with the 10 class scores predicted for some value of W
for those images.
And you can see that some of these scores are better
or worse than others.
So for example in the image on the left, if you look up,
it's actually a cat because you're a human
and you can tell these things,
but if we look at the assigned probabilities, cat,
well not probabilities but scores,
then the classifier maybe for this setting of W
gave the cat class a score of 2.9 for this image,
whereas the frog class gave 3.78.
So maybe the classifier is not doing not so good
on this image, that's bad, we wanted the true class
to be actually the highest class score,
whereas for some of these other examples, like the car
for example, you see that the automobile class
has a score of six which is much higher
than any of the others, so that's good.
And the frog, the predicted scores are maybe negative four,
which is much lower than all the other ones,
so that's actually bad.
So this is kind of a hand wavy approach,
just kind of looking at the scores and eyeballing
which ones are good and which ones are bad.
But to actually write algorithms about these things
and to actually to determine automatically which W
will be best, we need some way to quantify the badness
of any particular W.
And that's this function that takes in a W,
looks at the scores and then tells us how bad quantitatively
is that W, is something that we'll call a loss function.
And in this lecture we'll see a couple examples
of different loss functions that you can use for this image
classification problem.
So then once we've got this idea of a loss function,
this allows us to quantify for any given value of W,
how good or bad is it?
But then we actually need to find
and come up with an efficient procedure
for searching through the space of all possible Ws
and actually come up with what is the correct value
of W that is the least bad,
and this process will be an optimization procedure
and we'll talk more about that in this lecture.
So I'm going to shrink this example a little bit
because 10 classes is a little bit unwieldy.
So we'll kind of work with this tiny toy data set
of three examples and three classes going forward
in this lecture.
So again, in this example, the cat is maybe not so correctly
classified, the car is correctly classified, and the frog,
this setting of W got this frog image totally wrong,
because the frog score is much lower than others.
So to formalize this a little bit, usually when we talk
about a loss function, we imagine
that we have some training data set of xs and ys,
usually N examples of these where the xs are the inputs
to the algorithm in the image classification case,
the xs would be the actually pixel values of your images,
and the ys will be the things you want your algorithm
to predict, we usually call these the labels or the targets.
So in the case of image classification,
remember we're trying to categorize each image
for CIFAR-10 to one of 10 categories,
so the label y here will be an integer
between one and 10 or maybe between zero and nine
depending on what programming language you're using,
but it'll be an integer telling you
what is the correct category for each one of those images x.
And now our loss function will denote L_i to denote the,
so then we have this prediction function x
which takes in our example x and our weight matrix W
and makes some prediction for y,
in the case of image classification
these will be our 10 numbers.
Then we'll define some loss function L_i
which will take in the predicted scores
coming out of the function f
together with the true target or label Y
and give us some quantitative value for how bad
those predictions are for that training example.
And now the final loss L will be the average of these losses
summed over the entire data set over each of the N examples
in our data set.
So this is actually a very general formulation,
and actually extends even beyond image classification.
Kind of as we move forward and see other tasks,
other examples of tasks and deep learning,
the kind of generic setup is that for any task
you have some xs and ys and you want to write down
some loss function that quantifies exactly how happy
you are with your particular parameter settings W
and then you'll eventually search over the space of W
to find the W that minimizes the loss on your training data.
So as a first example of a concrete loss function
that is a nice thing to work with in image classification,
we'll talk about the multi-class SVM loss.
You may have seen the binary SVM, our support vector
machine in CS 229 and the multiclass SVM
is a generalization of that to handle multiple classes.
In the binary SVM case as you may have seen in 229,
you only had two classes, each example x
was going to be classified as either positive
or negative example,
but now we have 10 categories, so we need to generalize
this notion to handle multiple classes.
So this loss function has kind of a funny functional form,
so we'll walk through it in a bit more,
in quite a bit of detail over the next couple of slides.
But what this is saying is that the loss L_i
for any individual example, the way we'll compute it
is we're going to perform a sum over all of the categories, Y,
except for the true category, Y_i,
so we're going to sum over all the incorrect categories,
and then we're going to compare the score
of the correct category, and the score
of the incorrect category,
and now if the score for the correct category
is greater than the score of the incorrect category,
greater than the incorrect score by some safety margin
that we set to one, if that's the case that means that
the true score is much, or the score for the true category
is if it's much larger than any of the false categories,
then we'll get a loss of zero.
And we'll sum this up over all of the incorrect categories
for our image and this will give us our final loss
for this one example in the data set.
And again we'll take the average of this loss
over the whole training data set.
So this kind of like if then statement, like if the true
class score is much larger than the others,
this kind of if then formulation we often compactify
into this single max of zero S_j minus S_Yi plus one thing,
but I always find that notation a little bit confusing,
and it always helps me
to write it out in this sort of case based notation
to figure out exactly what the two cases are
and what's going on.
And by the way, this style of loss function
where we take max of zero and some other quantity
is often referred to as some type of a hinge loss,
and this name comes from the shape of the graph
when you go and plot it,
so here the x axis corresponds to the S_Yi,
that is the score of the true class for some training
example, and now the y axis is the loss,
and you can see that as the score for the true category
for this example increases, then the loss
will go down linearly
until we get to above this safety margin,
after which the loss will be zero
because we've already correctly classified this example.
So let's, oh, question?
- [Student] Sorry, in terms of notation
what is S underscore Yi?
Is that your right score?
- Yeah, so the question is
in terms of notation, what is S and what is SYI
in particular, so the Ss are the predicted scores
for the classes that are coming out of the classifier.
So if one is the cat class and two is the dog class then S1
and S2 would be the cat and dog scores respectively.
And remember we said that Yi was the category of the ground
truth label for the example which is some integer.
So then S sub Y sub i, sorry for the double subscript,
that corresponds to the score of the true class
for the i-th example in the training set.
Question?
- [Student] So what exactly is this computing?
- Yeah the question is what exactly is this computing here?
It's a little bit funny, I think it will become more clear
when we walk through an explicit example, but in some sense
what this loss is saying is that we are happy if the true
score is much higher than all the other scores.
It needs to be higher than all the other scores
by some safety margin, and if the true score
is not high enough, greater than any of the other scores,
then we will incur some loss and that would be bad.
So this might make a little bit more sense
if we walk through an explicit example
for this tiny three example data set.
So here remember I've sort of removed the case space
notation and just switching back to the zero one notation,
and now if we look at,
if we think about computing this multi-class SVM loss
for just this first training example
on the left, then remember we're going to loop over
all of the incorrect classes, so for this example,
cat is the correct class, so we're going to loop over the car
and frog classes, and now for car, we're going to compare the,
we're going to look at the car score, 5.1, minus the cat score,
3.2 plus one, when we're comparing cat and car we expect
to incur some loss here because the car score is greater
than the cat score which is bad.
So for this one class, for this one example,
we'll incur a loss of 2.9,
and then when we go and compare the cat score
and the frog score we see that cat is 3.2,
frog is minus 1.7,
so cat is more than one greater than frog,
which means that between these two classes
we incur zero loss.
So then the multiclass SVM loss for this training example
will be the sum of the losses across each of these pairs
of classes, which will be 2.9 plus zero which is 2.9.
Which is sort of saying that 2.9 is a quantitative measure
of how much our classifier screwed up
on this one training example.
And then if we repeat this procedure
for this next car image, then again the true class is car,
so we're going to iterate over all the other categories
when we compare the car and the cat score,
we see that car is more than one greater than cat
so we get no loss here.
When we compare car and frog, we again see
that the car score is more than one greater than frog,
so we get again no loss here, and our total loss
for this training example is zero.
And now I think you hopefully get the picture by now, but,
if you go look at frog, now frog, we again compare frog
and cat, incur quite a lot of loss because the frog score
is very low, compare frog and car, incur a lot of loss
because the score is very low, and then our loss for this
example is 12.9.
And then our final loss for the entire data set
is the average of these losses
across the different examples,
so when you sum those out it comes to about 5.3.
So then it's sort of, this is our quantitative measure
that our classifier is 5.3 bad on this data set.
Is there a question?
- [Student] How do you choose the plus one?
- Yeah, the question is how do you choose the plus one?
That's actually a really great question,
it seems like kind of an arbitrary choice here,
it's the only constant that appears in the loss function
and that seems to offend your aesthetic sensibilities
a bit maybe.
But it turns out that this is somewhat
of an arbitrary choice, because we don't actually care
about the absolute values of the scores
in this loss function, we only care
about the relative differences between the scores.
We only care that the correct score
is much greater than the incorrect scores.
So in fact if you imagine scaling up your whole W
up or down, then it kind of rescales all the scores
correspondingly and if you kind of work through the details
and there's a detailed derivation of this in the course notes
online, you find this choice of one actually doesn't matter.
That this free parameter of one kind of washes out
and is canceled with this scale,
like the overall setting of the scale in W.
And again, check the course notes for a bit more detail
on that.
So then I think it's kind of useful to think
about a couple different questions to try to understand
intuitively what this loss is doing.
So the first question is what's going to happen to the loss
if we change the scores of the car image just a little bit?
Any ideas?
Everyone's too scared to ask a question?
Answer?
[student speaking faintly]
- Yeah, so the answer is that if we jiggle the scores
for this car image a little bit, the loss will not change.
So the SVM loss, remember, the only thing it cares
about is getting the correct score to be greater than one
more than the incorrect scores, but in this case,
the car score is already quite a bit larger than the others,
so if the scores for this class changed for this example
changed just a little bit, this margin of one
will still be retained and the loss will not change,
we'll still get zero loss.
The next question, what's the min and max possible loss
for SVM?
[student speaking faintly]
Oh I hear some murmurs.
So the minimum loss is zero, because if you can imagine that
across all the classes, if our correct score was much
larger then we'll incur zero loss across all the classes
and it will be zero,
and if you think back to this hinge loss plot that we had,
then you can see that if the correct score
goes very, very negative, then we could incur
potentially infinite loss.
So the min is zero and the max is infinity.
Another question, sort of when you initialize these things
and start training from scratch,
usually you kind of initialize W
with some small random values, as a result your scores
tend to be sort of small uniform random values
at the beginning of training.
And then the question is that if all of your Ss,
if all of the scores are approximately zero
and approximately equal,
then what kind of loss do you expect
when you're using multiclass SVM?
- [Student] Number of classes minus one.
- Yeah, so the answer is number of classes minus one,
because remember that if we're looping over
all of the incorrect classes, so we're looping over
C minus one classes, within each of those classes
the two Ss will be about the same,
so we'll get a loss of one
because of the margin and we'll get C minus one.
So this is actually kind of useful because when you,
this is a useful debugging strategy
when you're using these things,
that when you start off training,
you should think about what you expect your loss to be,
and if the loss you actually see at the start of training
at that first iteration is not equal to C minus one
in this case,
that means you probably have a bug and you should go check
your code, so this is actually kind of a useful thing
to be checking in practice.
Another question, what happens if, so I said we're summing
an SVM over the incorrect classes, what happens if the sum
is also over the correct class
if we just go over everything?
- [Student] The loss increases by one.
- Yeah, so the answer is that the loss increases by one.
And I think the reason that we do this in practice
is because normally loss of zero is kind of, has this nice
interpretation that you're not losing at all,
so that's nice, so I think your answers
wouldn't really change,
you would end up finding the same classifier
if you actually looped over all the categories,
but if just by conventions we omit the correct class
so that our minimum loss is zero.
So another question, what if we used mean
instead of sum here?
- [Student] Doesn't change.
- Yeah, the answer is that it doesn't change.
So the number of classes is going to be fixed ahead of time
when we select our data set, so that's just rescaling
the whole loss function by a constant,
so it doesn't really matter, it'll sort of wash out
with all the other scale things
because we don't actually care about the true values
of the scores, or the true value of the loss
for that matter.
So now here's another example, what if we change
this loss formulation and we actually added a square term
on top of this max?
Would this end up being the same problem
or would this be a different classification algorithm?
- [Student] Different.
- Yes, this would be different.
So here the idea is that we're kind of changing
the trade-offs between good and badness
in kind of a nonlinear way,
so this would end up actually computing
a different loss function.
This idea of a squared hinge loss actually does get used
sometimes in practice, so that's kind of another trick
to have in your bag when you're making up
your own loss functions for your own problems.
So now you'll end up, oh, was there a question?
- [Student] Why would you use a squared loss
instead of a non-squared loss?
- Yeah, so the question is why would you ever consider
using a squared loss instead of a non-squared loss?
And the whole point of a loss function
is to kind of quantify how bad are different mistakes.
And if the classifier is making different sorts of mistakes,
how do we weigh off the different trade-offs
between different types of mistakes the classifier
might make?
So if you're using a squared loss,
that sort of says that things that are very, very bad
are now going to be squared bad
so that's like really, really bad,
like we don't want anything
that's totally catastrophically misclassified,
whereas if you're using this hinge loss,
we don't actually care between being a little bit wrong
and being a lot wrong, being a lot wrong kind of like,
if an example is a lot wrong, and we increase it
and make it a little bit less wrong,
that's kind of the same goodness as an example
which was only a little bit wrong and then increasing it
to be a little bit more right.
So that's a little bit hand wavy,
but this idea of using a linear versus a square
is a way to quantify how much we care
about different categories of errors.
And this is definitely something that you should think about
when you're actually applying these things in practice,
because the loss function is the way
that you tell your algorithm what types of errors
you care about and what types of errors
it should trade off against.
So that's actually super important in practice
depending on your application.
So here's just a little snippet of sort of vectorized code
in numpy, and you'll end up implementing
something like this for the first assignment,
but this kind of gives you the sense that this sum
is actually like pretty easy
to implement in numpy, it only takes a couple lines
of vectorized code.
And you can see in practice, like one nice trick
is that we can actually go in here and zero out the margins
corresponding to the correct class,
and that makes it easy to then just,
that's sort of one nice vectorized trick to skip,
iterate over all but one class.
You just kind of zero out the one you want to skip
and then compute the sum anyway, so that's a nice trick
you might consider using on the assignment.
So now, another question about this loss function.
Suppose that you were lucky enough to find a W
that has loss of zero, you're not losing at all,
you're totally winning,
this loss function is crushing it,
but then there's a question, is this W unique
or were there other Ws
that could also have achieved zero loss?
- [Student] There are other Ws.
- Answer, yeah, so there are definitely other Ws.
And in particular, because we talked a little bit
about this thing of scaling the whole problem up or down
depending on W, so you could actually take W
multiplied by two and this doubled W (Is it quad U now?
I don't know.)
[laughing]
This would also achieve zero loss.
So as a concrete example of this,
you can go back to your favorite example
and maybe work through the numbers
a little bit later,
but if you're taking W and we double W,
then the margins between the correct and incorrect scores
will also double.
So that means that if all these margins
were already greater than one, and we doubled them,
they're still going to be greater than one,
so you'll still have zero loss.
And this is kind of interesting,
because if our loss function
is the way that we tell our classifier which W we want
and which W we care about,
this is a little bit weird,
now there's this inconsistency
and how is the classifier to choose
between these different versions of W
that all achieve zero loss?
And that's because what we've done here
is written down only a loss in terms of the data,
and we've only told our classifier
that it should try to find the W
that fits the training data.
But really in practice, we don't actually care
that much about fitting the training data,
the whole point of machine learning
is that we use the training data to find some classifier
and then we'll apply that thing on test data.
So we don't really care about the training data performance,
we really care about the performance
of this classifier on test data.
So as a result, if the only thing
we're telling our classifier to do
is fit the training data,
then we can lead ourselves
into some of these weird situations sometimes,
where the classifier might have unintuitive behavior.
So a concrete, canonical example of this sort of thing,
by the way, this is not linear classification anymore,
this is a little bit of a more general
machine learning concept,
is that suppose we have this data set of blue points,
and we're going to fit some curve to the training data,
the blue points,
then if the only thing we've told our classifier to do
is to try and fit the training data,
it might go in and have very wiggly curves
to try to perfectly classify
all of the training data points.
But this is bad, because we don't actually care
about this performance,
we care about the performance on the test data.
So now if we have some new data come in
that sort of follows the same trend,
then this very wiggly blue line
is going to be totally wrong.
And in fact, what we probably would have preferred
the classifier to do was maybe predict
this straight green line,
rather than this very complex wiggly line
to perfectly fit all the training data.
And this is a core fundamental problem
in machine learning,
and the way we usually solve it,
is this concept of regularization.
So here we're going to add an additional term
to the loss function.
In addition to the data loss,
which will tell our classifier that it should fit
the training data, we'll also typically add
another term to the loss function
called a regularization term,
which encourages the model to somehow pick a simpler W,
where the concept of simple
kind of depends on the task and the model.
There's this whole idea of Occam's Razor,
which is this fundamental idea in scientific discovery
more broadly, which is that if you have many different
competing hypotheses, that could explain
your observations,
you should generally prefer the simpler one,
because that's the explanation that is more likely
to generalize to new observations in the future.
And the way we operationalize this intuition
in machine learning is typically through some explicit
regularization penalty
that's often written down as R.
So then your standard loss function
usually has these two terms,
a data loss and a regularization loss,
and there's some hyper-parameter here, lambda,
that trades off between the two.
And we talked about hyper-parameters
and cross-validation in the last lecture,
so this regularization hyper-parameter lambda