- Hello everyone, welcome to CS231.
I'm Song Han. Today I'm going to give a guest lecture
on the efficient methods and hardware for deep learning.
So I'm a fifth year PhD candidate here at Stanford,
advised by Professor Bill Dally.
So, in this course we have seen a lot of convolution neural
networks, recurrent neural networks, or even
since last time, the reinforcement learning.
They are spanning a lot of applications.
For example, the self-=driving car, machine translation,
AlphaGo and Smart Robots.
And it's changing our lives, but there is a recent
trend that in order to achieve such high accuracy,
the models are getting larger and larger.
For example for ImageNet recognition, the winner from
2012 to 2015, the model size increased by 16X.
And just in one year, for Baidu's deep speech
just in one year, the training operations, the number
of training operations increased by 10X.
So such large model creates lots of problems,
for example the model size becomes larger and larger
so it's difficult for them to be deployed either
on those for example, on the mobile phones.
If the item is larger than 100 megabytes, you
cannot download until you connect to Wi-Fi.
So those product managers and for example Baidu,
Facebook, they are very sensitive to the size of the binary
size of their model.
And also for example, the self-driving car, you can only
do those on over-the-air update for the model
if the model is too large, it's also difficult.
And the second challenge for those large models is
that the training speed is extremely slow.
For example, the ResNet152, which is only a few, less
than 1% actually, more accurate than ResNet101.
Takes 1.5 weeks to train on four Maxwell
M40 GPUs for example.
Which greatly limits either we are doing homework
or if the researcher's designing new models is
getting pretty slow.
And the third challenge for those bulky model is
the energy efficiency.
For example, the AlphaGo beating Lee Sedol last year,
took 2000 CPUs and 300 GPUs, which cost $3,000
just to pay for the electric bill, which is insane.
So either on those embedded devices, those models
are draining your battery power for on data-center
increases the total cost of ownership of maintaining
a large data-center.
For example, Google in their blog, they mentioned
if all the users using the Google Voice Search for
just three minutes, they have to double their data-center.
So that's a large cost.
So reducing such cost is very important.
And let's see where is actually the energy consumed.
The large model means lots of memory access.
You have to access, load those models from the memory
means more energy.
If you look at how much energy is consumed by loading
the memory versus how much is consumed by multiplications
and add those arithmetic operations, the memory access
is more than two or three orders of magnitude,
more energy consuming than those arithmetic operations.
So how to make deep learning more efficient.
So we have to improve energy efficiency by this
Algorithm and Hardware Co-Design.
So this is the previous way, which is our hardware.
For example, we have some benchmarks say Spec 2006
and then run those benchmarks and tune your CPU
architectures for those benchmarks.
Now what we should do is to open up the box to see
what can we do from algorithm side first and see what
is the optimum question mark processing unit.
That breaks the boundary between the algorithm
hardware to improve the overall efficiency.
So today's talk, I'm going to have the following agenda.
We are going to cover four aspects: The algorithm hardware
and inference and training.
So they form a small two by two matrix, so includes the
algorithm for efficient inference,
hardware for efficient inference
and the algorithm for efficient training,
and lastly, the hardware for efficient training.
For example, I'm going to cover the TPU, I'm
going to cover the Volta.
But before I cover those things, let's have three
slides for Hardware 101.
A brief introduction of the families of hardware
in such a tree.
So in general, we can have roughly two branches.
One is general purpose hardware.
It can do any applications versus the specialized
hardware, which is tuned for a specific kind of
applications, a domain of applications.
So the general purpose hardware includes, the CPU
or the GPU, and their difference is that CPU is
latency oriented, single threaded.
It's like a big elephant.
While the GPU is throughput oriented.
It has many small though weak threads, but there
are thousands of such small weak cores.
Like a group of small ants, where there are so many ants.
And specialized hardware, roughly there are FPGAs and ASICs.
So FPGA stand for Field Programmable Gate Array.
So it is programmable, hardware programmable so its
logic can be changed.
So it's cheaper for you to try new ideas and do prototype,
but it's less efficient.
It's in the middle between the general purpose and
pure ASIC.
So ASIC stands for Application Specific Integrated Circuit.
It has a fixed logic, just designed
for a certain application.
For example deep learning.
And Google's TPU is a kind of ASIC and the neural networks
we train on, the earlier GPUs is here.
And another slide for Hardware 101 is the number
representations.
So in this slide, I'm going to convey you the idea that
all the numbers in computer are not represented
by a real number.
It's not a real number, but they are actually discrete.
Even for those floating point with your 32 Bit.
Floating point numbers, their resolution is not perfect.
It's not continuous, but it's discrete.
So for example FP32, meaning using a 32 bit to represent
a floating point number.
So there are three components in the representation.
The sign bit, the exponent bit, the mantissa,
and the number it represents is shown by minus 1 to the S
times 1.M times 2 to the exponent.
So similar there is FP16, using a 16 bit to represent
a floating point number.
In particular, I'm going to introduce Int8, where
the core TPU use, using an integer to represent a fixed
point number.
So we have a certain number of bits for the integer.
Followed by a radix point, if we put different layers.
And lastly, the fractional bits.
So why do we prefer those eight bit, or 16 bit
rather than those traditional like the
32 bit floating point.
That's the cost.
So, I generated the figure from 45 nanometer technology
about the energy cost versus the area cost for different
operations.
In particular, let's see here, go you from 32 bit to
16 bit, we have about four times reduction in energy
and also about four times reduction in the area.
Area means money.
Every millimeter square takes money to take out a chip
So it's very beneficial for hardware design to go from
32 bit to 16 bit.
That's why you hear NVIDIA from Pascal Architecture,
they said they're starting to support FP16.
That's the reason why it's so beneficial.
For example, previous battery level could last four hours,
now it becomes 16 hours.
That's what it means to reduce
the energy cost by four times.
But here still, there's a problem of large energy costs
for reading the memory.
And let's see how can we deal with this memory reference
so expensive, how do we deal with this problem better?
So let's switch gear and come to our topic directly.
So let's first introduce algorithm for efficient inference.
So I'm going to cover six topics, this is a really long slide.
So I'm going to relatively fast.
So the first idea I'm going to talk about is pruning.
Pruning the neural networks.
For example, this is original neural network.
So what I'm trying to do is, can we remove some of the
weight and still have the same accuracy?
It's like pruning a tree, get rid
of those redundant connections.
This is first proposed by Professor Yann LeCun back in 1989,
and I revisited this problem, 26 years later, on those
modern deep neural nets to see how it works.
So not all parameters are useful actually.
For example, in this case, if you want to fit a single line,
but you're using a quadratic term, apparently the
0.01 is a redundant parameter.
So I'm going to train the connectivity first and then
prune some of the connections.
And then train the remaining weights,
and through this process, it regulates.
And as a result, I can reduce the number of connections,
and annex that from 16 million parameters to only
six million parameters, which is 10 times less
the computation.
So this is the accuracy.
So the x-axis is how much parameters to prune away
and the y-axis is the accuracy you have.
So we want to have less parameters, but we also
want to have the same accuracy as before.
We don't want to sacrifice accuracy,
For example at 80%, we locked zero away left 80%
of the parameters, but accuracy jumped by 4%.
That's intolerable.
But the good thing is that if we retrain the remaining
weights, the accuracy can fully recover here.
And if we do this process iteratively
by pruning and retraining, pruning and retraining,
we can fully recover the accuracy not until we are
prune away 90% of the parameters.
So if you go back to home and try it on your Ipad
or notebook, just zero away 50% of the parameters say
you went on your homework, you will astonishingly find
that accuracy actually doesn't hurt.
So we just mentioned convolution neural nets,
how about RNNs and LSTMs, so I tried with this neural talk.
Again, pruning away 90% of the rates doesn't hurt the
blue score.
And here are some visualizations.
For example, the original picture, the neural talk says
a basketball player in a white uniform is playing
with a ball.
Versus pruning away 90% it says, a basketball player
in a white uniform is playing with a basketball.
And on and so on.
But if you're too aggressive, say you prune away
95% of the weights, the network is going to get drunk.
It says, a man in a red shirt and white and black shirt
is running through a field.
So there's really a limit, a threshold, you have to
take care of during the pruning.
So interestingly, after I did the work, did some
resource and research and find actually the same
pruning procedure actually happens to human brain
as well.
So when we were born, there are about 50 trillion synapses
in the brain.
And at one year old, this number surged into 1,000 trillion.
And as we become adolescent, it becomes smaller actually,
500 trillion in the end, according to the study by Nature.
So this is very interesting.
And also, the pruning changed the weight distribution
because we are removing those small connections
and after we retrain them, that's why it becomes soft
in the end.
Yeah, question.
- [Student] Are you trying to mean that it terms
of your mixed weights during the training will be
just set at zero and just start from scratch?
And these start from the things that are at zero.
- Yeah. So the question is, how do we deal with those
zero connections?
So we force them to be zero in all the other iterations.
Question?
- [Student] How do you pick which rates to drop?
- Yeah so very simple. Small weights, drop it, sort it.
If it's small, just--
- [Student] Any threshold that I decide?
- Exactly, yeah.
So the next idea, weight sharing.
So now we have, remember our end goal is to remove
connections so that we can have less memory footprint
so that we can have more energy efficient deployment.
Now we have less number of parameters by pruning.
We want to have less number of bits per parameter
so they're multiplied together they get a small model.
So the idea is like this.
Not all numbers, not all the weights
has to be the exact number.
For example, 2.09, 2.12 or all these four weights, you
just put them using 2.0 to represent them.
That's enough.
Otherwise too accurate number is just leads to overfitting.
So the idea is I can cluster the weights if they
are similar, just using a centroid to represent
the number instead of using the full precision weight.
So that every time I do the inference, I just do inference
on this single number.
For example, this is a four by four weight matrix
in a certain layer.
And what I'm going to do is do k-means clustering by having
the similar weight sharing the same centroid.
For example, 2.09, 2.12, I store index of
three pointing to here.
So that, the good thing is we need to only store the
two bit index rather than the 32 bit, floating point number.
That's 16 times saving.
And how do we train such neural network?
They are binded together, so after we get the gradient,
we color them in the same pattern as the weight
and then we do a group by operation by having all
the in that weights with the same index grouped together.
And then we do a reduction by summing them up.
And then multiplied by the learning rate
subtracted from the original centroid.
That's one iteration of the SGD for such weight
shared neural network.
So remember previously, after pruning this is
what the weight distribution like and after
weight sharing, they become discrete.
There are only 16 different values here, meaning
we can use four bits to represent each number.
And by training on such weight shared neural network,
training on such extremely shared neural network,
these weights can adjust.
It is the subtle changes that compensated for the
loss of accuracy.
So let's see, this is the number of bits we give it,
this is the accuracy for convolution layers.
Not until four bits, does the accuracy begin to drop
and for those fully connected layers, very astonishingly,
it's not until two bits, only four number, does the
accuracy begins to drop.
And this result is per layer.
So we have covered two methods, pruning and weight sharing.
What if we combine these two methods together.
Do they work well?
So by combining those methods, this is the compression
ratio with the smaller on the left.
And this is the accuracy.
We can combine it together and make the model
about 3% of its original size without hurting the
accuracy at all.
Compared with the each working individual data by
10%, accuracy begins to drop.
And compared with the cheap SVD method,
this has a better compression ratio.
And final idea is we can apply the Huffman Coding
to use more number of bits for those infrequent numbers,
infrequently appearing weights and less number of bits
for those more frequently appearing weights.
So by combining these three methods, pruning, weight
sharing, and also Huffman Coding, we can compress the
neural networks, state-of-the-art  neural networks,
ranging from 10x to 49x without hurting the
prediction accuracy.
Sometimes a little bit better.
But maybe that is noise.
So the next question is, these models are just pre-trained
models by say Google, Microsoft.
Can we make a compact model, a pump compact model
to begin with?
Even before such compression?
So SqueezeNet, you may have already worked with this
neural network model in a homework.
So the idea is we are having a squeeze layer here to shield
at the three by three convolution with fewer number of
channels.
So that's where squeeze comes from.
And here we have two branches, rather than four branches
as in the inception model.
So as a result, the model is extremely compact.
It doesn't have any  fully connected layers.
Everything is fully convolutional.
The last layer is a global pooling.
So what if we apply deep compression algorithm
on such already compact model will it be getting even
smaller?
So this is AlexNet after compression, this is SqueezeNet.
Even before compression, it's 50x smaller than AlexNet,
but has the same accuracy.
After compression 510x smaller, but the same accuracy
only less than half a megabyte.
This means it's very easy to fit such a small model
on the cache, which is literally
tens of megabyte SRAM.
So what does it mean?
It's possible to achieve speed up.
So this is the speedup, I measured if all these fully
connected layers only for now, on the CPU, GPU, and
the mobile GPU, before pruning
and after pruning the weights,
and on average, I observed a 3x speedup in a CPU,
about 3X speedup on the GPU,
and roughly 5x speedup on the mobile GPU, which is a
TK1.
And so is the energy efficiency.
In an average improvement from 3x to 6x on a CPU, GPU,
and mobile GPU.
And these ideas are used in these companies.
Having talked about when pruning and when sharing,
which is a non-linear quantization method
and we're going to talk about quantization, which is, why
do they use in the TPU design?
All the TPU designs use at only eight bit for inference.
And the way, how they can use that is because of the
quantization.
And let's see how does it work.
So quantization has this complicated figure, but
the intuition is very simple.
You run the neural network and train it with the normal
floating point numbers.
And quantize the weight and activations by gather
the statistics for each layer.
For example, what is the maximum number, minimum number,
and how many bits are enough
to represent this dynamic range.
Then you use that number of bits for the integer part
and the rest of the eight bit or seven bit
for the other part of the 8 bit representation.
And also we can fine tune in the floating point format.
Or we can also use feed forward with fixed point
and back propagation with update with the floating
point number.
There are lots of different ideas to have better accuracy.
And this is the result, for how many number of bits
versus what is the accuracy.
For example, using a fixed, 8 bit, the accuracy for
GoogleNet doesn't drop significantly.
And for VGG-16, it also remains pretty well for
the accuracy.
While circling down to a six bit, the accuracy
begins to drop pretty dramatically.
Next idea, low rank approximation.
It turned out that for a convolution layer,
you can break it into two convolution layers.
One convolution here, followed by a one by one convolution.
So that it's like you break a complicated problem
into two separate small problems.
This is for convolution layer.
As we can see, achieving about
2x speedup, there's almost no loss of accuracy.
And achieving a speedup of 5x, roughly a 6%
loss of accuracy.
And this also works for fully connected layers.
The simplest idea is using the SVD to break it into
one matrix into two matrices.
And follow this idea, this paper proposes to use the
Tensor Tree to break down one fully connected layer into
a tree, lots of fully connected layers.
That's why it's called a tree.
So going even more crazy, can we use only
two weights or three weights to represent a neural network?
A ternary weight or a binary weight.
We already seen this distribution before, after pruning.
There's some positive weights and negative weights.
Can we just use three numbers, just use one, minus one, zero
to represent the neural network.
This is our recent paper clear that we maintain
a full precision weight during training time,
but at inference time, we only keep the scaling factor
and the ternary weight.
So during inference, we only need three weights.
That's very efficient and making the model very small.
This is the proportion of the positive zero
and negative weights, they can change during the training.
So is their absolute value.
And this is the visualization of kernels
by this trained ternary quantization.
We can see some of them are a corner detector like here.
And also here.
Some of them are maybe edge detector.
For example, this filter some of them
are corner detector like here this filter.
Actually we don't need such fine grain resolution.
Just three weights are enough.
So this is the validation accuracy on ImageNet with AlexNet.
So the threshline is the baseline accuracy
with floating point 32.
And the red line is our result.
Pretty much the same accuracy converged compared with
the full precision weights.
Last idea, Winograd Transformation.
So this about how do we implement deep neural nets,
how do we implement the convolutions.
So this is the conventional direct
convolution implementation method.
The slide credited to Julien, a friend from Nvidia.
So originally, we just do the element wise
do a dot product for those nine elements in the filter
and nine elements in the image and then sum it up.
For example, for every output we need nine times C
number of multiplication and adds.
Winograd Convolution is another method, equivalent method.
It's not lost, it's an equivalent method proposed at
first through this paper, Fast Algorithms
for Convolution Neural Networks.
That instead of directly doing the convolution, move
it one by one, at first it transforms the input feature
map to another feature map.
Which contains only the weight, contains only 1, 0.5, 2
that can efficiently implement it with shift.
And also transform the filter into a four by four tensor.
So what we are going to do here is sum over c and do an element-wise
element-wise product.
So there are only 16 multiplications happening here.
And then we do a inverse transform to get four outputs.
So the transform and the inverse transform can be
amortized and the multiplications, whether it can ignored.
So in order to get four output, we need nine times channel
times four, which is 36 times channel.
Multiplications originally for the direct convolution
but now we need 16 times C of our output
So that is 2.25x less number of multiplications to
perform the exact same multiplication.
And here is a speedup.
2.25x, so theoretically, 2.25x speedup and in real,
from cuDNN 5 they incorporated such
Winograd Convolution algorithm.
This is on the VGG net I believe, the speedup is
roughly 1.7 to 2x speedup.
Pretty significant.
And after cuDNN 5, the cuDNN begins to use the
Winograd Convolution algorithm.
Okay, so far we have covered those efficient algorithms
for efficient inference.
We covered pruning, weight sharing, quantization,
and also Winograd binary and ternary.
So now let's see what is the optimal hardware for those
efficient inference?
And what is a Google TPU?
So there are a wide range of domain specific
architectures or ASICS for deep neural networks.
They have a common goal is to minimize the memory
access to save power.
For example the Eyeriss from MIT by using the RS Dataflow
to minimize the off chip direct access.
And DaDiannao from China Academy of Science,
buffered all the weights on chip DRAM instead of having
to go to off-chip DRAM.
So the TPU from Google is using eight bit integer
to represent the numbers.
And at Stanford I proposed the EIE architecture
that support those compressed and
sparse deep neural network inference.
So this is what the TPU looks like.
It's actually smartly, can be put into the disk drive
up to four cards per server.
And this is the high-level architecture
for the Google TPU.
Don't be overwhelmed, it's actually, the kernel part
here, is this giant matrix multiplication unit.
So it's a 256 by 256 matrix multiplication unit.
So in one single cycle, it can perform 64 kilo
those number of multiplication and accumulate operations.
So running 700 Megahertz, the throughput is 92
Teraops per second
because it's actually integer operation.
So we just about 25x as GPU and more than 100x at the CPU.
And notice, TPU has a really large software-managed
on-chip buffer.
It is 24 megabytes.
The cache for the CPU the L3 cache is already
16 megabytes.
This is 24 megabytes which is pretty large.
And it's powered by two DDR3 DRAM channels.
So this is a little weak because the bandwidth is
only 30 gigabytes per second compared with the most
recent GPU that HBM, 900 Gigabytes per second.
The DDR4 is released in 2014, so that makes sense because
the design is a little during that day, used the DDR3.
But if you're using DDR4 or even high-bandwidth memory,
the performance can be even boosted.
So this is a comparison about Google's TPU compared
with the CPU, GPU of this K80 GPU by the way, and the TPU.
So the area is pretty much smaller, like half the size of a
CPU and GPU and the power consumption is roughly 75 watts.
And see this number, the peak teraops per second
is much higher than the CPU and GPU is, about 90
teraops per second, which is pretty high.
So here is a workload.
Thanks to David sharing the slide.
This is the workload at Google.
They did a benchmark on these TPUs.
So it's a little interesting that convolution neural nets
only account for 5% of data-center workload.
Most of them is multilayer perception,
those fully connected layers.
About 61% maybe for ads, I'm not sure.
And about 29% of the workload in data-center is the
Long Short Term Memory.
For example, speech recognition,
or machine translation, I suspect.
Remember just now we have seen there are
90 teraops per second.
But what actually number of teraops per second
can be achieved?
This is a basic tool to measure the bottleneck
of a computer system.
Whether you are bottlenecked by the arithmetic or
you are bottlenecked by the memory bandwidth.
It's like if you have a bucket,
the lowest part of the bucket determines how much
water we can hold in the bucket.
So in this region, you are bottlenecked
by the memory bandwidth.
So the x-axis is the arithmetic intensity.
Which is number of floating point operations per byte
the ratio between the computation and memory
of bandwidth overhead.
So the y-axis, is the actual attainable performance.
Here is the peak performance for example.
When you do a lot of operation after you fetch a single
piece of data, if you can do a lot of operation
on top of it, then you are bottlenecked by the arithmetic.
But after you fetch a lot of data from the memory,
but you just do a tiny little bit of arithmetic,
then you will be bottlenecked by the memory bandwidth.
So how much you can fetch from the memory determines
how much real performance you can get.
And remember there is a ratio.
When it is one here, this region it happens to be the same
as the turning point is the actual
memory bandwidth of your system.
So let's see what is the life for the TPU.
The TPU's peak performance is really high,
about 90 Tops per second.
For those convolution nets, they are pretty much saturating
the peak performance.
But there are lot of neural networks that has a utlitization
less than 10%,
meaning that 90 T-ops per second is actually
achieves about three to 12 T-ops per second in real case.
But why is it like that?
The reason is, in order to have those real-time guarantee
that the user not wait for too long, you cannot batch
a lot of user's images or speech voice data
at the same time.
So as a result, for those fully connect layers,
they have very little reuse, so they are bottlenecked
by the memory bandwidth.
For those convolution neural nets, for example this one,
this blue one, that achieve 86, which is CNN0.
The ratio between the ops and
the number of memory is the highest.
It's pretty high, more than 2,000 compared with other
multilayer perceptron or long short term memory
the ratio is pretty low.
So this figure compares, this is the TPU and this one is
the CPU, this is the GPU.
Here is memory bandwidth, the peak memory bandwidth
at a ratio of one here.
So TPU has the highest memory bandwidth.
And here is where are these neural networks
lie on this curve.
So the asterisk is for the TPU.
It's still higher than other dots,
but if you're not comfortable with this log scale figure,
this is what it's like putting it in linear roofline.
So pretty much everything disappeared except
for the TPU results.
So still, all these lines, although they are higher
than the CPU and GPU, it's still way below the
theoretical peak operations per second.
So as I mentioned before, it is really bottlenecked
by the low latency requirement so that it can have
a large batch size.
That's why you have low operations per byte.
And how do you solve this problem?
You want to have less number of memory footprint
so that it can reduce the memory bandwidth requirement.
One solution is to compress the model and the challenge
is how do we build a hardware that can do inference
directly on the compressed model?
So I'm going to introduce my design of EIE, the Efficient
Inference Engine, which deals with those sparse
and the compressed model to save the memory bandwidth.
And the rule of thumb, like we mentioned before is taking
out one bit of sparsity first.
Anything times zero is zero.
So don't store it, don't compute on it.
And second idea is, you don't need that much full precision,
but you can approximate it.
So by taking advantage of the sparse weight, we
get about a 10x saving in the computation, 5x less
memory footprint.
The 2x difference is due to index overhead.
And by taking advantage of the sparse activation,
meaning after bandwidth, if activation is zero, then
ignore it.
You save another 3x of computation.
And then by such weight sharing mechanism,
you can use four bits to represent each weight rather
than 32 bit.
That's another eight times saving in the memory footprint.
So this is physically, logically how the weights are stored.
00:3