[students murmuring]
- Okay, so good afternoon everyone, let's get started.
So hi, so for those of you who I haven't met yet,
my name is Serena Yeung and I'm the third
and final instructor for this class,
and I'm also a PhD student in Fei-Fei's group.
Okay, so today we're going to talk about backpropagation
and neural networks, and so now we're really starting
to get to some of the core material in this class.
Before we begin, let's see, oh.
So a few administrative details,
so assignment one is due Thursday, April 20th,
so a reminder, we shifted the date back by a little bit
and it's going to be due 11:59 p.m. on Canvas.
So you should start thinking about your projects,
there are TA specialties listed on the Piazza website
so if you have questions about a specific project topic
you're thinking about, you can go and try and find
the TAs that might be most relevant.
And then also for Google Cloud, so all students are going
to get $100 in credits to use for Google Cloud
for their assignments and project,
so you should be receiving an email
for that this week, I think.
A lot of you may have already, and then
for those of you who haven't, they're going to come,
should be by the end of this week.
Okay so where we are, so far we've talked about
how to define a classifier using a function f,
parameterized by weights W, and this function f
is going to take data x as input, and output a vector of scores
for each of the classes that you want to classify.
And so from here we can also define
a loss function, so for example, the SVM loss function
that we've talked about which basically quantifies
how happy or unhappy we are with
the scores that we've produced, right,
and then we can use that to define a total loss term.
So L here, which is a combination of this data term,
combined with a regularization term that expresses
how simple our model is, and we have a preference
for simpler models, for better generalization.
And so now we want to find the parameters W
that correspond to our lowest loss, right?
We want to minimize the loss function,
and so to do that we want to find
the gradient of L with respect to W.
So last lecture we talked about how we can do this
using optimization, and we're going
to iteratively take steps in the direction
of steepest descent, which is the negative of the gradient,
in order to walk down this loss landscape
and get to the point of lowest loss, right?
And we saw how this gradient descent can basically take
this trajectory, looking like this image on the right,
getting to the bottom of your loss landscape.
Oh!
Okay, and so we also talked about different ways
for computing a gradient, right?
We can compute this numerically
using finite difference approximation
which is slow and approximate, but at the same time
it's really easy to write out,
you know you can always get the gradient this way.
We also talked about how to use the analytic gradient
and computing this is, it's fast
and exact once you've gotten the expression for
the analytic gradient, but at the same time you have
to do all the math and the calculus to derive this,
so it's also, you know, easy to make mistakes, right?
So in practice what we want to do is we want to derive
the analytic gradient and use this,
but at the same time check our implementation using
the numerical gradient to make sure
that we've gotten all of our math right.
So today we're going to talk about how to compute
the analytic gradient for arbitrarily complex functions,
using a framework that I'm going to call computational graphs.
And so basically what a computational graph is,
is that we can use this kind of graph in order
to represent any function, where the nodes of the graph
are steps of computation that we go through.
So for example, in this example,
the linear classifier that we've talked about,
the inputs here are x and W, right,
and then this multiplication node represents
the matrix multiplier, the multiplication of
the parameters W with our data x that we have,
outputting our vector of scores.
And then we have another computational node
which represents our hinge loss, right,
computing our data loss term, Li.
And we also have this regularization term at
the bottom right, so this node
which computes our regularization term,
and then our total loss here at the end, L,
is the sum of the regularization term and the data term.
And the advantage is that once we can express
a function using a computational graph,
then we can use a technique that we call backpropagation
which is going to recursively use the chain rule
in order to compute the gradient
with respect to every variable in the computational graph,
and so we're going to see how this is done.
And this becomes very useful when we start working
with really complex functions,
so for example, convolutional neural networks
that we're going to talk about later in this class.
We have here the input image at the top,
we have our loss at the bottom,
and the input has to go through many layers
of transformations in order to get all
the way down to the loss function.
And this can get even crazier with things like,
the, you know, like a neural turing machine,
which is another kind of deep learning model,
and in this case you can see that the computational graph
for this is really insane, and especially,
we end up, you know, unrolling this over time.
It's basically completely impractical
if you want to compute the gradients
for any of these intermediate variables.
Okay, so how does backpropagation work?
So we're going to start off with a simple example,
where again, our goal is that we have a function.
So in this case, f of x, y, z
equals x plus y times z,
and we want to find the gradients of the output of
the function with respect to any of the variables.
So the first step, always, is we want
to take our function f, and we want
to represent it using a computational graph.
Right, so here our computational graph is on the right,
and you can see that we have our,
first we have the plus node, so x plus y,
and then we have this multiplication node, right,
for the second computation that we're doing.
And then, now we're going to do a forward pass
of this network, so given the values of
the variables that we have, so here,
x equals negative two, y equals five
and z equals negative four, I'm going to fill these all in
in our computational graph, and then here we can compute
an intermediate value, so x plus y gives three,
and then finally we pass it through again,
through the last node, the multiplication,
to get our final node of f equals negative 12.
So here we want to give every intermediate variable a name.
So here I've called this intermediate variable after
the plus node q, and we have q equals x plus y,
and then f equals q times z, using this intermediate node.
And I've also written out here, the gradients
of q with respect to x and y, which are just one
because of the addition, and then the gradients of f
with respect to q and z, which is z and q respectively
because of the multiplication rule.
And so what we want to find, is we want to find
the gradients of f with respect to x, y and z.
So what backprop is, it's a recursive application of
the chain rule, so we're going to start at the back,
the very end of the computational graph,
and then we're going to work our way backwards
and compute all the gradients along the way.
So here if we start at the very end, right,
we want to compute the gradient of the output
with respect to the last variable, which is just f.
And so this gradient is just one, it's trivial.
So now, moving backwards, we want the gradient
with respect to z, right, and we know
that df over dz is equal to q.
So the value of q is just three,
and so we have here, df over dz equals three.
And so next if we want to do df over dq,
what is the value of that?
What is df over dq?
So we have here, df over dq is equal to z, right,
and the value of z is negative four.
So here we have df over dq is equal to negative four.
Okay, so now continuing to move backwards to the graph,
we want to find df over dy, right,
but here in this case, the gradient with respect to y,
y is not connected directly to f, right?
It's connected through an intermediate node of z,
and so the way we're going to do this
is we can leverage the chain rule which says
that df over dy can be written as df over dq,
times dq over dy, and so the intuition of this
is that in order to get to find the effect of y on f,
this is actually equivalent to if we take
the effect of q times q on f, which we already know, right?
df over dq is equal to negative four,
and we compound it with the effect of y on q, dq over dy.
So what's dq over dy equal to in this case?
- [Student] One.
- One, right. Exactly.
So dq over dy is equal to one, which means, you know,
if we change y by a little bit,
q is going to change by approximately
the same amount right, this is the effect,
and so what this is doing is this is saying,
well if I change y by a little bit,
the effect of y on q is going to be one,
and then the effect of q on f is going to be approximately
a factor of negative four, right?
So then we multiply these together
and we get that the effect of y on f
is going to be negative four.
Okay, so now if we want to do the same thing for
the gradient with respect to x, right,
we can do the, we can follow the same procedure,
and so what is this going to be?
[students speaking away from microphone]
- I heard the same.
Yeah exactly, so in this case we want to, again,
apply the chain rule, right?
We know the effect of q on f is negative four,
and here again, since we have also the same addition node,
dq over dx is equal to one, again,
we have negative four times one, right, and the gradient
with respect to x is going to be negative four.
Okay, so what we're doing is, in backprop,
is we basically have all of these nodes
in our computational graph, but each node
is only aware of its immediate surroundings, right?
So we have, at each node, we have the local inputs
that are connected to this node,
the values that are flowing into the node,
and then we also have the output
that is directly outputted from this node.
So here our local inputs are x and y, and the output is z.
And at this node we also know the local gradient, right,
we can compute the gradient of z with respect to x,
and the gradient of z with respect to y,
and these are usually really simple operations, right?
Each node is going to be something like
the addition or the multiplication
that we had in that earlier example,
which is something where we can just write down
the gradient, and we don't have to, you know,
go through very complex calculus in order to find this.
- [Student] Can you go back and explain why
more in the last slide was different than planning
the first part of it using just normal calculus?
- Yeah, so basically if we go back,
hold on, let me...
So if we go back here, we could exactly write out,
find all of these using just calculus,
so we could say, you know, we want df over dx, right,
and we can probably expand out this expression
and see that it's just going to be z,
but we can do this for, in this case,
because it's simple, but we'll see examples later on
where once this becomes a really complicated expression,
you don't want to have to use calculus
to derive, right, the gradient for something,
for a super-complicated expression,
and instead, if you use this formalism
and you break it down into these computational nodes,
then you can only ever work with gradients
of very simple computations, right,
at the level of, you know, additions, multiplications,
exponentials, things as simple as you want them,
and then you just use the chain rule
to multiply all these together,
and get your, the value of your gradient
without having to ever derive the entire expression.
Does that make sense?
[student murmuring]
Okay, so we'll see an example of this later.
And so, was there another question, yeah?
[student speaking away from microphone]
- [Student] What's the negative four
next to the z representing?
- Negative, okay yeah, so the negative four,
these were the, the green values on top
were all the values of the function as we passed
it forward through the computational graph, right?
So we said up here that x is equal to negative two,
y is equal to five, and z equals negative four,
so we filled in all of these values, and then we just wanted
to compute the value of this function.
Right, so we said this value of q is going to be x plus y,
it's going to be negative two plus five, it is going
to be three, and we have z is equal to negative four
so we fill that in here, and then we multiplied q
and z together, negative four times three
in order to get the final value of f, right?
And then the red values underneath
were as we were filling in the gradients
as we were working backwards.
Okay.
Okay, so right, so we said that, you know,
we have these local, these nodes,
and each node basically gets its local inputs coming in
and the output that it sees directly passing on
to the next node, and we also have these local gradients
that we computed, right, the gradient of
the immediate output of the node
with respect to the inputs coming in.
And so what happens during backprop is we have these,
we'll start from the back of the graph, right,
and then we work our way from the end
all the way back to the beginning,
and when we reach each node, at each node we have
the upstream gradients coming back, right,
with respect to the immediate output of the node.
So by the time we reach this node in backprop,
we've already computed the gradient
of our final loss l, with respect to z, right?
And so now what we want to find next
is we want to find the gradients with respect
to just before the node, to the values of x and y.
And so as we saw earlier, we do this using the chain rule,
right, we have from the chain rule,
that the gradient of this loss function
with respect to x is going to be
the gradient with respect to z times, compounded by
this gradient, local gradient of z with respect to x.
Right, so in the chain rule we always take
this upstream gradient coming down,
and we multiply it by the local gradient
in order to get the gradient with respect to the input.
- [Student] So, sorry, is it,
it's different because this would never work
to get a general formula into the,
or general symbolic formula for the gradient.
It only works with instantaneous values,
where you like.
[student coughing]
Or passing a little constant value as a symbolic.
- So the question is whether this only works
because we're working with the current values of
the function, and so it works, right,
given the current values of the function that we plug in,
but we can write an expression for this,
still in terms of the variables, right?
So we'll see that gradient of L with respect to z
is going to be some expression, and gradient of z
with respect to x is going to be another expression, right?
But we plug in these, we plug in the values
of these numbers at the time in order to get
the value of the gradient with respect to x.
So what you could do is you could recursively plug in
all of these expressions, right?
Gradient with respect, z with respect to x
is going to be a simple, simple expression, right?
So in this case, if we have a multiplication node,
gradient of z with respect to x is just going
to be y, right, we know that,
but the gradient of L with respect to z,
this is probably a complex part of
the graph in itself, right, so here's where we want to just,
in this case, have this numerical, right?
So as you said, basically this is going to be just
a number coming down, right, a value,
and then we just multiply it with
the expression that we have for the local gradient.
And I think this will be more clear when we go through
a more complicated example in a few slides.
Okay, so now the gradient of L with respect to y,
we have exactly the same idea, where again,
we use the chain rule, we have gradient of L
with respect to z, times the gradient of z
with respect to y, right, we use the chain rule,
multiply these together and get our gradient.
And then once we have these, we'll pass these on to
the node directly before, or connected to this node.
And so the main thing to take away from this
is that at each node we just want to have our local gradient
that we compute, just keep track of this,
and then during backprop as we're receiving, you know,
numerical values of gradients coming from upstream,
we just take what that is, multiply it by
the local gradient, and then this is
what we then send back to the connected nodes,
the next nodes going backwards, without having to care
about anything else besides these immediate surroundings.
So now we're going to go through another example,
this time a little bit more complex,
so we can see more why backprop is so useful.
So in this case, our function is f of w and x,
which is equal to one over one plus e
to the negative of w-zero times x-zero
plus w-one x-one, plus w-two, right?
So again, the first step always is we want
to write this out as a computational graph.
So in this case we can see that in this graph, right,
first we multiply together the w and x terms that we have,
w-zero with x-zero, w-one with x-one,
and w-two, then we add all of these together, right?
Then we do, scale it by negative one,
we take the exponential, we add one,
and then finally we do one over this whole term.
And then here I've also filled in values of these,
so let's say given values that we have
for the ws and xs, right, we can make a forward pass
and basically compute what the value is
at every stage of the computation.
And here I've also written down here at the bottom
the values, the expressions for some derivatives
that are going to be helpful later on,
so same as we did before with the simple example.
Okay, so now then we're going to do backprop through here,
right, so again, we're going to start at
the very end of the graph, and so here again
the gradient of the output with respect to the last variable
is just one, it's just trivial,
and so now moving backwards one step, right?
So what's the gradient with respect to
the input just before one over x?
Well, so in this case, we know that the upstream gradient
that we have coming down, right, is this red one, right?
This is the upstream gradient that we have flowing down,
and then now we need to find the local gradient, right,
and the local gradient of this node,
this node is one over x, right,
so we have f of x equals one over x here in red,
and the local gradient of this df over dx
is equal to negative one over x-squared, right?
So here we're going to take negative one over x-squared,
and plug in the value of x that we had during
this forward pass, 1.37, and so our final gradient
with respect to this variable is going
to be negative one over 1.37 squared times one
equals negative 0.53.
So moving back to the next node,
we're going to go through the exact same process, right?
So here, the gradient flowing from upstream
is going to be negative 0.53, right,
and here the local gradient, the node here is a plus one,
and so now looking at our reference of derivatives at
the bottom, we have that for a constant plus x,
the local gradient is just one, right?
So what's the gradient with respect
to this variable using the chain rule?
So it's going to be the upstream gradient
of negative 0.53 times our local gradient of one,
which is equal to negative 0.53.
So let's keep moving backwards one more step.
So here we have the exponential, right?
So what's the upstream gradient coming down?
[student speaking away from microphone]
Right, so the upstream gradient is negative 0.53,
what's the local gradient here?
It's going to be the local gradient of e to the x, right?
This is an exponential node, and so our chain rule
is going to tell us that our gradient
is going to be negative 0.53 times e to the power of x,
which in this case is negative one,
from our forward pass, and this is going to give us
our final gradient of negative 0.2.
Okay, so now one more node here,
the next node is, that we reach, is going to be
a multiplication with negative one, right?
So here, what's the upstream gradient coming down?
- [Student] Negative 0.2?
- [Serena] Negative 0.2, right, and what's going to be
the local gradient, can look at the reference sheet.
It's going to be, what was it?
I think I heard it.
- [Student] That's minus one?
- It's going to be minus one, exactly, yeah,
because our local gradient says it's going to be,
df over dx is a, right, and the value of a
that we scaled x by is negative one here.
So we have here that the gradient
is negative one times negative 0.2,
and so our gradient is 0.2.
Okay, so now we've reached an addition node,
and so in this case we have these two branches
both connected to it, right?
So what's the upstream gradient here?
It's going to be 0.2, right, just as everything else,
and here now the gradient with respect
to each of these branches, it's an addition, right,
and we saw from before in our simple example
that when we have an addition node,
the gradient with respect to each of the inputs
to the addition is just going to be one, right?
So here, our local gradient for looking at our top stream
is going to be one times the upstream gradient
of 0.2, which is going to give a total gradient of 0.2, right?
And then we, for our bottom branch we'd do
the same thing, right, our upstream gradient is 0.2,
our local gradient is one again,
and the total gradient is 0.2.
So is everything clear about this?
Okay.
So we have a few more gradients to fill out,
so moving back now we've reached w-zero and x-zero,
and so here we have a multiplication node, right,
so we saw the multiplication node from before,
it just, the gradient with respect
to one of the inputs just is the value of the other input.
And so in this case, what's the gradient
with respect to w-zero?
- [Student] Minus 0.2.
- Minus, I'm hearing minus 0.2, exactly.
Yeah, so with respect to w-zero,
we have our upstream gradient, 0.2, right,
times our, this is the bottom one,
times our value of x, which is negative one,
we get negative 0.2 and we can do the same thing
for our gradient with respect to x-zero.
It's going to be 0.2 times the value of w-zero
which is two, and we get 0.4.
Okay, so here we've filled out most of these gradients,
and so there was the question earlier
about why this is simpler than just computing,
deriving the analytic gradient, the expression with respect
to any of these variables, right?
And so you can see here, all we ever dealt with
was expressions for local gradients
that we had to write out, so once we had these expressions
for local gradients, all we did
was plug in the values for each of these that we have,
and use the chain rule to numerically multiply this all
the way backwards and get the gradients
with respect to all of the variables.
And so, you know, we can also fill out
the gradients with respect to w-one and x-one here
in exactly the same way, and so one thing
that I want to note is that right when we're creating
these computational graphs, we can define
the computational nodes at any granularity that we want to.
So in this case, we broke it down into
the absolute simplest that we could, right,
we broke it down into additions and multiplications,
you know, it basically can't get any simpler than that,
but in practice, right, we can group some of
these nodes together into more complex nodes if we want.
As long as we're able to write down
the local gradient for that node, right?
And so as an example, if we look at a sigmoid function,
so I've defined the sigmoid function in
the upper-right here, of a sigmoid of x
is equal to one over one plus e to the negative x,
and this is something that's a really common function
that you'll see a lot in the rest of this class,
and we can compute the gradient for this,
we can write it out, and if we do actually go through
the math of doing this analytically,
we can get a nice expression at the end.
So in this case it's equal to one minus sigma of x,
so the output of this function times sigma of x, right?
And so in cases where we have something like this,
we could just take all the computations
that we had in our graph that made up this sigmoid,
and we could just replace it
with one big node that's a sigmoid, right,
because we do know the local gradient for this gate,
it's this expression, d of the sigmoid of x over dx, right?
So basically the important thing here is
that you can, group any nodes that you want
to make any sorts of a little bit more complex nodes,
as long as you can write down the local gradient for this.
And so all this is is basically a trade-off between,
you know, how much math that you want to do
in order to get a more, kind of concise and simpler graph,
right, versus how simple you want
each of your gradients to be, right?
And then you can write out as complex of
a computational graph that you want.
Yeah, question?
- [Student] This is a question on the graph itself,
is there a reason that the first two multiplication nodes
and the weights are not connected to a single addition node?
- So they could also be connected into
a single addition node, so the question was,
is there a reason why w-zero and x-zero
are not connected with w-two?
All of these additions just connected together,
and yeah, so the reason, the answer is
that you can do that if you want,
and in practice, maybe you would actually want to do that
because this is still a very simple node, right?
So in this case I just wrote this out into as simple
as possible, where each node only had up to two inputs,
but yeah, you could definitely do that.
Any other questions about this?
Okay, so the one thing that I really like
about thinking about this like a computational graph
is that I feel very comforted, right,
like anytime I have to take a gradient,
find gradients of something, even if the expression
that I want to compute gradients of is really hairy,
and really scary, you know, whether it's something like
this sigmoid or something worse,
I know that, you know, I could derive this if I want to,
but really, if I just sit down and write it out
in terms of a computational graph,
I can go as simple as I need to
to always be able to apply backprop and the chain rule,
and be able to compute all the gradients that I need.
And so this is something that you guys should think about
when you're doing your homeworks, as basically, you know,
anytime you're having trouble finding gradients of something
just think about it as a computational graph,
break it down into all of these parts,
and then use the chain rule.
Okay, and so, you know, so we talked about
how we could group these set of nodes together
into a sigmoid gate, and just to confirm, like,
that this is actually exactly equivalent,
we can plug this in, right?
So we have that our input here to the sigmoid gate
is going to be one, in green, and then we have
that the output is going to be here, 0.73, right,
and this'll work out if you plug
it in to the sigmoid function.
And so now if we want to do, if we want to take
the gradient, and we want to treat this entire sigmoid
as one node, now what we should do
is we need to use this local gradient
that we've derived up here, right?
One minus sigmoid of x times the sigmoid of x.
So if we plug this in, and here we know
that the value of sigmoid of x was 0.73,
so if we plug this value in we'll see that this,
the value of this gradient is equal to 0.2, right,
and so the value of this local gradient is 0.2,
we multiply it by the x upstream gradient which is one,
and we're going to get out exactly the same value
of the gradient with respect to before the sigmoid gate,
as if we broke it down into all of the smaller computations.
Okay, and so as we're looking at what's happening, right,
as we're taking these gradients going backwards
through our computational graph,
there's some patterns that you'll notice
where there's some intuitive interpretation
that we can give these, right?
So we saw that the add gate is a gradient distributor right,
when we passed through this addition gate here,
which had two branches coming out of it,
it took the gradient, the upstream gradient
and it just distributed it, passed the exact same thing
to both of the branches that were connected.
So here's a couple more that we can think about.
So what's a max gate look like?
So we have a max gate here at the bottom, right,
where the input's coming in are z and w,
z has a value of two, w has a value of negative one,
and then we took the max of this, which is two, right,
and so we pass this down into the remainder
of our computational graph.
So now if we're taking the gradients with respect to this,
the upstream gradient is, let's say two coming back, right,
and what does this local gradient look like?
So anyone, yes?
- [Student] It'll be zero for one, and one for the other?
- Right.
[student speaking away from microphone]
Exactly, so the answer that was given
is that z will have a gradient of two,
w will have a value, a gradient of zero,
and so one of these is going to get
the full value of the gradient just passed back,
and routed to that variable, and then the other one
will have a gradient of zero, and so,
so we can think of this as kind of a gradient router, right,