- Okay we have a lot to cover today so let's get started.
Today we'll be talking about Generative Models.
And before we start, a few administrative details.
So midterm grades will be released on Gradescope this week
A reminder that A3 is due next Friday May 26th.
The HyperQuest deadline for extra credit you can do this
still until Sunday May 21st.
And our poster session is June 6th from 12 to 3 P.M..
Okay so an overview of what we're going to talk about today
we're going to switch gears a little bit
and take a look at unsupervised learning today.
And in particular we're going to talk about generative
models which is a type of unsupervised learning.
And we'll look at three types of generative models.
So pixelRNNs and pixelCNNs variational autoencoders
and Generative Adversarial networks.
So so far in this class we've talked a lot about supervised
learning and different kinds
of supervised learning problems.
So in the supervised learning set up we have our data X and
then we have some labels Y.
And our goal is to learn a function that's mapping
from our data X to our labels Y.
And these labels can take many different types of forms.
So for example, we've looked at classification
where our input is an image
and we want to output Y, a class label for the category.
We've talked about object detection where now our input
is still an image but here we want to output the
bounding boxes of instances of up to multiple dogs or cats.
We've talked about semantic segmentation where here we have
a label for every pixel the category that every pixel
belongs to.
And we've also talked about image captioning
where here our label is now a sentence
and so it's now in the form of natural language.
So unsupervised learning in this set up,
it's a type of learning where here we have
unlabeled training data and our goal now is to learn some
underlying hidden structure of the data.
Right, so an example of this can be something like
clustering which you guys might have seen before
where here the goal is to find groups within the data
that are similar through some type of metric.
For example, K means clustering.
Another example of an unsupervised learning task
is a dimensionality reduction.
So in this problem want to find axes along which
our training data has the most variation,
and so these axes are part of the underlying structure
of the data.
And then we can use this to reduce of dimensionality
of the data such that the data has significant variation
among each of the remaining dimensions.
Right, so this example here we start off with data
in three dimensions and we're going to find two
axes of variation in this case
and reduce our data projected down to 2D.
Another example of unsupervised learning
is learning feature representations for data.
We've seen how to do this in supervised ways before
where we used the supervised loss,
for example classification.
Where we have the classification label.
We have something like a Softmax loss
And we can train a neural network where
we can interpret activations for example
our FC7 layers as some kind of future
representation for the data.
And in an unsupervised setting,
for example here autoencoders which we'll talk
more about later
In this case our loss is now trying to
reconstruct the input data to basically,
you have a good reconstruction of our input data
and use this to learn features.
So we're learning a feature representation without
using any additional external labels.
And finally another example of unsupervised learning
is density estimation where in this case we want to
estimate the underlying distribution of our data.
So for example in this top case over here,
we have points in 1-d and we can try
and fit a Gaussian into this density
and in this bottom example over here it's 2D data
and here again we're trying to estimate the density and
we can model this density.
We want to fit a model such that the density is higher
where there's more points concentrated.
And so to summarize the differences in unsupervised
learning which we've looked a lot so far,
we want to use label data to learn
a function mapping from X to Y
and an unsupervised learning we use no labels
and instead we try to learn some underlying hidden
structure of the data, whether this is grouping,
acts as a variation or underlying density estimation.
And unsupervised learning is a huge
and really exciting area of research and
and some of the reasons are that training data is really
cheap, it doesn't use labels so we're able to learn
from a lot of data at one time and basically utilize a lot
more data than if we required annotating
or finding labels for data.
And unsupervised learning is still relatively
unsolved research area by comparison.
There's a lot of open problems in this,
but it also, it holds the potential of
if you're able to successfully learn
and represent a lot of the underlying structure
in the data then this also takes you a
long way towards the Holy Grail of trying to understand the
structure of the visual world.
So that's a little bit of kind of a high-level big picture
view of unsupervised learning.
And today will focus more specifically on generative models
which is a class of models for unsupervised
learning where given training data our goal is to try and
generate new samples from the same distribution.
Right, so we have training data over here generated
from some distribution P data
and we want to learn a model, P model
to generate samples from the same distribution
and so we want to learn P model to be similar to P data.
And generative models address density estimations.
So this problem that we saw earlier of trying
to estimate the underlying distribution of your
training data which is a core problem
in unsupervised learning.
And we'll see that there's several flavors of this.
We can use generative models to do explicit density
estimation where we're going to explicitly define
and solve for our P model
or we can also do implicit density estimation
where in this case we'll learn a model that can
produce samples from P model without explicitly defining it.
So, why do we care about generative models?
Why is this a really interesting core problem
in unsupervised learning?
Well there's a lot of things that we can do
with generative models.
If we're able to create realistic samples from the data
distributions that we want we can do really cool things
with this, right?
We can generate just beautiful samples to start
with so on the left you can see a completely new samples of
just generated by these generative models.
Also in the center here generated samples of
images we can also do tasks like super resolution,
colorization so hallucinating or filling in these edges
with generated ideas of colors
and what the purse should look like.
We can also use generative models of time series data
for simulation and planning and so this will be useful in
for reinforcement learning applications
which we'll talk a bit more about reinforcement learning
in a later lecture.
And training generative models can also enable
inference of latent representations.
Learning latent features that can be useful
as general features for downstream tasks.
So if we look at types of generative models
these can be organized into the taxonomy here
where we have these two major branches that we talked about,
explicit density models and implicit density models.
And then we can also get down into many
of these other sub categories.
And well we can refer to this figure is adapted
from a tutorial on GANs from Ian Goodfellow
and so if you're interested in some
of these different taxonomy and categorizations of
generative models this is a good resource that you can take
a look at.
But today we're going to discuss three of the most
popular types of generative models that are in use
and in research today.
And so we'll talk first briefly about pixelRNNs and CNNs
And then we'll talk about variational autoencoders.
These are both types of explicit density models.
One that's using a tractable density
and another that's using an approximate density
And then we'll talk about generative adversarial networks,
GANs which are a type of implicit density estimation.
So let's first talk about pixelRNNs and CNNs.
So these are a type of fully visible belief networks
which are modeling a density explicitly
so in this case what they do is we have this
image data X that we have and we want to model the
probability or likelihood of this image P of X.
Right and so in this case, for these kinds of models,
we use the chain rule to decompose this likelihood
into a product of one dimensional distribution.
So we have here the probability of each pixel X I
conditioned on all previous pixels X1 through XI - 1.
and your likelihood all right, your joint likelihood
of all the pixels in your image is going to be the product
of all of these pixels together,
all of these likelihoods together.
And then once we define this likelihood,
in order to train this model we can just maximize
the likelihood of our training data
under this defined density.
So if we look at this this distribution over pixel values
right, we have this P of XI given all the previous
pixel values, well this is a really complex distribution.
So how can we model this?
Well we've seen before that if we want to have complex
transformations we can do these using neural networks.
Neural networks are a good way to express complex
transformations.
And so what we'll do is we'll use a neural network
to express this complex function that we have
of the distribution.
And one thing you'll see here is that,
okay even if we're going to use a neural network for this
another thing we have to take care of is how do we order
the pixels.
Right, I said here that we have a distribution
for P of XI given all previous pixels
but what does all previous the pixels mean?
So we'll take a look at that.
So PixelRNN was a model proposed in 2016
that basically defines a way for setting up and optimizing
this problem and so how this model works is
that we're going to generate pixels starting
in a corner of the image.
So we can look at this grid as basically the pixels
of your image and so what we're going to do is start
from the pixel in the upper left-hand corner
and then we're going to sequentially generate pixels based
on these connections from the arrows
that you can see here.
And each of the dependencies on the previous pixels
in this ordering is going to be modeled using an RNN
or more specifically an LSTM which we've seen before
in lecture.
Right so using this we can basically continue to move
forward just moving down a long is diagonal
and generating all of these pixel values dependent
on the pixels that they're connected to.
And so this works really well but the drawback here
is that this sequential generation, right,
so it's actually quite slow to do this.
You can imagine you know if you're going to generate a new
image instead of all of these feed forward networks that we
see, we've seen with CNNs.
Here we're going to have to iteratively go through
and generate all these images, all these pixels.
So a little bit later, after a pixelRNN,
another model called pixelCNN was introduced.
And this has very similar setup as pixelCNN
and we're still going to do this image generation
starting from the corner of the of the image and expanding
we're going to use the CNN instead.
And we're now going to use a CNN over a a context region
that you can see here around in the particular pixel
that we're going to generate now.
Right so we take the pixels around it,
this gray area within the region that's already been
generated and then we can pass this through a CNN
and use that to generate our next pixel value.
And so what this is going to give is this is going to give
This is a CNN, a neural network at each pixel location
right and so the output of this is going to be a soft
max loss over the pixel values here.
In this case we have a 0 to 255 and then we can train this
by maximizing the likelihood of the training images.
Right so we say that basically we want to take a training
image we're going to do this generation process
and at each pixel location we have the ground truth
training data image value that we have here
and this is a quick basically the label
or the the the classification label that we want
our pixel to be which of these 255 values
and we can train this using a Softmax loss.
Right and so basically the effect of doing this
is that we're going to maximize the likelihood
of our training data pixels being generated.
Okay any questions about this?
Yes.
[student's words obscured due to lack of microphone]
Yeah, so the question is, I thought we were talking
about unsupervised learning, why do we have basically
a classification label here?
The reason is that this loss, this output that we have
is the value of the input training data.
So we have no external labels, right?
We didn't go and have to manually collect any labels
for this, we're just taking our input data
and saying that this is what we used for the last function.
[student's words obscured due to lack of microphone]
The question is, is this like bag of words?
I would say it's not really bag of words,
it's more saying that we want where we're outputting
a distribution over pixel values at each location
of our image right, and what we want to do
is we want to maximize the likelihood of our input,
our training data being produced, being generated.
Right so, in that sense, this is why it's using our input
data to create our loss.
So using pixelCNN training is faster than pixelRNN
because here now right at every pixel location
we want to maximize the value of our,
we want to maximize the likelihood of our training data
showing up and so we have all of these values already right,
just from our training data and so we can do this much
faster but a generation time for a test time we want to
generate a completely new image right, just starting from
the corner and we're not, we're not trying to do any type
of learning so in that generation time we still
have to generate each of these pixel locations
before we can generate the next location.
And so generation time here it still slow even though
training time is faster.
Question.
[student's words obscured due to lack of microphone]
So the question is, is this training a sensitive
distribution to what you pick for the first pixel?
Yeah, so it is dependent on what you have as the initial
pixel distribution and then everything is conditioned
based on that.
So again, how do you pick this distribution?
So at training time you have these distributions
from your training data and then at generation time
you can just initialize this with either uniform
or from your training data, however you want.
And then once you have that everything else is conditioned
based on that.
Question.
[student's words obscured due to lack of microphone]
Yeah so the question is is there a way that we define
this in this chain rule fashion instead of predicting
all the pixels at one time?
And so we'll see, we'll see models later that do do this,
but what the chain rule allows us to do is it allows us
to find this very tractable density that we can then
basically optimize and do, directly optimizes likelihood
Okay so these are some examples of generations
from this model and so here on the left you can see
generations where the training data is CIFAR-10,
CIFAR-10 dataset.
And so you can see that in general they are starting
to capture statistics of natural images.
You can see general types of blobs
and kind of things that look like parts of natural images
coming out.
On the right here it's ImageNet, we can again see samples
from here and
these are starting to look like natural images
but they're still not, there's still room for improvement.
You can still see that there are differences obviously
with regional training images and some of the semantics
are not clear in here.
So, to summarize this, pixelRNNs and CNNs allow you
to explicitly compute likelihood P of X.
It's an explicit density that we can optimize.
And being able to do this also has another benefit
of giving a good evaluation metric.
You know you can kind of measure how good your samples are
by this likelihood of the data that you can compute.
And it's able to produce pretty good samples
but it's still an active area of research
and the main disadvantage of these methods is that
the generation is sequential and so it can be pretty slow.
And these kinds of methods have also been used
for generating audio for example.
And you can look online for some pretty interesting examples
of this, but again the drawback is that it takes a long time
to generate these samples.
And so there's a lot of work, has been work since then
on still on improving pixelCNN performance
And so all kinds of different you know architecture changes
add the loss function formulating this differently
on different types of training tricks
And so if you're interested in learning more about this
you can look at some of these papers on PixelCNN
and then other pixelCNN plus plus better improved version
that came out this year.
Okay so now we're going to talk about another type
of generative models call variational autoencoders.
And so far we saw that pixelCNNs defined a tractable
density function, right, using this this definition
and based on that we can optimize directly optimize
the likelihood of the training data.
So with variational autoencoders now we're going to define
an intractable density function.
We're now going to model this with an additional latent
variable Z and we'll talk in more detail
about how this looks.
And so our data likelihood P of X is now basically
has to be this integral right,
taking the expectation over all possible values of Z.
And so this now is going to be a problem.
We'll see that we cannot optimize this directly.
And so instead what we have to do is we have to derive
and optimize a lower bound on the likelihood instead.
Yeah, question.
So the question is is what is Z?
Z is a latent variable and I'll go through this
in much more detail.
So let's talk about some background first.
Variational autoencoders are related to a type of
unsupervised learning model called autoencoders.
And so we'll talk little bit more first about autoencoders
and what they are and then I'll explain how variational
autoencoders are related and build off of this
and allow you to generate data.
So with autoencoders we don't use this to generate data,
but it's an unsupervised approach for learning a lower
dimensional feature representation
from unlabeled training data.
All right so in this case we have our input data X
and then we're going to want to learn some features
that we call Z.
And then we'll have an encoder that's going to be a mapping,
a function mapping from this input data
to our feature Z.
And this encoder can take many different forms right,
they would generally use neural networks so originally
these models have been around, autoencoders have been
around for a long time.
So in the 2000s we used linear layers of non-linearities,
then later on we had fully connected deeper networks
and then after that we moved on to using CNNs for these
encoders.
So we take our input data X and then we map this
to some feature Z.
And Z we usually have as, we usually specify this
to be smaller than X and we perform basically dimensionality
reduction because of that.
So the question who has an idea of why do we want to do
dimensionality reduction here?
Why do we want Z to be smaller than X?
Yeah.
[student's words obscured due to lack of microphone]
So the answer I heard is Z should represent the most
important features in X and that's correct.
So we want Z to be able to learn features that can capture
meaningful factors of variation in the data.
Right this makes them good features.
So how can we learn this feature representation?
Well the way autoencoders do this is that we train
the model such that the features can be used to reconstruct
our original data.
So what we want is we want to have input data that we use
an encoder to map it to some lower dimensional features Z.
This is the output of the encoder network,
and we want to be able to take these features that were
produced based on this input data and then use a decoder
a second network and be able to output now something
of the same size dimensionality as X and have it be similar
to X right so we want to be able to reconstruct the original
data.
And again for the decoder we are basically using same types
of networks as encoders so it's usually a little bit
symmetric and now we can use CNN networks
for most of these.
Okay so the process is going to be we're going to take
our input data right we pass it through our encoder first
which is going to be something for example like a four layer
convolutional network and then we're going to pass it,
get these features and then we're going to pass it through
a decoder which is a four layer for example upconvolutional
network and then get a reconstructed data out at the end
of this.
Right in the reason why we have a convolutional network
for the encoder and an upconvolutional network
for the decoder is because at the encoder we're basically
taking it from this high dimensional input to these lower
dimensional features and now we want to go the other way
go from our low dimensional features back out to our
high dimensional reconstructed input.
And so in order to get this effect that we said we wanted
before of being able to reconstruct our input data
we'll use something like an L2 loss function.
Right that basically just says let me make my pixels
of my input data to be the same as my,
my pixels in my reconstructed data to be the same
as the pixels of my input data.
An important thing to notice here,
this relates back to a question that we had earlier,
is that even though we have this loss function here,
there's no, there's no external labels that are being used
in training this.
All we have is our training data that we're going to use
both to pass through the network as well as to compute
our loss function.
So once we have this after training this model
what we can do is we can throw away this decoder.
All this was used was too to be able to produce our
reconstruction input and be able to compute our loss
function.
And we can use the encoder that we have which produces our
feature mapping and we can use this to initialize
a supervised model.
Right and so for example we can now go from this input
to our features and then have an additional classifier
network on top of this that now we can use to output
a class label for example for classification problem
we can have external labels from here
and use our standard loss functions like Softmax.
And so the value of this is that we basically were able
to use a lot of unlabeled training data to try and learn
good general feature representations.
Right, and now we can use this to initialize a supervised
learning problem where sometimes we don't have so much data
we only have small data.
And we've seen in previous homeworks and classes
that with small data it's hard to learn a model, right?
You can have over fitting and all kinds of problems
and so this allows you to initialize your model first
with better features.
Okay so we saw that autoencoders are able to reconstruct
data and are able to, as a result, learn features
to initialize, that we can use to initialize a supervised
model.
And we saw that these features that we learned
have this intuition of being able to capture factors
of variation in the training data.
All right so based on this intuition of okay these,
we can have this latent this vector Z which has
factors of variation in our training data.
Now a natural question is well can we use a similar type
of setup to generate new images?
And so now we will talk about variational autoencoders
which is a probabillstic spin on autoencoders that will let
us sample from the model in order to generate new data.
Okay any questions on autoencoders first?
Okay, so variational autoencoders.
All right so here we assume that our training data
that we have X I from one to N
is generated from some underlying, unobserved
latent representation Z.
Right, so it's this intuition that Z is some vector
right which element of Z is capturing how little
or how much of some factor of variation that we have
in our training data.
Right so the intuition is, you know, maybe these could
be something like different kinds of attributes.
Let's say we're trying to generate faces,
it could be how much of a smile is on the face,
it could be position of the eyebrows hair
orientation of the head.
These are all possible types of latent factors
that could be learned.
Right, and so our generation process is that we're going to
sample from a prior over Z.
Right so for each of these attributes for example,
you know, how much smile that there is,
we can have a prior over what sort of distribution
we think that there should be for this so,
a gaussian is something that's a natural prior
that we can use for each of these factors of Z
and then we're going to generate our data X
by sampling from a conditional, conditional distribution
P of X given Z.
So we sample Z first, we sample a value for each of these
latent factors and then we'll use that
and sample our image X from here.
And so the true parameters of this generation process
are theta, theta star right?
So we have the parameters of our prior
and our conditional distributions
and what we want to do is in order to have a generative
model be able to generate new data
we want to estimate these parameters of our true parameters
Okay so let's first talk about how should we represent
this model.
All right, so if we're going to have a model for this generator
process, well we've already said before that we can choose
our prior P of Z to be something simple.
Something like a Gaussian, right?
And this is the reasonable thing to choose for
for latent attributes.
Now for our conditional distribution P of X given Z
this is much more complex right,
because we need to use this to generate an image
and so for P of X given Z, well as we saw before,
when we have some type of complex function that we want
to represent we can represent this with a neural network.
And so that's a natural choice for let's try and model
P of X given Z with a neural network.
And we're going to call this the decoder network.
Right, so we're going to think about taking some latent
representation and trying to decode this into the image
that it's specifying.
So now how can we train this model?
Right, we want to be able to train this model so that we can
learn an estimate of these parameters.
So if we remember our strategy from training generative
models, back from are fully visible belief networks,
our pixelRNNs and CNNs,
a straightforward natural strategy is to try
and learn these model parameters in order to maximize
the likelihood of the training data.
Right, so we saw earlier that in this case,
with our latent variable Z, we're going to have
to write out P of X taking expectation over all possible
values of Z which is continuous and so we get this
expression here.
Right so now we have it with this latent Z
and now if we're going to, if you want to try and maximize
its likelihood, well what's the problem?
Can we just take this take gradients and maximize
this likelihood?
[student's words obscured due to lack of microphone]
Right, so this integral is not going to be tractable,
that's correct.
So let's take a look at this in a little bit more detail.
Right, so we have our data likelihood term here.
And the first time is P of Z.
And here we already said earlier, we can just choose this
to be a simple Gaussian prior, so this is fine.
P of X given Z, well we said we were going to
specify a decoder neural network.
So given any Z, we can get P of X given Z from here.
It's the output of our neural network.
But then what's the problem here?
Okay this was supposed to be a different unhappy face
but somehow I don't know what happened,
in the process of translation,
it turned into a crying black ghost
but what this is symbolizing is that basically if we want
to compute P of X given Z
for every Z this is now intractable right,
we cannot compute this integral.
So data likelihood is intractable
and it turns out that if we look at other terms
in this model if we look at our posterior density,
So P of our posterior of Z given X,
then this is going to be P of X given Z
times P of Z over P of X by Bayes' rule
and this is also going to be intractable, right.
We have P of X given Z is okay, P of Z is okay,
but we have this P of X our likelihood
which has the integral and it's intractable.
So we can't directly optimizes this.
but we'll see that a solution,
a solution that will enable us to learn this model
is if in addition to using a decoder network
defining this neural network to model P of X given Z.
If we now define an additional encoder network
Q of Z given X we're going to call this an encoder
because we want to turn our input X into,
get the likelihood of Z given X,
we're going to encode this into Z.
And defined this network to approximate
the P of Z given X.
Right this was posterior density term now is also
intractable.
If we use this additional network to approximate this
then we'll see that this will actually allow us to derive
a lower bound on the data likelihood that is tractable
and which we can optimize.
Okay so