- Hello?
Okay, it's after 12, so I want to get started.
So today, lecture eight, we're going to talk about
deep learning software.
This is a super exciting topic because it changes
a lot every year.
But also means it's a lot of work to give this lecture
'cause it changes a lot every year.
But as usual, a couple administrative notes
before we dive into the material.
So as a reminder the project proposals for your
course projects were due on Tuesday.
So hopefully you all turned that in,
and hopefully you all have a somewhat good idea
of what kind of projects you want to work on
for the class.
So we're in the process of assigning TA's to projects
based on what the project area is
and the expertise of the TA's.
So we'll have some more information about that
in the next couple days I think.
We're also in the process of grading assignment one,
so stay tuned and we'll get those grades back to you
as soon as we can.
Another reminder is that assignment two has been out
for a while.
That's going to be due next week, a week from today, Thursday.
And again, when working on assignment two,
remember to stop your Google Cloud instances
when you're not working to try to preserve your credits.
And another bit of confusion, I just wanted to
re-emphasize is that for assignment two you really
only need to use GPU instances for the last notebook.
For all of the several notebooks it's just in Python
and Numpy so you don't need any GPUs for those questions.
So again, conserve your credits,
only use GPUs when you need them.
And the final reminder is that the midterm is coming up.
It's kind of hard to believe we're there already,
but the midterm will be in class on Tuesday, five nine.
So the midterm will be more theoretical.
It'll be sort of pen and paper working through different
kinds of, slightly more theoretical questions
to check your understanding of the material that we've
covered so far.
And I think we'll probably post at least a short sort of
sample of the types of questions to expect.
Question?
[student's words obscured due to lack of microphone]
Oh yeah, question is whether it's open-book,
so we're going to say closed note, closed book.
So just,
Yeah, yeah, so that's what we've done in the past
is just closed note, closed book, relatively
just like want to check that you understand
the intuition behind most of the stuff we've presented.
So, a quick recap as a reminder of what we were talking
about last time.
Last time we talked about fancier optimization algorithms
for deep learning models including SGD Momentum,
Nesterov, RMSProp and Adam.
And we saw that these relatively small tweaks
on top of vanilla SGD, are relatively easy to implement
but can make your networks converge a bit faster.
We also talked about regularization,
especially dropout.
So remember dropout, you're kind of randomly setting
parts of the network to zero during the forward pass,
and then you kind of marginalize out over that noise
in the back at test time.
And we saw that this was kind of a general pattern
across many different types of regularization
in deep learning, where you might add some kind
of noise during training, but then marginalize out
that noise at test time so it's not stochastic
at test time.
We also talked about transfer learning where you
can maybe download big networks that were pre-trained
on some dataset and then fine tune them for your
own problem.
And this is one way that you can attack a lot of problems
in deep learning, even if you don't have a huge
dataset of your own.
So today we're going to shift gears a little bit
and talk about some of the nuts and bolts
about writing software and how the hardware works.
And a little bit, diving into a lot of details
about what the software looks like that you actually
use to train these things in practice.
So we'll talk a little bit about CPUs and GPUs
and then we'll talk about several of the major
deep learning frameworks that are out there in use
these days.
So first, we've sort of mentioned this off hand
a bunch of different times,
that computers have CPUs, computers have GPUs.
Deep learning uses GPUs, but we weren't really
too explicit up to this point about what exactly
these things are and why one might be better
than another for different tasks.
So, who's built a computer before?
Just kind of show of hands.
So, maybe about a third of you, half of you,
somewhere around that ballpark.
So this is a shot of my computer at home
that I built.
And you can see that there's a lot of stuff going on
inside the computer, maybe, hopefully you know
what most of these parts are.
And the CPU is the Central Processing Unit.
That's this little chip hidden under this cooling fan
right here near the top of the case.
And the CPU is actually relatively small piece.
It's a relatively small thing inside the case.
It's not taking up a lot of space.
And the GPUs are these two big monster things
that are taking up a gigantic amount of space
in the case.
They have their own cooling,
they're taking a lot of power.
They're quite large.
So, just in terms of how much power they're using,
in terms of how big they are, the GPUs are kind of
physically imposing and taking up a lot of space
in the case.
So the question is what are these things
and why are they so important for deep learning?
Well, the GPU is called a graphics card,
or Graphics Processing Unit.
And these were really developed, originally for rendering
computer graphics, and especially around games
and that sort of thing.
So another show of hands, who plays video games at home
sometimes, from time to time on their computer?
Yeah, so again, maybe about half, good fraction.
So for those of you who've played video games before
and who've built your own computers,
you probably have your own opinions on this debate.
[laughs]
So this is one of those big debates in computer science.
You know, there's like Intel versus AMD,
NVIDIA versus AMD for graphics cards.
It's up there with Vim versus Emacs for text editor.
And pretty much any gamer has their own opinions
on which of these two sides they prefer
for their own cards.
And in deep learning we kind of have mostly picked
one side of this fight, and that's NVIDIA.
So if you guys have AMD cards,
you might be in a little bit more trouble if you want
to use those for deep learning.
And really, NVIDIA's been pushing a lot for deep learning
in the last several years.
It's been kind of a large focus of some of their strategy.
And they put in a lot effort into engineering
sort of good solutions to make their hardware
better suited for deep learning.
So most people in deep learning when we talk about GPUs,
we're pretty much exclusively talking about NVIDIA GPUs.
Maybe in the future this'll change a little bit,
and there might be new players coming up,
but at least for now NVIDIA is pretty dominant.
So to give you an idea of like what is the difference
between a CPU and a GPU, I've kind of made a little
spread sheet here.
On the top we have two of the kind of top end Intel
consumer CPUs, and on the bottom we have two of
NVIDIA's sort of current top end consumer GPUs.
And there's a couple general trends to notice here.
Both GPUs and CPUs are kind of a general purpose
computing machine where they can execute programs
and do sort of arbitrary instructions,
but they're qualitatively pretty different.
So CPUs tend to have just a few cores,
for consumer desktop CPUs these days,
they might have something like four or six
or maybe up to 10 cores.
With hyperthreading technology that means they can run,
the hardware can physically run, like maybe eight
or up to 20 threads concurrently.
So the CPU can maybe do 20 things in parallel at once.
So that's just not a gigantic number,
but those threads for a CPU are pretty powerful.
They can actually do a lot of things,
they're very fast.
Every CPU instruction can actually do quite a lot
of stuff.
And they can all work pretty independently.
For GPUs it's a little bit different.
So for GPUs we see that these sort of common top end
consumer GPUs have thousands of cores.
So the NVIDIA Titan XP which is the current
top of the line consumer GPU has 3840 cores.
So that's a crazy number.
That's like way more than the 10 cores that you'll get
for a similarly priced CPU.
The downside of a GPU is that each of those cores,
one, it runs at a much slower clock speed.
And two they really can't do quite as much.
You can't really compare CPU cores and GPU cores
apples to apples.
The GPU cores can't really operate very independently.
They all kind of need to work together
and sort of paralyze one task across many cores
rather than each core totally doing its own thing.
So you can't really compare these numbers directly.
But it should give you the sense that due
to the large number of cores GPUs can sort of,
are really good for parallel things where you
need to do a lot of things all at the same time,
but those things are all pretty much the same flavor.
Another thing to point out between CPUs and GPUs
is this idea of memory.
Right, so CPUs have some cache on the CPU,
but that's relatively small and the majority
of the memory for your CPU is pulling from your
system memory, the RAM, which will maybe be like
eight, 12, 16, 32 gigabytes of RAM on a typical
consumer desktop these days.
Whereas GPUs actually have their own RAM built
into the chip.
There's a pretty large bottleneck communicating
between the RAM in your system and the GPU,
so the GPUs typically have their own
relatively large block of memory within the card itself.
And for the Titan XP, which again is maybe the current
top of the line consumer card,
this thing has 12 gigabytes of memory local to the GPU.
GPUs also have their own caching system
where there are sort of multiple hierarchies of caching
between the 12 gigabytes of GPU memory
and the actual GPU cores.
And that's somewhat similar to the caching hierarchy
that you might see in a CPU.
So, CPUs are kind of good for general purpose processing.
They can do a lot of different things.
And GPUs are maybe more specialized for these highly
paralyzable algorithms.
So the prototypical algorithm of something that works
really really well and is like perfectly suited
to a GPU is matrix multiplication.
So remember in matrix multiplication on the left
we've got like a matrix composed of a bunch of rows.
We multiply that on the right by another matrix composed
of a bunch of columns and then this produces
another, a final matrix where each element in the
output matrix is a dot product between one of the rows
and one of the columns of the two input matrices.
And these dot products are all independent.
Like you could imagine, for this output matrix
you could split it up completely
and have each of those different elements
of the output matrix all being computed in parallel
and they all sort of are running the same computation
which is taking a dot product of these two vectors.
But exactly where they're reading that data from
is from different places in the two input matrices.
So you could imagine that for a GPU you can just
like blast this out and have all of this elements
of the output matrix all computed in parallel
and that could make this thing computer super super fast
on GPU.
So that's kind of the prototypical type of problem
that like where a GPU is really well suited,
where a CPU might have to go in and step through
sequentially and compute each of these elements
one by one.
That picture is a little bit of a caricature because
CPUs these days have multiple cores,
they can do vectorized instructions as well,
but still, for these like massively parallel problems
GPUs tend to have much better throughput.
Especially when these matrices get really really big.
And by the way, convolution is kind of the same
kind of story.
Where you know in convolution we have this input tensor,
we have this weight tensor and then every point in the
output tensor after a convolution is again some inner
product between some part of the weights
and some part of the input.
And you can imagine that a GPU could really paralyze
this computation, split it all up across the many cores
and compute it very quickly.
So that's kind of the general flavor of the types
of problems where GPUs give you a huge speed advantage
over CPUs.
So you can actually write programs that run directly
on GPUs.
So NVIDIA has this CUDA abstraction that lets you write
code that kind of looks like C,
but executes directly on the GPUs.
But CUDA code is really really tricky.
It's actually really tough to write CUDA code that's
performant and actually squeezes all the juice out
of these GPUs.
You have to be very careful managing the memory hierarchy
and making sure you don't have cache misses
and branch mispredictions and all that sort of stuff.
So it's actually really really hard to write performant
CUDA code on your own.
So as a result NVIDIA has released a lot of libraries
that implement common computational primitives
that are very very highly optimized for GPUs.
So for example NVIDIA has a cuBLAS library that implements
different kinds of matrix multiplications
and different matrix operations that are super optimized,
run really well on GPU, get very close to sort of
theoretical peak hardware utilization.
Similarly they have a cuDNN library which implements
things like convolution, forward and backward passes,
batch normalization, recurrent networks,
all these kinds of computational primitives
that we need in deep learning.
NVIDIA has gone in there and released their own binaries
that compute these primitives very efficiently
on NVIDIA hardware.
So in practice, you tend not to end up writing your own
CUDA code for deep learning.
You typically are just mostly calling into existing
code that other people have written.
Much of which is the stuff which has been heavily
optimized by NVIDIA already.
There's another sort of language called OpenCL
which is a bit more general.
Runs on more than just NVIDIA GPUs,
can run on AMD hardware, can run on CPUs,
but OpenCL, nobody's really spent a really large amount
of effort and energy trying to get optimized deep learning
primitives for OpenCL, so it tends to be a lot less
performant the super optimized versions in CUDA.
So maybe in the future we might see a bit of a more open
standard and we might see this across many different
more types of platforms, but at least for now,
NVIDIA's kind of the main game in town for deep learning.
So you can check, there's a lot of different resources
for learning about how you can do GPU programming yourself.
It's kind of fun.
It's sort of a different paradigm of writing code
because it's this massively parallel architecture,
but that's a bit beyond the scope of this course.
And again, you don't really need to write your own
CUDA code much in practice for deep learning.
And in fact, I've never written my own CUDA code
for any research project, so,
but it is kind of useful to know like how it works
and what are the basic ideas even if you're not
writing it yourself.
So if you want to look at kind of CPU GPU performance
in practice, I did some benchmarks last summer
comparing a decent Intel CPU
against a bunch of different GPUs that were sort
of near top of the line at that time.
And these were my own benchmarks that you can find
more details on GitHub, but my findings were that
for things like VGG 16 and 19, ResNets, various ResNets,
then you typically see something like a 65 to 75 times
speed up when running the exact same computation
on a top of the line GPU, in this case a Pascal Titan X,
versus a top of the line, well, not quite top of the line
CPU, which in this case was an Intel E5 processor.
Although, I'd like to make one sort of caveat here
is that you always need to be super careful
whenever you're reading any kind of benchmarks
about deep learning, because it's super easy to be
unfair between different things.
And you kind of need to know a lot of the details about
what exactly is being benchmarked in order to know
whether or not the comparison is fair.
So in this case I'll come right out and tell you
that probably this comparison is a little bit unfair
to CPU because I didn't spend a lot of effort
trying to squeeze the maximal performance
out of CPUs.
I probably could have tuned the blast libraries better
for the CPU performance.
And I probably could have gotten these numbers
a bit better.
This was sort of out of the box performance
between just installing Torch, running it on a CPU,
just installing Torch running it on a GPU.
So this is kind of out of the box performance,
but it's not really like peak, possible, theoretical
throughput on the CPU.
But that being said, I think there are still pretty
substantial speed ups to be had here.
Another kind of interesting outcome from this benchmarking
was comparing these optimized cuDNN libraries
from NVIDIA for convolution and whatnot versus
sort of more naive CUDA that had been hand written
out in the open source community.
And you can see that if you compare the same networks
on the same hardware with the same deep learning
framework and the only difference is swapping out
these cuDNN versus sort of hand written, less optimized
CUDA you can see something like nearly a three X speed up
across the board when you switch from the relatively
simple CUDA to these like super optimized cuDNN
implementations.
So in general, whenever you're writing code on GPU,
you should probably almost always like just make sure
you're using cuDNN because you're leaving probably
a three X performance boost on the table if you're
not calling into cuDNN for your stuff.
So another problem that comes up in practice,
when you're training these things is that
you know, your model is maybe sitting on the GPU,
the weights of the model are in that 12 gigabytes
of local storage on the GPU, but your big dataset
is sitting over on the right on a hard drive
or an SSD or something like that.
So if you're not careful you can actually bottleneck
your training by just trying to read the data
off the disk.
'Cause the GPU is super fast, it can compute
forward and backward quite fast, but if you're reading
sequentially off a spinning disk, you can actually
bottleneck your training quite,
and that can be really bad and slow you down.
So some solutions here are that like you know
if your dataset's really small, sometimes you might just
read the whole dataset into RAM.
Or even if your dataset isn't so small,
but you have a giant server with a ton of RAM,
you might do that anyway.
You can also make sure you're using an SSD instead
of a hard drive, that can help a lot with read throughput.
Another common strategy is to use multiple threads
on the CPU that are pre-fetching data off RAM
or off disk, buffering it in memory, in RAM so that
then you can continue feeding that buffer data down
to the GPU with good performance.
This is a little bit painful to set up,
but again like, these GPU's are so fast that
if you're not really careful with trying to feed
them data as quickly as possible,
just reading the data can sometimes bottleneck
the whole training process.
So that's something to be aware of.
So that's kind of the brief introduction to like
sort of GPU CPU hardware in practice when it comes
to deep learning.
And then I wanted to switch gears a little bit
and talk about the software side of things.
The various deep learning frameworks that people are using
in practice.
But I guess before I move on,
is there any sort of questions about CPU GPU?
Yeah, question?
[student's words obscured due to lack of microphone]
Yeah, so the question is what can you sort of,
what can you do mechanically when you're coding
to avoid these problems?
Probably the biggest thing you can do in software
is set up sort of pre-fetching on the CPU.
Like you couldn't like, sort of a naive thing
would be you have this sequential process where you
first read data off disk, wait for the data,
wait for the minibatch to be read,
then feed the minibatch to the GPU,
then go forward and backward on the GPU,
then read another minibatch and sort of do this all
in sequence.
And if you actually have multiple,
like instead you might have CPU threads running in the
background that are fetching data off the disk
such that while the,
you can sort of interleave all of these things.
Like the GPU is computing,
the CPU background threads are feeding data off disk
and your main thread is kind of waiting for these things to,
just doing a bit of synchronization between these things
so they're all happening in parallel.
And thankfully if you're using some of these deep learning
frameworks that we're about to talk about,
then some of this work has already been done for you
'cause it's a little bit painful.
So the landscape of deep learning frameworks
is super fast moving.
So last year when I gave this lecture I talked mostly
about Caffe, Torch, Theano and TensorFlow.
And when I last gave this talk, again more than a year ago,
TensorFlow was relatively new.
It had not seen super widespread adoption yet at that time.
But now I think in the last year TensorFlow
has gotten much more popular.
It's probably the main framework of choice for many people.
So that's a big change.
We've also seen a ton of new frameworks
sort of popping up like mushrooms in the last year.
So in particular Caffe2 and PyTorch are new frameworks
from Facebook that I think are pretty interesting.
There's also a ton of other frameworks.
Paddle, Baidu has Paddle, Microsoft has CNTK,
Amazon is mostly using MXNet and there's a ton
of other frameworks as well, but I'm less familiar with,
and really don't have time to get into.
But one interesting thing to point out from this picture
is that kind of the first generation of deep learning
frameworks that really saw wide adoption
were built in academia.
So Caffe was from Berkeley, Torch was developed
originally NYU and also in collaboration with Facebook.
And Theana was mostly build at the University of Montreal.
But these kind of next generation deep learning
frameworks all originated in industry.
So Caffe2 is from Facebook, PyTorch is from Facebook.
TensorFlow is from Google.
So it's kind of an interesting shift that we've seen
in the landscape over the last couple of years
is that these ideas have really moved a lot
from academia into industry.
And now industry is kind of giving us these big powerful
nice frameworks to work with.
So today I wanted to mostly talk about PyTorch
and TensorFlow 'cause I personally think that those
are probably the ones you should be focusing on for
a lot of research type problems these days.
I'll also talk a bit about Caffe and Caffe2.
But probably a little bit less emphasis on those.
And before we move any farther, I thought I should make
my own biases a little bit more explicit.
So I have mostly, I've worked with Torch mostly
for the last several years.
And I've used it quite a lot, I like it a lot.
And then in the last year I've mostly switched to PyTorch
as my main research framework.
So I have a little bit less experience with some
of these others, especially TensorFlow,
but I'll still try to do my best to give you a fair
picture and a decent overview of these things.
So, remember that in the last several lectures
we've hammered this idea of computational graphs in
sort of over and over.
That whenever you're doing deep learning,
you want to think about building some computational graph
that computes whatever function that you want to compute.
So in the case of a linear classifier you'll combine
your data X and your weights W with a matrix multiply.
You'll do some kind of hinge loss to maybe have,
compute your loss.
You'll have some regularization term
and you imagine stitching together all these different
operations into some graph structure.
Remember that these graph structures can get pretty
complex in the case of a big neural net,
now there's many different layers,
many different activations.
Many different weights spread all around in a pretty
complex graph.
And as you move to things like neural turing machines
then you can get these really crazy computational graphs
that you can't even really draw because they're
so big and messy.
So the point of deep learning frameworks is really,
there's really kind of three main reasons why you might
want to use one of these deep learning frameworks
rather than just writing your own code.
So the first would be that these frameworks enable
you to easily build and work with these big hairy
computational graphs without kind of worrying
about a lot of those bookkeeping details yourself.
Another major idea is that,
whenever we're working in deep learning
we always need to compute gradients.
We're always computing some loss,
we're always computer gradient of our weight
with respect to the loss.
And we'd like to make this automatically computing gradient,
you don't want to have to write that code yourself.
You want that framework to handle all these back propagation
details for you so you can just think about
writing down the forward pass of your network
and have the backward pass sort of come out for free
without any additional work.
And finally you want all this stuff to run efficiently
on GPUs so you don't have to worry too much about these
low level hardware details about cuBLAS and cuDNN
and CUDA and moving data between the CPU and GPU memory.
You kind of want all those messy details to be taken care of
for you.
So those are kind of some of the major reasons
why you might choose to use frameworks rather than
writing your own stuff from scratch.
So as kind of a concrete example of a computational graph
we can maybe write down this super simple thing.
Where we have three inputs, X, Y, and Z.
We're going to combine X and Y to produce A.
Then we're going to combine A and Z to produce B
and then finally we're going to do some maybe summing out
operation on B to give some scaler final result C.
So you've probably written enough Numpy code at this point
to realize that it's super easy to write down,
to implement this computational graph,
or rather to implement this bit of computation in Numpy,
right?
You can just kind of write down in Numpy that you want to
generate some random data, you want to multiply two things,
you want to add two things, you want to sum out a couple things.
And it's really easy to do this in Numpy.
But then the question is like suppose that we want
to compute the gradient of C with respect to X, Y, and Z.
So, if you're working in Numpy, you kind of need to write out
this backward pass yourself.
And you've gotten a lot of practice with this on the
homeworks, but it can be kind of a pain
and a little bit annoying and messy once you get to
really big complicated things.
The other problem with Numpy is that it doesn't run
on the GPU.
So Numpy is definitely CPU only.
And you're never going to be able to experience
or take advantage of these GPU accelerated speedups
if you're stuck working in Numpy.
And it's, again, it's a pain to have to compute
your own gradients in all these situations.
So, kind of the goal of most deep learning frameworks
these days is to let you write code in the forward pass
that looks very similar to Numpy,
but lets you run it on the GPU
and lets you automatically compute gradients.
And that's kind of the big picture goal of most of these
frameworks.
So if you imagine looking at, if we look at an example
in TensorFlow of the exact same computational graph,
we now see that in this forward pass,
you write this code that ends up looking very very similar
to the Numpy forward pass where you're kind of doing
these multiplication and these addition operations.
But now TensorFlow has this magic line that just
computes all the gradients for you.
So now you don't have go in and write your own backward pass
and that's much more convenient.
The other nice thing about TensorFlow is you can really
just, like with one line you can switch all this computation
between CPU and GPU.
So here, if you just add this with statement
before you're doing this forward pass,
you just can explicitly tell the framework,
hey I want to run this code on the CPU.
But now if we just change that with statement a little bit
with just with a one character change in this case,
changing that C to a G, now the code runs on GPU.
And now in this little code snippet,
we've solved these two problems.
We're running our code on the GPU
and we're having the framework compute all the gradients
for us, so that's really nice.
And PyTorch kind looks almost exactly the same.
So again, in PyTorch you kind of write down,
you define some variables,
you have some forward pass and the forward pass again
looks very similar to like, in this case identical
to the Numpy code.
And then again, you can just use PyTorch to compute
gradients, all your gradients with just one line.
And now in PyTorch again, it's really easy to switch
to GPU, you just need to cast all your stuff to the
CUDA data type before you rung your computation
and now everything runs transparently on the GPU for you.
So if you kind of just look at these three examples,
these three snippets of code side by side,
the Numpy, the TensorFlow and the PyTorch
you see that the TensorFlow and the PyTorch code
664%0