- All right welcome to lecture nine.
So today we will be talking about CNN Architectures.
And just a few administrative points
before we get started, assignment two is due Thursday.
The mid term will be in class on Tuesday May ninth,
so next week and it will cover material through Tuesday
through this coming Thursday May fourth.
So everything up to recurrent neural networks
are going to be fair game.
The poster session we've decided on a time,
it's going to be Tuesday June sixth
from twelve to three p.m.
So this is the last week of classes.
So we have our our poster session a little bit early
during the last week so that after that,
once you guys get feedback you still have some time
to work for your final report which will be due finals week.
Okay, so just a quick review of last time.
Last time we talked about different kinds of
deep learning frameworks.
We talked about you know PyTorch, TensorFlow,
Caffe2
and we saw that using these kinds of frameworks
we were able to easily build big computational graphs,
for example very large neural networks and comm nets,
and be able to really easily compute gradients
in these graphs.
So to compute all of the gradients for all the intermediate
variables weights inputs and use that to train our models
and to run all this efficiently on GPUs
And we saw that for a lot of these frameworks
the way this works is by working with these modularized
layers that you guys have been working writing with,
in your home works as well where we have a forward pass,
we have a backward pass,
and then in our final model architecture,
all we need to do then is to just define
all of these sequence of layers together.
So using that we're able to very easily be able to
build up very complex network architectures.
So today we're going to talk about some specific kinds
of CNN Architectures that are used today in cutting edge
applications and research.
And so we'll go into depth in some of the most commonly
used architectures for these that are winners
of ImageNet classification benchmarks.
So in chronological order AlexNet, VGG net,
GoogLeNet, and ResNet.
And so these will go into a lot of depth.
And then I'll also after that, briefly go through
some other architectures that are not
as prominently used these days, but are interesting
either from a historical perspective,
or as recent areas of research.
Okay, so just a quick review.
We talked a long time ago about LeNet,
which was one of the first instantiations of a comNet
that was successfully used in practice.
And so this was the comNet that took an input image,
used com filters five by five filters
applied at stride one and had a couple of conv layers,
a few pooling layers and then some fully connected layers
at the end.
And this fairly simple comNet was very successfully applied
to digit recognition.
So AlexNet from 2012 which you guys have also heard
already before in previous classes,
was the first large scale convolutional neural network
that was able to do well on the ImageNet classification
task so in 2012 AlexNet was entered in the competition,
and was able to outperform all previous non deep
learning based models by a significant margin,
and so this was the comNet that started the spree
of comNet research and usage afterwards.
And so the basic comNet AlexNet architecture
is a conv layer followed by pooling layer,
normalization, com pool norm,
and then a few more conv layers, a pooling layer,
and then several fully connected layers afterwards.
So this actually looks very similar to the LeNet network
that we just saw.
There's just more layers in total.
There is five of these conv layers,
and two fully connected layers before
the final fully connected layer going to the output
classes.
So let's first get a sense of the sizes involved
in the AlexNet.
So if we look at the input to the AlexNet
this was trained on ImageNet, with inputs
at a size 227 by 227 by 3 images.
And if we look at this first layer which is a conv layer
for the AlexNet, it's 11 by 11 filters,
96 of these applied at stride 4.
So let's just think about this for a moment.
What's the output volume size of this first layer?
And there's a hint.
So remember we have our input size,
we have our convolutional filters, ray.
And we have this formula, which is the hint over here
that gives you the size of the output dimensions
after applying com right?
So remember it was the full image, minus the filter size,
divided by the stride, plus one.
So given that that's written up here for you 55,
does anyone have a guess at what's the final output size
after this conv layer?
[student speaks off mic]
- So I had 55 by 55 by 96, yep.
That's correct.
Right so our spatial dimensions at the output
are going to be 55 in each dimension and then we have
96 total filters so the depth after our conv layer
is going to be 96.
So that's the output volume.
And what's the total number of parameters in this layer?
So remember we have 96 11 by 11 filters.
[student speaks off mic]
- [Lecturer] 96 by 11 by 11, almost.
So yes, so I had another by three,
yes that's correct.
So each of the filters is going to
see through a local region of 11 by 11 by three,
right because the input depth was three.
And so, that's each filter size, times we have 96
of these total.
And so there's 35K parameters in this first layer.
Okay, so now if we look at the second layer
this is a pooling layer right and in this case
we have three three by three filters applied at stride two.
So what's the output volume of this layer after pooling?
And again we have a hint, very similar to the last question.
Okay, 27 by 27 by 96.
Yes that's correct.
Right so the pooling layer is basically going to use
this formula that we had here.
Again because these are pooling applied at a stride of two
so we're going to use the same formula to determine
the spatial dimensions and so the spatial dimensions
are going to be 27 by 27, and pooling preserves
the depth.
So we had 96 as depth as input,
and it's still going to be 96 depth
at output.
And next question.
What's the number of parameters in this layer?
I hear some muttering.
[student answers off mic]
- Nothing.
Okay.
Yes, so pooling layer has no parameters, so,
kind of a trick question.
Okay, so we can basically, yes, question?
[student speaks off mic]
- The question is, why are there no parameters in the
pooling layer?
The parameters are the weights right,
that we're trying to learn.
And so convolutional layers have weights that we learn
but pooling all we do is have a rule,
we look at the pooling region,
and we take the max.
So there's no parameters that are learned.
So we can keep on doing this and you can just repeat
the process and it's kind of a good exercise to go through
this and figure out the sizes, the parameters,
at every layer.
And so if you do this all the way,
you can look at this is the final architecture
that you can work with.
There's 11 by 11 filters at the beginning,
then five by five and some three by three filters.
And so these are generally pretty familiar looking sizes
that you've seen before and then at the end
we have a couple of fully connected layers
of size 4096 and finally the last layer,
is FC8 going to the soft max,
which is going to the 1000 ImageNet classes.
And just a couple of details about this,
it was the first use of the ReLu non-linearity
that we've talked about that's the most commonly used
non-linearity.
They used local response normalization layers
basically trying to normalize the response across
neighboring channels but this is something that's not really
used anymore.
It turned out not to, other people showed
that it didn't have so much of an effect.
There's a lot of heavy data augmentation,
and so you can look in the paper for more details,
but things like flipping, jittering, cropping,
color normalization all of these things
which you'll probably find useful for you when
you're working on your projects for example,
so a lot of data augmentation here.
They also use dropout batch size of 128,
and learned with SGD with momentum which we talked about
in an earlier lecture, and basically just started
with a base learning rate of 1e negative 2.
Every time it plateaus, reduce by a factor of 10
and then just keep going.
Until they finish training
and a little bit of weight decay and in the end,
in order to get the best numbers they also did
an ensembling of models and so training multiple of these,
averaging them together and this also gives an improvement
in performance.
And so one other thing I want to point out
is that if you look at this AlexNet diagram up here,
it looks kind of like the normal comNet diagrams
that we've been seeing, except for one difference,
which is that it's, you can see it's kind of split
in these two different rows or columns going across.
And so the reason for this is mostly historical note,
so AlexNet was trained on GTX580 GPUs older GPUs
that only had three gigs of memory.
So it couldn't actually fit this entire network on here,
and so what they ended up doing,
was they spread the network across two GPUs.
So on each GPU you would have half of the neurons,
or half of the feature maps.
And so for example if you look at this first conv layer,
we have 55 by 55 by 96 output,
but if you look at this diagram carefully,
you can zoom in later in the actual paper,
you can see that, it's actually only 48
depth-wise, on each GPU,
and so they just spread it, the feature maps,
directly in half.
And so what happens is that for most of these layers,
for example com one, two, four and five,
the connections are only with feature maps
on the same GPU, so you would take as input,
half of the feature maps that were on the the same GPU
as before and you don't look at the full 96
feature maps for example.
You just take as input the 48 in that first layer.
And then there's a few layers so com three,
as well as FC six, seven and eight,
where here are the GPUs do talk to each other
and so there's connections with all feature maps
in the preceding layer.
so there's communication across the GPUs,
and each of these neurons are then connected
to the full depth of the previous input layer.
Question.
- [Student] It says the full simplified AlexNetwork
architecture.
[mumbles]
- Oh okay, so the question is why does it say
full simplified AlexNet architecture here?
It just says that because I didn't put all the details
on here, so for example this is the full set of layers
in the architecture, and the strides and so on,
but for example the normalization layer, there's other,
these details are not written on here.
And then just one little note,
if you look at the paper and try and write out
the math and architectures and so on,
there's a little bit of an issue on the very first
layer they'll say if you'll look in the figure
they'll say 224 by 224 ,
but there's actually some kind of funny pattern
going on and so the numbers actually work out
if you look at it as 227.
AlexNet was the winner of the ImageNet classification
benchmark in 2012, you can see that
it cut the error rate by quite a large margin.
It was the first CNN base winner, and it was widely used
as a base to our architecture
almost ubiquitously from then until a couple years ago.
It's still used quite a bit.
It's used in transfer learning for lots of different tasks
and so it was used for basically a long time,
and it was very famous and now though there's been
some more recent architectures that have generally
just had better performance and so we'll talk about these
next and these are going to be the more common architectures
that you'll be wanting to use in practice.
So just quickly first in 2013 the ImageNet challenge
was won by something called a ZFNet.
Yes, question.
[student speaks off mic]
- So the question is intuition why AlexNet
was so much better than the ones that came before,
DefLearning comNets [mumbles] this is just
a very different kind of approach in architecture.
So this was the first deep learning based approach
first comNet that was used.
So in 2013 the challenge was won by something called
a ZFNet [Zeller Fergus Net] named after the creators.
And so this mostly was improving hyper parameters
over the AlexNet.
It had the same number of layers,
the same general structure and they made a few
changes things like changing the stride size,
different numbers of filters and after playing around
with these hyper parameters more,
they were able to improve the error rate.
But it's still basically the same idea.
So in 2014 there are a couple of architectures
that were now more significantly different
and made another jump in performance,
and the main difference with these networks first of all
was much deeper networks.
So from the eight layer network that was in 2012
and 2013, now in 2014 we had two very close winners
that were around 19 layers and 22 layers.
So significantly deeper.
And the winner of this was GoogleNet, from Google
but very close behind was something called VGGNet
from Oxford, and on actually the localization challenge
VGG got first place in some of the other tracks.
So these were both very, very strong networks.
So let's first look at VGG in a little bit more detail.
And so the VGG network is the idea of much deeper networks
and with much smaller filters.
So they increased the number of layers
from eight layers in AlexNet right to now they had
models with 16 to 19 layers in VGGNet.
And one key thing that they did was they kept very small
filter so only three by three conv all the way,
which is basically the smallest com filter size
that is looking at a little bit of the neighboring pixels.
And they just kept this very simple structure
of three by three convs with the periodic pooling
all the way through the network.
And it's very simple elegant network architecture,
was able to get 7.3% top five error
on the ImageNet challenge.
So first the question of why use smaller filters.
So when we take these small filters now we have
fewer parameters and we try and stack more of them
instead of having larger filters,
have smaller filters with more depth instead,
have more of these filters instead,
what happens is that you end up having the same effective
receptive field as if you only have one seven by seven
convolutional layer.
So here's a question, what is the effective receptive field
of three of these three by three conv layers
with stride one?
So if you were to stack three three by three conv layers
with Stride one what's the effective receptive field,
the total area of the input, spatial area of the input
that enure at the top layer of the three layers
is looking at.
So I heard fifteen pixels, why fifteen pixels?
- [Student] Okay, so the reason given was because
they overlap--
- Okay, so the reason given was because they overlap.
So it's on the right track.
What actually is happening though is you have to see,
at the first layer, the receptive field is going to be
three by three right?
And then at the second layer,
each of these neurons in the second layer
is going to look at three by three other first layer
filters, but the corners of these three by three
have an additional pixel on each side,
that is looking at in the original input layer.
So the second layer is actually looking at five by five
receptive field and then if you do this again,
the third layer is looking at three by three
in the second layer but this is going to,
if you just draw out this pyramid is looking at
seven by seven in the input layer.
So the effective receptive field here
is going to be seven by seven.
Which is the same as one seven by seven conv layer.
So what happens is that this has the same effective
receptive field as a seven by seven conv layer
but it's deeper.
It's able to have more non-linearities in there,
and it's also fewer parameters.
So if you look at the total number of parameters,
each of these conv filters for the three by threes
is going to have nine parameters in each conv [mumbles]
three times three, and then times the input depth,
so three times three times C, times this total number
of output feature maps, which is again C
is we're going to preserve the total
number of channels.
So you get three times three,
times C times C for each of these layers,
and we have three layers so it's going to be
three times this number,
compared to if you had a single seven by seven layer
then you get, by the same reasoning,
seven squared times C squared.
So you're going to have fewer parameters total,
which is nice.
So now if we look at this full network here
there's a lot of numbers up here that you can go back
and look at more carefully but if we look at all
of the sizes and number of parameters the same way
that we calculated the example for AlexNet,
this is a good exercise to go through,
we can see that you know going the same way
we have a couple of these conv layers and a pooling layer
a couple more conv layers, pooling layer, several more
conv layers and so on.
And so this just keeps going up.
And if you counted the total number of convolutional
and fully connected layers, we're going to have 16
in this case for VGG 16,
and then VGG 19, it's just a very similar
architecture, but with a few more conv layers in there.
And so the total memory usage of this network,
so just making a forward pass through counting up
all of these numbers so in the memory numbers here
written in terms of the total numbers,
like we calculated earlier,
and if you look at four bytes per number,
this is going to be about 100 megs per image,
and so this is the scale of the memory usage
that's happening and this is only for a forward pass right,
when you do a backward pass you're going to have to store
more and so this is pretty heavy memory wise.
100 megs per image, if you have on five gigs
of total memory, then you're only going to be able
to store about 50 of these.
And so also the total number of parameters here we have
is 138 million parameters in this network,
and this compares with 60 million for AlexNet.
Question?
[student speaks off mic]
- So the question is what do we mean by deeper,
is it the number of filters, number of layers?
So deeper in this case is always referring to layers.
So there are two usages of the word depth
which is confusing one is the depth rate per channel,
width by height by depth, you can use
the word depth here,
but in general we talk about the depth of a network,
this is going to be the total number of layers
in the network, and usually in particular
we're counting the total number of weight layers.
So the total number of layers with trainable weight,
so convolutional layers and fully connected layers.
[student mumbles off mic]
- Okay, so the question is, within each layer
what do different filters need?
And so we talked about this back in the comNet lecture,
so you can also go back and refer to that,
but each filter is a set of let's say three by three convs,
so each filter is looking at a,
is a set of weight looking at a three by three value input
input depth, and this produces one feature map,
one activation map of all the responses of the
different spatial locations.
And then we have we can have as many filters as we want
right so for example 96 and each of these
is going to produce a feature map.
And so it's just like each filter corresponds
to a different pattern that we're looking for
in the input that we convolve around and we see
the responses everywhere in the input,
we create a map of these and then another filter
will we convolve over the image and create another map.
Question.
[student speaks off mic]
- So question is, is there intuition behind,
as you go deeper into the network we have more channel depth
so more number of filters right and so you can have
any design that you want so you don't have to do this.
In practice you will see this happen a lot of the times
and one of the reasons is people try and maintain
kind of a relatively constant level of compute,
so as you go higher up or deeper into your network,
you're usually also using basically down sampling
and having smaller total spatial area and then so then
they also increase now you increase by depth a little bit,
it's not as expensive now to increase by depth
because it's spatially smaller and so,
yeah that's just a reason.
Question.
[student speaks off mic]
- So performance-wise is there any reason to use
SBN [mumbles] instead of SouthMax [mumbles],
so no, for a classifier you can use either one,
and you did that earlier in the class as well,
but in general SouthMax losses,
have generally worked well and been standard use
for classification here.
Okay yeah one more question.
[student mumbles off mic]
- Yes, so the question is, we don't have to store
all of the memory like we can throw away the parts
that we don't need and so on?
And yes this is true.
Some of this you don't need to keep,
but you're also going to be doing a backwards pass
through ware for the most part,
when you were doing the chain
rule and so on you needed a lot of these activations
as part of it and so in large part a lot of this
does need to be kept.
So if we look at the distribution of where memory is used
and where parameters are, you can see that a lot
of memories in these early layers right where you still have
spatial dimensions you're going to have more memory usage
and then a lot of the parameters are actually in
the last layers, the fully connected layers
have a huge number of parameters right,
because we have all of these dense connections.
And so that's something just to know and then
keep in mind so later on we'll see some networks actually
get rid of these fully connected layers and be able
to save a lot on the number of parameters.
And then just one last thing to point out,
you'll also see different ways of calling
all of these layers right.
So here I've written out exactly what the layers are.
conv3-64 means three by three convs
with 64 total filters.
But for VGGNet on this diagram on the right here
there's also common ways that people will look
at each group of filters,
so each orange block here, as in conv1
part one, so conv1-1, conv1-2,
and so on.
So just something to keep in mind.
So VGGNet ended up getting second place in the
ImageNet 2014 classification challenge,
first in localization.
They followed a very similar training procedure
as Alex Krizhevsky for the AlexNet.
They didn't use local response normalization,
so as I mentioned earlier,
they found out this didn't really help them,
and so they took it out.
You'll see VGG 16 and VGG 19 are common variants
of the cycle here, and this is just
the number of layers, 19 is slightly deeper than 16.
In practice VGG 19 works very little bit better,
and there's a little bit more memory usage,
so you can use either but 16 is very commonly used.
For best results, like AlexNet, they did ensembling
in order to average several models,
and you get better results.
And they also showed in their work that
the FC7 features of the last fully connected layer before
going to the 1000 ImageNet classes.
The 4096 size layer just before that,
is a good feature representation,
that can even just be used as is,
to extract these features from other data,
and generalized these other tasks as well.
And so FC7 is a good feature representation.
Yeah question.
[student speaks off mic]
- Sorry what was the question?
Okay, so the question is what is localization here?
And so this is a task, and we'll talk about it
a little bit more in a later lecture
on detection and localization so I don't want to
go into detail here but it's basically an image,
not just classifying What's the class of the image,
but also drawing a bounding box around where that
object is in the image.
And the difference with detection,
which is a very related task is that detection
there can be multiple instances of this object in the image
localization we're assuming there's just one,
this classification but we just how this
additional bounding box.
So we looked at VGG which was one of the deep networks
from 2014 and then now we'll talk about GoogleNet
which was the other one that won
the classification challenge.
So GoogleNet again was a much deeper network
with 22 layers but one of the main insights
and special things about GoogleNet is that it really
looked at this problem of computational efficiency
and it tried to design a network architecture that was
very efficient in the amount of compute.
And so they did this using this inception module
which we'll go into more detail and basically stacking
a lot of these inception modules on top of each other.
There's also no fully connected layers in this network,
so they got rid of that were able to save a lot
of parameters and so in total there's only five million
parameters which is twelve times less than AlexNet,
which had 60 million even though it's much deeper now.
It got 6.7% top five error.
So what's the inception module?
So the idea behind the inception module
is that they wanted to design a good local network typology
and it has this idea of this local topology
that's you know you can think of it as a network
within a network and then stack a lot of these
local typologies one on top of each other.
And so in this local network that they're calling
an inception module what they're doing is they're basically
applying several different kinds of filter operations
in parallel on top of the same input coming into
this same layer.
So we have our input coming in from the previous layer
and then we're going to do different kinds of convolutions.
So a one by one conv, right a three by three conv,
five by five conv, and then they also
have a pooling operation in this case three by three
pooling, and so you get all of these different
outputs from these different layers,
and then what they do is they concatenate all these
filter outputs together depth wise, and so
then this creates one tenser output at the end
that is going tom pass on to the next layer.
So if we look at just a naive way of doing this
we just do exactly that we have all of these different
operations we get the outputs we concatenate them together.
So what's the problem with this?
And it turns out that computational complexity
is going to be a problem here.
So if we look more carefully at an example,
so here just for as an example I've put one by one conv,
128 filter so three by three conv 192 filters,
five by five convs and 96 filters.
Assume everything has basically the stride
that's going to maintain the spatial dimensions,
and that we have this input coming in.
So what is the output size of the one by one filter
with 128 , one by one conv with 128 filters?
Who has a guess?
OK so I heard 28 by 28, by 128 which is correct.
So right by one by one conv we're going to maintain
spatial dimensions and then on top of that,
each conv filter is going to look through
the entire 256 depth of the input,
but then the output is going to be,
we have a 28 by 28 feature map
for each of the 128 filters that we have
in this conv layer.
So we get 28 by 28 by 128.
OK and then now if we do the same thing
and we look at the filter sizes of the output sizes sorry
of all of the different filters here, after the
three by three conv we're going to have this volume
of 28 by 28 by 192 right after five by five conv
we have 96 filters here.
So 28 by 28 by 96,
and then out pooling layer is just going
to keep the same spatial dimension here, so pooling layer
will preserve it in depth,
and here because of our stride,
we're also going to preserve our spatial dimensions.
And so now if we look at the output size after filter
concatenation what we're going to get is 28 by 28,
these are all 28 by 28, and we concatenating depth wise.
So we get 28 by 28 times all of these added together,
and the total output size is going to be
28 by 28 by 672.
So the input to our inception module was 28 by 28
by 256, then the output from this module is 28 by 28
by 672.
So we kept the same spatial dimensions,
and we blew up the depth.
Question.
[student speaks off mic]
OK So in this case, yeah, the question is,
how are we getting 28 by 28 for everything?
So here we're doing all the zero padding
in order to maintain the spatial dimensions,
and that way we can do this filter
concatenation depth-wise.
Question in the back.
[student speaks off mic]
- OK The question is what's the 256 deep at the input,
and so this is not the input to the network,
this is the input just to this local module
that I'm looking at.
So in this case 256 is the depth of the previous
inception module that came just before this.
And so now coming out we have 28 by 28 by 672,
676%0