- Hello, hi.
So I want to get started.
Welcome to CS 231N Lecture 11.
We're going to talk about today detection segmentation
and a whole bunch of other really exciting topics
around core computer vision tasks.
But as usual, a couple administrative notes.
So last time you obviously took the midterm,
we didn't have lecture, hopefully that went okay
for all of you but so we're going to work on grading
the midterm this week, but as a reminder
please don't make any public discussions
about the midterm questions or answers or whatever
until at least tomorrow because there are still
some people taking makeup midterms today
and throughout the rest of the week
so we just ask you that you refrain from talking
publicly about midterm questions.
Why don't you wait until Monday?
[laughing]
Okay, great.
So we're also starting to work on midterm grading.
We'll get those back to you as soon as you can,
as soon as we can.
We're also starting to work on grading assignment two
so there's a lot of grading being done this week.
The TA's are pretty busy.
Also a reminder for you guys, hopefully you've been working
hard on your projects now that most of you
are done with the midterm so your project milestones
will be due on Tuesday so any sort of last minute
changes that you had in your projects,
I know some people decided to switch projects
after the proposal, some teams reshuffled a little bit,
that's fine but your milestone should reflect
the project that you're actually doing
for the rest of the quarter.
So hopefully that's going out well.
I know there's been a lot of worry and stress
on Piazza, wondering about assignment three.
So we're working on that as hard as we can
but that's actually a bit of a new assignment,
it's changing a bit from last year
so it will be out as soon as possible,
hopefully today or tomorrow.
Although we promise that whenever it comes out
you'll have two weeks to finish it
so try not to stress out about that too much.
But I'm pretty excited, I think assignment three
will be really cool, has a lot of cool,
it'll cover a lot of really cool material.
So another thing, last time in lecture
we mentioned this thing called the Train Game
which is this really cool thing we've been working on
sort of as a side project a little bit.
So this is an interactive tool that you guys can go on
and use to explore a little bit the process
of tuning hyperparameters in practice so we hope that,
so this is again totally not required for the course.
Totally optional, but if you do we will offer
a small amount of extra credit for those of you
who want to do well and participate on this.
And we'll send out exactly some more details
later this afternoon on Piazza.
But just a bit of a demo for what exactly is this thing.
So you'll get to go in and we've changed the name
from Train Game to HyperQuest because you're questing
to solve, to find the best hyperparameters for your model
so this is really cool, it'll be an interactive tool
that you can use to explore the training of hyperparameters
interactively in your browser.
So you'll login with your student ID and name.
You'll fill out a little survey with some
of your experience on deep learning
then you'll read some instructions.
So in this game you'll be shown some random data set
on every trial.
This data set might be images or it might be vectors
and your goal is to train a model by picking
the right hyperparameters interactively to perform
as well as you can on the validation set
of this random data set.
And it'll sort of keep track of your performance
over time and there'll be a leaderboard,
it'll be really cool.
So every time you play the game,
you'll get some statistics about your data set.
In this case we're doing a classification problem
with 10 classes.
You can see down at the bottom you have these statistics
about random data set, we have 10 classes.
The input data size is three by 32 by 32
so this is some image data set and we can see
that in this case we have 8500 examples
in the training set and 1500 examples in the validation set.
These are all random, they'll change
a little bit every time.
Based on these data set statistics you'll make some choices
on your initial learning rate, your initial network size,
and your initial dropout rate.
Then you'll see a screen like this where it'll run
one epoch with those chosen hyperparameters,
show you on the right here you'll see two plots.
One is your training and validation loss
for that first epoch.
Then you'll see your training and validation accuracy
for that first epoch and based on the gaps that you see
in these two graphs you can make choices interactively
to change the learning rates and hyperparameters
for the next epoch.
So then you can either choose to continue training
with the current or changed hyperparameters,
you can also stop training, or you can revert to
go back to the previous checkpoint
in case things got really messed up.
So then you'll get to make some choice,
so here we'll decide to continue training
and in this case you could go and set new learning rates
and new hyperparameters for the next epoch of training.
You can also, kind of interesting here,
you can actually grow the network interactively
during training in this demo.
There's this cool trick from a couple recent papers
where you can either take existing layers
and make them wider or add new layers to the network
in the middle of training while still maintaining
the same function in the network so you can do that
to increase the size of your network in the middle
of training here which is kind of cool.
So then you'll make choices over several epochs
and eventually your final validation accuracy
will be recorded and we'll have some leaderboard
that compares your score on that data set
to some simple baseline models.
And depending on how well you do on this leaderboard
we'll again offer some small amounts of extra credit
for those of you who choose to participate.
So this is again, totally optional, but I think
it can be a really cool learning experience for you guys
to play around with and explore how hyperparameters
affect the learning process.
Also, it's really useful for us.
You'll help science out by participating in this experiment.
We're pretty interested in seeing how people behave
when they train neural networks so you'll be helping us out
as well if you decide to play this.
But again, totally optional, up to you.
Any questions on that?
Hopefully at some point but it's.
So the question was will this be a paper
or whatever eventually?
Hopefully but it's really early stages of this project
so I can't make any promises but I hope so.
But I think it'll be really cool.
[laughing]
Yeah, so the question is how can you add layers
during training?
I don't really want to get into that right now
but the paper to read is Net2Net by Ian Goodfellow's
one of the authors and there's another paper
from Microsoft called Network Morphism.
So if you read those two papers you can see how this works.
Okay, so last time, a bit of a reminder
before we had the midterm last time we talked
about recurrent neural networks.
We saw that recurrent neural networks can be used
for different types of problems.
In addition to one to one we can do one to many,
many to one, many to many.
We saw how this can apply to language modeling
and we saw some cool examples of applying neural networks
to model different sorts of languages at the character level
and we sampled these artificial math and Shakespeare
and C source code.
We also saw how similar things could be applied
to image captioning by connecting a CNN feature extractor
together with an RNN language model.
And we saw some really cool examples of that.
We also talked about the different types of RNN's.
We talked about this Vanilla RNN.
I also want to mention that this is sometimes called
a Simple RNN or an Elman RNN so you'll see
all of these different terms in literature.
We also talked about the Long Short Term Memory or LSTM.
And we talked about how the gradient,
the LSTM has this crazy set of equations
but it makes sense because it helps improve gradient flow
during back propagation and helps this thing model
more longer term dependencies in our sequences.
So today we're going to switch gears and talk about
a whole bunch of different exciting tasks.
We're going to talk about, so so far we've been talking about
mostly the image classification problem.
Today we're going to talk about various types of other
computer vision tasks where you actually want to go in
and say things about the spatial pixels inside your images
so we'll see segmentation, localization, detection,
a couple other different computer vision tasks
and how you can approach these
with convolutional neural networks.
So as a bit of refresher, so far the main thing
we've been talking about in this class
is image classification so here we're going to have
some input image come in.
That input image will go through
some deep convolutional network,
that network will give us some feature vector
of maybe 4096 dimensions in the case of AlexNet RGB
and then from that final feature vector
we'll have some fully-connected,
some final fully-connected layer
that gives us 1000 numbers for the different class scores
that we care about where 1000 is maybe the number
of classes in ImageNet in this example.
And then at the end of the day
what the network does is we input an image
and then we output a single category label
saying what is the content of this entire image as a whole.
But this is maybe the most basic possible task
in computer vision and there's a whole bunch
of other interesting types of tasks
that we might want to solve using deep learning.
So today we're going to talk about several
of these different tasks and step through each of these
and see how they all work with deep learning.
So we'll talk about these more in detail
about what each problem is as we get to it
but this is kind of a summary slide
that we'll talk first about semantic segmentation.
We'll talk about classification and localization,
then we'll talk about object detection,
and finally a couple brief words
about instance segmentation.
So first is the problem of semantic segmentation.
In the problem of semantic segmentation,
we want to input an image and then output a decision
of a category for every pixel in that image
so for every pixel in this, so this input image for example
is this cat walking through the field, he's very cute.
And in the output we want to say
for every pixel is that pixel a cat or grass or sky or trees
or background or some other set of categories.
So we're going to have some set of categories
just like we did in the image classification case
but now rather than assigning a single category
labeled to the entire image, we want to produce
a category label for each pixel of the input image.
And this is called semantic segmentation.
So one interesting thing about semantic segmentation
is that it does not differentiate instances
so in this example on the right we have this image
with two cows where they're standing right next
to each other and when we're talking about semantic
segmentation we're just labeling all the pixels
independently for what is the category of that pixel.
So in the case like this where we have two cows
right next to each other the output does not make
any distinguishing, does not distinguish
between these two cows.
Instead we just get a whole mass of pixels
that are all labeled as cow.
So this is a bit of a shortcoming of semantic segmentation
and we'll see how we can fix this later
when we move to instance segmentation.
But at least for now we'll just talk about
semantic segmentation first.
So you can imagine maybe using a class,
so one potential approach for attacking
semantic segmentation might be through classification.
So there's this, you could use this idea
of a sliding window approach to semantic segmentation.
So you might imagine that we take our input image
and we break it up into many many small, tiny local crops
of the image so in this example we've taken
maybe three crops from around the head of this cow
and then you could imagine taking each of those crops
and now treating this as a classification problem.
Saying for this crop, what is the category
of the central pixel of the crop?
And then we could use all the same machinery
that we've developed for classifying entire images
but now just apply it on crops rather than
on the entire image.
And this would probably work to some extent
but it's probably not a very good idea.
So this would end up being super super
computationally expensive because we want to label
every pixel in the image, we would need a separate
crop for every pixel in that image and this would be
super super expensive to run forward and backward
passes through.
And moreover, we're actually, if you think about this
we can actually share computation between different
patches so if you're trying to classify two patches
that are right next to each other and actually overlap
then the convolutional features of those patches
will end up going through the same convolutional layers
and we can actually share a lot of the computation
when applying this to separate passes
or when applying this type of approach
to separate patches in the image.
So this is actually a terrible idea and nobody does this
and you should probably not do this
but it's at least the first thing you might think of
if you were trying to think about semantic segmentation.
Then the next idea that works a bit better
is this idea of a fully convolutional network right.
So rather than extracting individual patches from the image
and classifying these patches independently,
we can imagine just having our network be a whole giant
stack of convolutional layers with no fully connected
layers or anything so in this case we just have a bunch
of convolutional layers that are all maybe three by three
with zero padding or something like that
so that each convolutional layer preserves the spatial size
of the input and now if we pass our image
through a whole stack of these convolutional layers,
then the final convolutional layer could just output
a tensor of something by C by H by W
where C is the number of categories that we care about
and you could see this tensor as just giving
our classification scores for every pixel
in the input image at every location in the input image.
And we could compute this all at once
with just some giant stack of convolutional layers.
And then you could imagine training this thing
by putting a classification loss at every pixel
of this output, taking an average over those pixels
in space, and just training this kind of network
through normal, regular back propagation.
Question?
Oh, the question is how do you develop
training data for this?
It's very expensive right.
So the training data for this would be
we need to label every pixel in those input images
so there's tools that people sometimes have online
where you can go in and sort of draw contours
around the objects and then fill in regions
but in general getting this kind of training data
is very expensive.
Yeah, the question is what is the loss function?
So here since we're making a classification decision
per pixel then we put a cross entropy loss
on every pixel of the output.
So we have the ground truth category label
for every pixel in the output,
then we compute across entropy loss
between every pixel in the output
and the ground truth pixels and then
take either a sum or an average over space
and then sum or average over the mini-batch.
Question?
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, the question is do we assume
that we know the categories?
So yes, we do assume that we know the categories up front
so this is just like the image classification case.
So an image classification we know at the start of training
based on our data set that maybe there's 10 or 20
or 100 or 1000 classes that we care about
for this data set and then here we are fixed
to that set of classes that are fixed for the data set.
So this model is relatively simple
and you can imagine this working reasonably well
assuming that you tuned all the hyperparameters right
but it's kind of a problem right.
So in this setup, since we're applying a bunch
of convolutions that are all keeping the same
spatial size of the input image,
this would be super super expensive right.
If you wanted to do convolutions that maybe have
64 or 128 or 256 channels for those convolutional filters
which is pretty common in a lot of these networks,
then running those convolutions on this high resolution
input image over a sequence of layers would be
extremely computationally expensive
and would take a ton of memory.
So in practice, you don't usually see networks
with this architecture.
Instead you tend to see networks that look something
like this where we have some downsampling
and then some upsampling of the feature map
inside the image.
So rather than doing all the convolutions
of the full spatial resolution of the image,
we'll maybe go through a small number
of convolutional layers at the original resolution
then downsample that feature map using something
like max pooling or strided convolutions
and sort of downsample, downsample,
so we have convolutions in downsampling
and convolutions in downsampling
that look much like a lot of the classification networks
that you see but now the difference is that
rather than transitioning to a fully connected layer
like you might do in an image classification setup,
instead we want to increase the spatial resolution
of our predictions in the second half of the network
so that our output image can now be the same size
as our input image and this ends up being
much more computationally efficient
because you can make the network very deep
and work at a lower spatial resolution
for many of the layers at the inside of the network.
So we've already seen examples of downsampling
when it comes to convolutional networks.
We've seen that you can do strided convolutions
or various types of pooling to reduce the spatial size
of the image inside a network but we haven't
really talked about upsampling and the question
you might be wondering is what are these upsampling
layers actually look like inside the network?
And what are our strategies for increasing the size
of a feature map inside the network?
Sorry, was there a question in the back?
Yeah, so the question is how do we upsample?
And the answer is that's the topic
of the next couple slides.
[laughing]
So one strategy for upsampling is something like
unpooling so we have this notion of pooling
to downsample so we talked about average pooling
or max pooling so when we talked about average pooling
we're kind of taking a spatial average
within a receptive field of each pooling region.
One kind of analog for upsampling is this idea
of nearest neighbor unpooling.
So here on the left we see this example
of nearest neighbor unpooling where our input
is maybe some two by two grid and our output
is a four by four grid and now in our output
we've done a two by two stride two nearest neighbor
unpooling or upsampling where we've just duplicated
that element for every point in our two by two
receptive field of the unpooling region.
Another thing you might see is this bed of nails unpooling
or bed of nails upsampling where you'll just take,
again we have a two by two receptive field
for our unpooling regions and then you'll take the,
in this case you make it all zeros except for one element
of the unpooling region so in this case we've taken
all of our inputs and always put them in the upper
left hand corner of this unpooling region
and everything else is zeros.
And this is kind of like a bed of nails
because the zeros are very flat,
then you've got these things poking up
for the values at these various non-zero regions.
Another thing that you see sometimes which was alluded to
by the question a minute ago is this idea of max unpooling
so in a lot of these networks they tend to be symmetrical
where we have a downsampling portion of the network
and then an upsampling portion of the network
with a symmetry between those two portions of the network.
So sometimes what you'll see is this idea of max unpooling
where for each unpooling, for each upsampling layer,
it is associated with one of the pooling layers
in the first half of the network and now in the first half,
in the downsampling when we do max pooling
we'll actually remember which element of the receptive field
during max pooling was used to do the max pooling
and now when we go through the rest of the network
then we'll do something that looks like this bed of nails
upsampling except rather than always putting the elements
in the same position, instead we'll stick it
into the position that was used in the corresponding
max pooling step earlier in the network.
I'm not sure if that explanation was clear
but hopefully the picture makes sense.
Yeah, so then you just end up filling the rest with zeros.
So then you fill the rest with zeros
and then you stick the elements from the low resolution
patch up into the high resolution patch
at the points where the max pooling took place
at the corresponding max pooling there.
Okay, so that's kind of an interesting idea.
Sorry, question?
Oh yeah, so the question is why is this a good idea?
Why might this matter?
So the idea is that when we're doing semantic segmentation
we want our predictions to be pixel perfect right.
We kind of want to get those sharp boundaries
and those tiny details in our predictive segmentation
so now if you're doing this max pooling,
there's this sort of heterogeneity that's happening
inside the feature map due to the max pooling
where from the low resolution image you don't know,
you're sort of losing spatial information in some sense
by you don't know where that feature vector came from
in the local receptive field after max pooling.
So if you actually unpool by putting the vector
in the same slot you might think that that might help us
handle these fine details a little bit better
and help us preserve some of that spatial information
that was lost during max pooling.
Question?
The question is does this make things easier for back prop?
Yeah, I guess, I don't think it changes the back prop
dynamics too much because storing these indices
is not a huge computational overhead.
They're pretty small in comparison to everything else.
So another thing that you'll see sometimes
is this idea of transpose convolution.
So transpose convolution, so for these various types
of unpooling that we just talked about,
these bed of nails, this nearest neighbor,
this max unpooling, all of these are kind of
a fixed function, they're not really learning exactly
how to do the upsampling so if you think about something
like strided convolution, strided convolution
is kind of like a learnable layer that learns the way
that the network wants to perform downsampling
at that layer.
And by analogy with that there's this type of layer
called a transpose convolution that lets us do
kind of learnable upsampling.
So it will both upsample the feature map
and learn some weights about how it wants
to do that upsampling.
And this is really just another type of convolution
so to see how this works remember how a normal
three by three stride one pad one convolution would work.
That for this kind of normal convolution
that we've seen many times now in this class,
our input might by four by four,
our output might be four by four,
and now we'll have this three by three kernel
and we'll take an inner product between,
we'll plop down that kernel at the corner of the image,
take an inner product, and that inner product
will give us the value and the activation
in the upper left hand corner of our output.
And we'll repeat this for every receptive field
in the image.
Now if we talk about strided convolution
then strided convolution ends up looking pretty similar.
However, our input is maybe a four by four region
and our output is a two by two region.
But we still have this idea of taking,
of there being some three by three filter or kernel
that we plop down in the corner of the image,
take an inner product and use that to compute
a value of the activation and the output.
But now with strided convolution the idea is that
we're moving that, rather than popping down that filter
at every possible point in the input,
instead we're going to move the filter by two pixels
in the input every time we move the filter by one pixel,
every time we move by one pixel in the output.
Right so this stride of two gives us a ratio
between how much do we move in the input
versus how much do we move in the output.
So when you do a strided convolution with stride two
this ends up downsampling the image or the feature map
by a factor of two in kind of a learnable way.
And now a transpose convolution is sort of the opposite
in a way so here our input will be a two by two region
and our output will be a four by four region.
But now the operation that we perform
with transpose convolution is a little bit different.
Now so rather than taking an inner product
instead what we're going to do is we're going to
take the value of our input feature map
at that upper left hand corner and that'll be
some scalar value in the upper left hand corner.
We're going to multiply the filter by that scalar value
and then copy those values over to this three by three
region in the output so rather than taking an inner product
with our filter and the input, instead our input
gives weights that we will use to weight the filter
and then our output will be weighted copies of the filter
that are weighted by the values in the input.
And now we can do this sort of same ratio trick
in order to upsample so now when we move one pixel
in the input now we can plop our filter down
two pixels away in the output and it's the same trick
that now the blue pixel in the input is some scalar value
and we'll take that scalar value,
multiply it by the values in the filter,
and copy those weighted filter values
into this new region in the output.
The tricky part is that sometimes these receptive fields
in the output can overlap now and now when these
receptive fields in the output overlap
we just sum the results in the output.
So then you can imagine repeating this everywhere
and repeating this process everywhere
and this ends up doing sort of a learnable upsampling
where we use these learned convolutional filter weights
to upsample the image and increase the spatial size.
By the way, you'll see this operation go
by a lot of different names in literature.
Sometimes this gets called things like deconvolution
which I think is kind of a bad name but you'll see it
out there in papers so from a signal processing perspective
deconvolution means the inverse operation to convolution
which this is not however you'll frequently see this
type of layer called a deconvolution layer
in some deep learning papers so be aware of that,
watch out for that terminology.
You'll also sometimes see this called upconvolution
which is kind of a cute name.
Sometimes it gets called fractionally strided convolution
because if we think of the stride as the ratio in step
between the input and the output then now this is something
like a stride one half convolution because of this ratio
of one to two between steps in the input
and steps in the output.
This also sometimes gets called a backwards strided
convolution because if you think about it
and work through the math this ends up being the same,
the forward pass of a transpose convolution
ends up being the same mathematical operation
as the backwards pass in a normal convolution
so you might have to take my word for it,
that might not be super obvious when you first look at this
but that's kind of a neat fact so you'll sometimes
see that name as well.
And as maybe a bit of a more concrete example
of what this looks like I think it's maybe a little easier
to see in one dimension so if we imagine,
so here we're doing a three by three transpose convolution
in one dimension.
Sorry, not three by three, a three by one
transpose convolution in one dimension.
So our filter here is just three numbers.
Our input is two numbers and now you can see
that in our output we've taken the values in the input,
used them to weight the values of the filter
and plopped down those weighted filters in the output
with a stride of two and now where these receptive fields
overlap in the output then we sum.
So you might be wondering, this is kind of a funny name.
Where does the name transpose convolution come from
and why is that actually my preferred name
for this operation?
So that comes from this kind of
neat interpretation of convolution.
So it turns out that any time you do convolution
you can always write convolution as a matrix multiplication.
So again, this is kind of easier to see
with a one-dimensional example
but here we've got some weight.
So we're doing a one-dimensional convolution
of a weight vector x which has three elements,
and an input vector, a vector, which has four elements,
A, B, C, D.
So here we're doing a three by one convolution
with stride one and you can see that we can frame
this whole operation as a matrix multiplication
where we take our convolutional kernel x
and turn it into some matrix capital X
which contains copies of that convolutional kernel
that are offset by different regions.
And now we can take this giant weight matrix X
and do a matrix vector multiplication between x