- Okay, let's get started.
Okay, so today we're going to get into some of the details
about how we train neural networks.
So, some administrative details first.
Assignment 1 is due today, Thursday,
so 11:59 p.m. tonight on Canvas.
We're also going to be releasing Assignment 2 today,
and then your project proposals
are due Tuesday, April 25th.
So you should be really starting to think
about your projects now if you haven't already.
How many people have decided
what they want to do for their project so far?
Okay, so some, some people,
so yeah, everyone else, you can go to TA office hours
if you want suggestions
and bounce ideas off of TAs.
We also have a list of projects
that other people have proposed.
Some people usually affiliated with Stanford,
so on Piazza, so you can take a look at those
for additional ideas.
And we also have some notes on backprop
for a linear layer and a vector and tensor derivatives
that Justin's written up,
so that should help with understanding
how exactly backprop works
and for vectors and matrices.
So these are linked to lecture four on the syllabus
and you can go and take a look at those.
Okay, so where we are now.
We've talked about how to express a function
in terms of a computational graph,
that we can represent any function
in terms of a computational graph.
And we've talked more explicitly about neural networks,
which is a type of graph
where we have these linear layers
that we stack on top of each other
with nonlinearities in between.
And we've also talked last lecture
about convolutional neural networks,
which are a particular type of network
that uses convolutional layers
to preserve the spatial structure
throughout all the the hierarchy of the network.
And so we saw exactly how a convolution layer looked,
where each activation map
in the convolutional layer output
is produced by sliding a filter of weights
over all of the spatial locations in the input.
And we also saw that usually
we can have many filters per layer,
each of which produces a separate activation map.
And so what we can get is from an input right,
with a certain depth, we'll get an activation map output,
which has some spatial dimension that's preserved,
as well as the depth is the total number of filters
that we have in that layer.
And so what we want to do
is we want to learn the values
of all of these weights or parameters,
and we saw that we can learn
our network parameters through optimization,
which we talked about little bit earlier
in the course, right?
And so we want to get to a point in the loss landscape
that produces a low loss,
and we can do this by taking steps
in the direction of the negative gradient.
And so the whole process we actually call
a Mini-batch Stochastic Gradient Descent
where the steps are that we continuously,
we sample a batch of data.
We forward prop it through
our computational graph or our neural network.
We get the loss at the end.
We backprop through our network
to calculate the gradients.
And then we update the parameters
or the weights in our network using this gradient.
Okay, so now for the next couple of lectures
we're going to talk about some of the details
involved in training neural networks.
And so this involves things like
how do we set up our neural network at the beginning,
which activation functions that we choose,
how do we preprocess the data,
weight initialization, regularization, gradient checking.
We'll also talk about training dynamics.
So, how do we babysit the learning process?
How do we choose how we do parameter updates,
specific perimeter update rules,
and how do we do hyperparameter optimization
to choose the best hyperparameters?
And then we'll also talk about evaluation
and model ensembles.
So today in the first part,
I will talk about activation functions, data preprocessing,
weight initialization, batch normalization,
babysitting the learning process,
and hyperparameter optimization.
Okay, so first activation functions.
So, we saw earlier how out of any particular layer,
we have the data coming in.
We multiply by our weight in you know,
fully connected or a convolutional layer.
And then we'll pass this through
an activation function or nonlinearity.
And we saw some examples of this.
We used sigmoid previously in some of our examples.
We also saw the ReLU nonlinearity.
And so today we'll talk more about different choices
for these different nonlinearities
and trade-offs between them.
So first, the sigmoid, which we've seen before,
and probably the one we're most comfortable with, right?
So the sigmoid function is as we have up here,
one over one plus e to the negative x.
And what this does is it takes each number
that's input into the sigmoid nonlinearity, so each element,
and the elementwise squashes these
into this range [0,1] right, using this function here.
And so, if you get very high values as input,
then output is going to be something near one.
If you get very low values,
or, I'm sorry, very negative values,
it's going to be near zero.
And then we have this regime near zero
that it's in a linear regime.
It looks a bit like a linear function.
And so this is been historically popular,
because sigmoids, in a sense,
you can interpret them as a kind of
a saturating firing rate of a neuron, right?
So if it's something between zero and one,
you could think of it as a firing rate.
And we'll talk later about other nonlinearities,
like ReLUs that, in practice, actually turned out to be
more biologically plausible,
but this does have a kind of interpretation
that you could make.
So if we look at this nonlinearity more carefully,
there's several problems that there actually are with this.
So the first is that saturated neurons
can kill off the gradient.
And so what exactly does this mean?
So if we look at a sigmoid gate right,
a node in our computational graph,
and we have our data X as input into it,
and then we have the output
of the sigmoid gate coming out of it,
what does the gradient flow look like
as we're coming back?
We have dL over d sigma right?
The upstream gradient coming down,
and then we're going to multiply this by dSigma over dX.
This will be the gradient of a local sigmoid function.
And we're going to chain these together
for our downstream gradient that we pass back.
So who can tell me what happens
when X is equal to -10?
It's very negative.
What does is gradient look like?
Zero, yeah, so that's right.
So the gradient become zero
and that's because in this negative,
very negative region of the sigmoid,
it's essentially flat, so the gradient is zero,
and we chain any upstream gradient coming down.
We multiply by basically something near zero,
and we're going to get a very small gradient
that's flowing back downwards, right?
So, in a sense, after the chain rule,
this kills the gradient flow and you're going to have
a zero gradient passed down to downstream nodes.
And so what happens when X is equal to zero?
So there it's, yeah, it's fine in this regime.
So, in this regime near zero,
you're going to get a reasonable gradient here,
and then it'll be fine for backprop.
And then what about X equals 10?
Zero, right.
So again, so when X is equal to a very negative
or X is equal to large positive numbers,
then these are all regions where
the sigmoid function is flat,
and it's going to kill off the gradient
and you're not going to get a gradient flow coming back.
Okay, so a second problem is that
the sigmoid outputs are not zero centered.
And so let's take a look at why this is a problem.
So, consider what happens when
the input to a neuron is always positive.
So in this case, all of our Xs we're going to say is positive.
It's going to be multiplied by some weight, W,
and then we're going to run it
through our activation function.
So what can we say about the gradients on W?
So think about what the local gradient is going to be,
right, for this linear layer.
We have DL over whatever the activation function,
the loss coming down,
and then we have our local gradient,
which is going to be basically X, right?
And so what does this mean, if all of X is positive?
Okay, so I heard it's always going to be positive.
So that's almost right.
It's always going to be either positive,
or all positive or all negative, right?
So, our upstream gradient coming down
is DL over our loss.
L is going to be DL over DF.
and this is going to be either positive or negative.
It's some arbitrary gradient coming down.
And then our local gradient that we multiply this by is,
if we're going to find the gradients on W,
is going to be DF over DW, which is going to be X.
And if X is always positive then the gradients on W,
which is multiplying these two together,
are going to always be
the sign of the upstream gradient coming down.
And so what this means is that all the gradients of W,
since they're always either positive or negative,
they're always going to move in the same direction.
You're either going to increase all of the,
when you do a parameter update,
you're going to either increase all of the values of W
by a positive amount, or differing positive amounts,
or you will decrease them all.
And so the problem with this is that,
this gives very inefficient gradient updates.
So, if you look at on the right here,
we have an example of a case where,
let's say W is two-dimensional,
so we have our two axes for W,
and if we say that we can only have
all positive or all negative updates,
then we have these two quadrants,
and, are the two places where the axis
are either all positive or negative,
and these are the only directions in which
we're allowed to make a gradient update.
And so in the case where,
let's say our hypothetical optimal W
is actually this blue vector here, right,
and we're starting off at you know some point,
or at the top of the the the beginning of the red arrows,
we can't just directly take
a gradient update in this direction,
because this is not in one of those
two allowed gradient directions.
And so what we're going to have to do,
is we'll have to take a sequence of gradient updates.
For example, in these red arrow directions
that are each in allowed directions,
in order to finally get to this optimal W.
And so this is why also, in general,
we want a zero mean data.
So, we want our input X to be zero meaned,
so that we actually have positive and negative values
and we don't get into this problem
of the gradient updates.
They'll be all moving in the same direction.
So is this clear?
Any questions on this point?
Okay.
Okay, so we've talked about these two
main problems of the sigmoid.
The saturated neurons can kill the gradients
if we're too positive or too negative of an input.
They're also not zero-centered
and so we get these,
this inefficient kind of gradient update.
And then a third problem,
we have an exponential function in here,
so this is a little bit computationally expensive.
In the grand scheme of your network,
this is usually not the main problem,
because we have all these convolutions
and dot products that are a lot more expensive,
but this is just a minor point also to observe.
So now we can look at a second
activation function here at tanh.
And so this looks very similar to the sigmoid,
but the difference is that now
it's squashing to the range [-1, 1].
So here, the main difference
is that it's now zero-centered,
so we've gotten rid of the second problem that we had.
It still kills the gradients, however, when it's saturated.
So, you still have these regimes
where the gradient is essentially flat
and you're going to kill the gradient flow.
So this is a bit better than the sigmoid,
but it still has some problems.
Okay, so now let's look at the ReLU activation function.
And this is one that we saw in our examples last lecture
when we were talking about
the convolutional neural network.
And we saw that we interspersed ReLU nonlinearities
between many of the convolutional layers.
And so, this function is f of x equals max of zero and x.
So it takes an elementwise operation on your input
and basically if your input is negative,
it's going to put it to zero.
And then if it's positive,
it's going to be just passed through.
It's the identity.
And so this is one that's pretty commonly used,
and if we look at this one
and look at and think about the problems
that we saw earlier with the sigmoid and the tanh,
we can see that it doesn't saturate
in the positive region.
So there's whole half of our input space
where it's not going to saturate,
so this is a big advantage.
So this is also computationally very efficient.
We saw earlier that the sigmoid
has this E exponential in it.
And so the ReLU is just this simple max
and there's, it's extremely fast.
And in practice, using this ReLU,
it converges much faster than the sigmoid and the tanh,
so about six times faster.
And it's also turned out to be more
biologically plausible than the sigmoid.
So if you look at a neuron
and you look at what the inputs look like,
and you look at what the outputs look like,
and you try to measure this in neuroscience experiments,
you'll see that this one
is actually a closer approximation
to what's happening than sigmoids.
And so ReLUs were starting to be used
a lot around 2012 when we had AlexNet,
the first major convolutional neural network
that was able to do well
on ImageNet and large-scale data.
They used the ReLU in their experiments.
So a problem however, with the ReLU,
is that it's still, it's not not zero-centered anymore.
So we saw that the sigmoid was not zero-centered.
Tanh fixed this and now ReLU has this problem again.
And so that's one of the issues of the ReLU.
And then we also have this further annoyance of,
again we saw that in the positive half of the inputs,
we don't have saturation,
but this is not the case of the negative half.
Right, so just thinking about this
a little bit more precisely.
So what's happening here when X equals negative 10?
So zero gradient, that's right.
What happens when X is equal to positive 10?
It's good, right.
So, we're in the linear regime.
And then what happens when X is equal to zero?
Yes, it undefined here,
but in practice, we'll say, you know, zero, right.
And so basically, it's killing the gradient
in half of the regime.
And so we can get this phenomenon
of basically dead ReLUs,
when we're in this bad part of the regime.
And so there's, you can look at this in,
as coming from several potential reasons.
And so if we look at our data cloud here,
this is all of our training data,
then if we look at where the ReLUs can fall,
so the ReLUs can be, each of these is basically
the half of the plane where it's going to activate.
And so each of these is the plane
that defines each of these ReLUs,
and we can see that you can have these dead ReLUs
that are basically off of the data cloud.
And in this case, it will never activate and never update,
as compared to an active ReLU
where some of the data
is going to be positive and passed through
and some won't be.
And so there's several reasons for this.
The first is that it can happen
when you have bad initialization.
So if you have weights that happen to be unlucky
and they happen to be off the data cloud,
so they happen to specify this bad ReLU over here.
Then they're never going to get
a data input that causes it to activate,
and so they're never going to get
good gradient flow coming back.
And so it'll just never update and never activate.
What's the more common case is
when your learning rate is too high.
And so this case you started off with an okay ReLU,
but because you're making these huge updates,
the weights jump around
and then your ReLU unit in a sense,
gets knocked off of the data manifold.
And so this happens through training.
So it was fine at the beginning
and then at some point, it became bad and it died.
And so if in practice,
if you freeze a network that you've trained
and you pass the data through,
you can see it actually is much as 10 to 20%
of the network is these dead ReLUs.
And so you know that's a problem,
but also most networks do have
this type of problem when you use ReLUs.
Some of them will be dead,
and in practice, people look into this,
and it's a research problem,
but it's still doing okay for training networks.
Yeah, is there a question?
[student speaking off mic]
Right.
So the question is, yeah,
so the data cloud is just your training data.
[student speaking off mic]
Okay, so the question is when,
how do you tell when the ReLU is going to be dead or not,
with respect to the data cloud?
And so if you look at,
this is an example of like a simple two-dimensional case.
And so our ReLU, we're going to get our input to the ReLU,
which is going to be a basically you know,
W1 X1 plus W2 X2, and it we apply this,
so that that defines this this separating hyperplane here,
and then we're going to take half of it
that's going to be positive,
and half of it's going to be killed off,
and so yes, so you, you know you just,
it's whatever the weights happened to be,
and where the data happens to be is where these,
where these hyperplanes fall, and so,
so yeah so just throughout the course of training,
some of your ReLUs will be in different places,
with respect to the data cloud.
Oh, question.
[student speaking off mic]
Yeah.
So okay, so the question is
for the sigmoid we talked about two drawbacks,
and one of them was that the neurons can get saturated,
so let's go back to the sigmoid here,
and the question was this is not the case,
when all of your inputs are positive.
So when all of your inputs are positive,
they're all going to be coming in
in this zero plus region here,
and so you can still get a saturating neuron,
because you see up in this positive region,
it also plateaus at one,
and so when it's when you have large positive values
as input you're also going to get the zero gradient,
because you have you have a flat slope here.
Okay.
Okay, so in practice people also like to initialize ReLUs
with slightly positive biases,
in order to increase the likelihood of it being
active at initialization and to get some updates.
Right and so this basically just biases towards more ReLUs
firing at the beginning,
and in practice some say that it helps.
Some say that it doesn't.
Generally people don't always use this.
It's yeah, a lot of times people just initialize it
with zero biases still.
Okay, so now we can look at some modifications
on the ReLU that have come out since then,
and so one example is this leaky ReLU.
And so this looks very similar to the original ReLU,
and the only difference is that now instead of being flat
in the negative regime,
we're going to give a slight negative slope here
And so this solves a lot of the problems
that we mentioned earlier.
Right here we don't have any saturating regime,
even in the negative space.
It's still very computationally efficient.
It still converges faster than sigmoid and tanh,
very similar to a ReLU.
And it doesn't have this dying problem.
And there's also another example
is the parametric rectifier, so PReLU.
And so in this case it's just like a leaky ReLU
where we again have this sloped region
in the negative space,
but now this slope in the negative regime
is determined through this alpha parameter,
so we don't specify, we don't hard-code it.
but we treat it as now a parameter
that we can backprop into and learn.
And so this gives it a little bit more flexibility.
And we also have something called
an Exponential Linear Unit, an ELU,
so we have all these different LUs, basically.
and this one again, you know,
it has all the benefits of the ReLu,
but now you're, it is also closer to zero mean outputs.
So, that's actually an advantage that the leaky ReLU,
parametric ReLU, a lot of these they allow you
to have your mean closer to zero,
but compared with the leaky ReLU,
instead of it being sloped in the negative regime,
here you actually are building back
in a negative saturation regime,
and there's arguments that basically this allows you
to have some more robustness to noise,
and you basically get these deactivation states
that can be more robust.
And you can look at this paper for,
there's a lot of kind of more justification
for why this is the case.
And in a sense this is kind of something
in between the ReLUs and the leaky ReLUs,
where has some of this shape,
which the Leaky ReLU does,
which gives it closer to zero mean output,
but then it also still has some of this
more saturating behavior that ReLUs have.
A question?
[student speaking off mic]
So, whether this parameter alpha
is going to be specific for each neuron.
So, I believe it is often specified,
but I actually can't remember exactly,
so you can look in the paper for exactly,
yeah, how this is defined,
but yeah, so I believe this function is basically
very carefully designed in order to have
nice desirable properties.
Okay, so there's basically all of these
kinds of variants on the ReLU.
And so you can see that, all of these it's kind of,
you can argue that each one may have certain benefits,
certain drawbacks in practice.
People just want to run experiments all of them,
and see empirically what works better,
try and justify it, and come up with new ones,
but they're all different things
that are being experimented with.
And so let's just mention one more.
This is Maxout Neuron.
So, this one looks a little bit different
in that it doesn't have the same form as the others did
of taking your basic dot product,
and then putting this element-wise
nonlinearity in front of it.
Instead, it looks like this,
this max of W dot product of X plus B,
and a second set of weights,
W2 dot product with X plus B2.
And so what does this, is this is taking the max
of these two functions in a sense.
And so what it does is it generalizes the ReLU
and the leaky ReLu,
because you're just you're taking the max over these two,
two linear functions.
And so what this give us,
it's again you're operating in a linear regime.
It doesn't saturate and it doesn't die.
The problem is that here,
you are doubling the number of parameters per neuron.
So, each neuron now has this original set of weights, W,
but it now has W1 and W2, so you have twice these.
So in practice,
when we look at all of these activation functions,
kind of a good general rule of thumb is use ReLU.
This is the most standard one
that generally just works well.
And you know you do want to be careful in general
with your learning rates to adjust them based,
see how things do.
We'll talk more about adjusting learning rates
later in this lecture,
but you can also try out some of these
fancier activation functions,
the leaky ReLU, Maxout, ELU,
but these are generally,
they're still kind of more experimental.
So, you can see how they work for your problem.
You can also try out tanh,
but probably some of these ReLU
and ReLU variants are going to be better.
And in general don't use sigmoid.
This is one of the earliest original activation functions,
and ReLU and these other variants
have generally worked better since then.
Okay, so now let's talk a little bit
about data preprocessing.
Right, so the activation function,
we design this is part of our network.
Now we want to train the network,
and we have our input data
that we want to start training from.
So, generally we want to always preprocess the data,
and this is something that you've probably seen before
in machine learning classes if you taken those.
And some standard types of preprocessing are,
you take your original data
and you want to zero mean them,
and then you probably want to also normalize that,
so normalized by the standard deviation,
And so why do we want to do this?
For zero centering, you can remember earlier
that we talked about when all the inputs
are positive, for example,
then we get all of our gradients
on the weights to be positive,
and we get this basically suboptimal optimization.
And in general even if it's not all zero or all negative,
any sort of bias will still cause this type of problem.
And so then in terms of normalizing the data,
this is basically you want to normalize data
typically in the machine learning problems,
so that all features are in the same range,
and so that they contribute equally.
In practice, since for images, which is what
we're dealing with in this course here for the most part,
we do do the zero centering,
but in practice we don't actually normalize
the pixel value so much, because generally for images
right at each location you already have
relatively comparable scale and distribution,
and so we don't really need to normalize so much,
compared to more general machine learning problems,
where you might have different features
that are very different and of very different scales.
And in machine learning,
you might also see a more complicated things,
like PCA or whitening, but again with images,
we typically just stick with the zero mean,
and we don't do the normalization,
and we also don't do some of these
more complicated pre-processing.
And one reason for this is generally with images
we don't really want to take all of our input,
let's say pixel values and project this
onto a lower dimensional space
of new kinds of features that we're dealing with.
We typically just want to apply
convolutional networks spatially
and have our spatial structure over the original image.
Yeah, question.
[student speaking off mic]
So the question is we do this pre-processing
in a training phase,
do we also do the same kind of thing in the test phase,
and the answer is yes.
So, let me just move to the next slide here.
So, in general on the training phase
is where we determine our let's say, mean,
and then we apply this exact same mean to the test data.
So, we'll normalize by the same
empirical mean from the training data.
Okay, so to summarize basically for images,
we typically just do the zero mean pre-processing
and we can subtract either the entire mean image.
So, from the training data,
you compute the mean image,
which will be the same size as your, as each image.
So, for example 32 by 32 by three,
you'll get this array of numbers,
and then you subtract that from each image
that you're about to pass through the network,
and you'll do the same thing at test time
for this array that you determined at training time.
In practice, we can also for some networks,
we also do this by just of subtracting
a per-channel mean,
and so instead of having an entire mean image
that were going to zero-center by,
we just take the mean by channel,
and this is just because it turns out that
it was similar enough across the whole image,
it didn't make such a big difference
to subtract the mean image
versus just a per-channel value.
And this is easier to just pass around and deal with.
So, you'll see this as well for example, in a VGG Network,
which is a network that came after AlexNet,
and we'll talk about that later.
Question.
[student speaking off mic]
Okay, so there are two questions.
The first is what's a channel, in this case,
when we are subtracting a per-channel mean?
And this is RGB, so our array,
our images are typically for example, 32 by 32 by three.
So, width, height, each are 32,
and our depth, we have three channels RGB,
and so we'll have one mean for the red channel,
one mean for a green, one for blue.
And then the second, what was your second question?
[student speaking off mic]
Oh