- Okay, sounds like it is.
I'll be telling you about adversarial examples
and adversarial training today.
Thank you.
As an overview, I will start off by telling you
what adversarial examples are,
and then I'll explain why they happen,
why it's possible for them to exist.
I'll talk a little bit about how adversarial examples
pose real world security threats,
that they can actually be used to compromise
systems built on machine learning.
I'll tell you what the defenses are so far,
but mostly defenses are an open research problem
that I hope some of you will move on to tackle.
And then finally I'll tell you
how to use adversarial examples
to improve other machine learning algorithms
even if you want to build a machine learning algorithm
that won't face a real world adversary.
Looking at the big picture and the context for this lecture,
I think most of you are probably here
because you've heard how incredibly powerful
and successful machine learning is,
that very many different tasks
that could not be solved with software before
are now solvable thanks to deep learning
and convolutional networks and gradient descent.
All of these technologies that are working really well.
Until just a few years ago,
these technologies didn't really work.
In about 2013, we started to see
that deep learning achieved human level performance
at a lot of different tasks.
We saw that convolutional nets
could recognize objects and images
and score about the same as people in those benchmarks,
with the caveat that part of the reason that
algorithms score as well as people
is that people can't tell
Alaskan Huskies from Siberian Huskies very well,
but modulo the strangeness of the benchmarks
deep learning caught up to about human level performance
for object recognition in about 2013.
That same year, we also saw that object recognition
applied to human faces caught up to about human level.
That suddenly we had computers
that could recognize faces about as well as
you or I could recognize faces of strangers.
You can recognize the faces of your friends and family
better than a computer, but when you're dealing
with people that you haven't had a lot of experience with
the computer caught up to us in about 2013.
We also saw that computers caught up
to humans for reading type written fonts in photos
in about 2013.
It even got the point that we could no longer use CAPTCHAs
to tell whether a user of a webpage is human or not
because the convolutional network
is better at reading obfuscated text than a human is.
So with this context today
of deep learning working really well
especially for computer vision
it's a little bit unusual to think about
the computer making a mistake.
Before about 2013, nobody was ever surprised
if the computer made a mistake.
That was the rule not the exception,
and so today's topic which is all about
unusual mistakes that deep learning algorithms make
this topic wasn't really a serious avenue of study
until the algorithms started to work well most of the time,
and now people study the way that they break
now that that's actually the exception rather than the rule.
An adversarial example is an example
that has been carefully computed to be misclassified.
In a lot of cases we're able to make the new image
indistinguishable to a human observer
from the original image.
Here, I show you one where we start with a panda.
On the left this is a panda
that has not been modified in any way,
and the convolutional network trained on the image
in that dataset is able to recognize it as being a panda.
One interesting thing is that the model
doesn't have a whole lot of confidence in that decision.
It assigns about 60% probability
to this image being a panda.
If we then compute exactly the way
that we could modify the image
to cause the convolutional network to make a mistake
we find that the optimal direction
to move all the pixels is given by this image in the middle.
To a human it looks a lot like noise.
It's not actually noise.
It's carefully computed as a function
of the parameters of the network.
There's actually a lot of structure there.
If we multiply that image of the structured attack
by a very small coefficient and add it to the original panda
we get an image that a human can't tell
from the original panda.
In fact, on this slide there is no difference
between the panda on the left
and the panda on the right.
When we present the image to convolutional network
we use 32-bit floating point values.
The monitor here can only display eight bits
of color resolution, and we have made a change
that's just barely too small
to affect the smallest of those eight bits,
but it effects the other 24
of the 32-bit floating point representation,
and that little tiny change is enough
to fool the convolutional network
into recognizing this image of a panda as being a gibbon.
Another interesting thing is that
it doesn't just change the class.
It's not that we just barely found the decision boundary
and just barely stepped across it.
The convolutional network actually has much more confidence
in its incorrect prediction,
that the image on the right is a gibbon,
than it had for the original being a panda.
On the right, it believes that the image
is a gibbon with 99.9% probability,
so before it thought that there was about
1/3 chance that it was something other than a panda,
and now it's about as certain as it can possibly be
that it's a gibbon.
As a little bit of history, people have studied ways
of computing attacks to fool
different machine learning models
since at least about 2004, and maybe earlier.
For a long time this was done in the context
of fooling spam detectors.
In about 2013, Battista Biggio found
that you could fool neural networks in this way,
and around the same time my colleague, Christian Szegedy,
found that you could make this kind of attack
against deep neural networks
just by using an optimization algorithm
to search on the input of the image.
A lot of what I'll be telling you about today
is my own follow-up work on this topic,
but I've spent a lot of my career over the past few years
understanding why these attacks are possible
and why it's so easy to fool these convolutional networks.
When my colleague, Christian,
first discovered this phenomenon
independently from Battista Biggio but around the same time,
he found that it was actually a result
of a visualization he was trying to make.
He wasn't studying security.
He wasn't studying how to fool a neural network.
Instead, he had a convolutional network
that could recognize objects very well,
and he wants to understand how it worked,
so he thought that maybe he could take an image of a scene,
for example a picture of a ship,
and he could gradually transform that image
into something that the network would recognize
as being an airplane.
Over the course of that transformation,
he could see how the features of the input change.
or you might expect that the ship
would grow wings to look more like an airplane.
You could conclude from that that the convolution
uses the blue sky or uses the wings to recognize airplanes.
That's actually not really what happened at all.
Each of these panels here shows an animation
that you read left to right, top to bottom.
Each panel is another step of gradient ascent
on the log probability that the input is an airplane
according to a convolutional net model,
and then we follow the gradient on the input to the image.
You're probably used to following the gradient
on the parameters of a model.
You can use the back propagation algorithm
to compute the gradient on the input image
using exactly the same procedure
that you would use to compute the gradient
on the parameters.
In this animation of the ship in the upper left,
we see five panels that all look basically the same.
Gradient descent doesn't seem
to have moved the image at all,
but by the last panel the network is completely confident
that this is an airplane.
When you first code up this kind of experiment,
especially if you don't know what's going to happen,
it feels a little bit like you have a bug in your script
and you're just displaying
the same image over and over again.
The first time I did it,
I couldn't believe it was happening,
and I had to open up the images in NumPy,
and take the difference of them,
and make sure that there was actually
a non-zero difference in there, but there is.
I show several different animations here
of a ship, a car, a cat, and a truck.
The only one where I actually see any change at all
is the image of the cat.
The color of the cat's face changes a little bit,
and maybe it becomes a little bit more
like the color of a metal airplane.
Other than that, I don't see any changes
in any of these animations,
and I don't see anything very suggestive of an airplane.
So gradient descent, rather than turning the input
into an example of an airplane,
has found an image that fools the network
into thinking that the input is an airplane.
And if we were malicious attackers
we didn't even have to work very hard to figure out
how to fool the network.
We just asked the network
to give us an image of an airplane,
and it gave us something that fools it into thinking
that the input is an airplane.
When Christian first published this work,
a lot of articles came out with titles like,
The Flaw Looking At Every Deep Neural Network,
or Deep Learning has Deep Flaws.
It's important to remember that these vulnerabilities
apply to essentially every machine learning algorithm
that we've studied so far.
Some of them like RBF networks
and partisan density estimators
are able to resist this effect somewhat,
but even very simple machine learning algorithms
are highly vulnerable to adversarial examples.
In this image, I show an animation
of what happens when we attack a linear model,
so it's not a deep algorithm at all.
It's just a shallow softmax model.
You multiply by a matrix, you add a vector of bias terms,
you apply the softmax function,
and you've got your probability distribution
over the 10 MNIST classes.
At the upper left, I start with an image of a nine,
and then as we move left to right, top to bottom,
I gradually transform it to be a zero.
Where I've drawn the yellow box,
the model assigns high probability to it being a zero.
I forget exactly what my threshold was for high probability,
but I think it was around 0.9 or so.
Then as we move to the second row,
I transform it into a one,
and the second yellow box indicates
where we've successfully fooled the model
into thinking it's a one with high probability.
And then as you read the rest of the yellow boxes
left to right, top to bottom,
we go through the twos, threes, fours, and so on,
until finally at the lower right
we have a nine that has a yellow box around it,
and it actually looks like a nine,
but in this case the only reason
it actually looks like a nine
is that we started the whole process with a nine.
We successfully swept through all 10 classes of MNIST
without substantially changing the image of the digit
in any way that would interfere with human recognition.
This linear model was actually extremely easy to fool.
Besides linear models, we've also seen
that we can fool many different kinds of linear models
including logistic regression and SVMs.
We've also found that we can fool decision trees,
and to a lesser extent, nearest neighbors classifiers.
We wanted to explain exactly why this happens.
Back in about 2014, after we'd published the original paper
where we'd said that these problems exist,
we were trying to figure out why they happen.
When we wrote our first paper,
we thought that basically this is a form of overfitting,
that you have a very complicated deep neural network,
it learns to fit the training set,
its behavior on the test set is somewhat undefined,
and then it makes random mistakes
that an attacker can exploit.
Let's walk through what that story looks like
somewhat concretely.
I have here a training set of three blue X's
and three green O's.
We want to make a classifier
that can recognize X's and recognize O's.
We have a very complicated classifier
that can easily fit the training set,
so we represent everywhere it believes
X's should be with blobs of blue color,
and I've drawn a blob of blue
around all of the training set X's,
so it correctly classifies the training set.
It also has a blob of green mass showing where the O's are,
and it successfully fits all of the green training set O's,
but then because this is a very complicated function
and it has just way more parameters
than it actually needs to represent the training task,
it throws little blobs of probability mass
around the rest of space randomly.
On the left there's a blob of green space
that's kind of near the training set X's,
and I've drawn a red X there to show
that maybe this would be an adversarial example
where we expect the classification to be X,
but the model assigns O.
On the right, I've shown that there's a red O
where we have another adversarial example.
We're very near the other O's.
We might expect the model to assign this class to be an O,
and yet because it's drawn blue mass there
it's actually assigning it to be an X.
If overfitting is really the story
then each adversarial example is more or less
the result of bad luck and also more or less unique.
If we fit the model again
or we fit a slightly different model
we would expect to make different random mistakes
on this points that are off the training set,
but that was actually not what we found at all.
We found that many different models would misclassify
the same adversarial examples,
and they would assign the same class to them.
We also found that if we took the difference
between an original example and an adversarial example
then we had a direction in input space
and we could add that same offset vector
to any clean example, and we would almost always
get an adversarial example as a result.
So we started to realize
that there was systematic effect going on here,
not just a random effect.
That led us to another idea
which is that adversarial examples
might actually be more like underfitting
rather than overfitting.
They might actually come from the model being too linear.
Here I draw the same task again
where we have the same manifold of O's
and the same line of X's,
and this time I fit a linear model to the data set
rather than fitting a high capacity, non-linear model to it.
We see that we get a dividing hyperplane
running in between the two classes.
This hyperplane doesn't really capture
the true structure of the classes.
The O's are clearly arranged in a C-shaped manifold.
If we keep walking past the end of the O's,
we've crossed the decision boundary and we've drawn a red O
where even though we're very near the decision boundary
and near other O's we believe that it is now an X.
Similarly we can take steps that go from near X's
to just over the line that are classified as O's.
Another thing that's somewhat unusual about this plot
is that if we look at the lower left or upper right corners
these corners are very confidently classified
as being X's on the lower left or O's on the upper right
even though we've never seen any data over there at all.
The linear model family forces the model
to have very high confidence in these regions
that are very far from the decision boundary.
We've seen that linear models can actually assign
really unusual confidence as you move very far
from the decision boundary,
even if there isn't any data there,
but are deep neural networks actually
anything like linear models?
Could linear models actually explain anything
about how it is that deep neural nets fail?
It turns out that modern deep neural nets
are actually very piecewise linear,
so rather than being a single linear function
they are piecewise linear
with maybe not that many linear pieces.
If we use rectified linear units
then the mapping from the input image to the output logits
is literally a piecewise linear function.
By the logits I mean the un-normalized log probabilities
before we apply the softmax op at the output of the model.
There are other neural networks
like maxout networks that are also
literally piecewise linear.
And then there are several that become very close to it.
Before rectified linear units became popular
most people used to use sigmoid units of one form or another
either logistic sigmoid or hyperbolic tangent units.
These sigmoidal units have to be carefully tuned,
especially at initialization
so that you spend most of your time
near the center of the sigmoid
where the sigmoid is approximately linear.
Then finally, the LSTM, a kind of recurrent network
that is one of the most popular recurrent networks today,
uses addition from one time step to the next
in order to accumulate and remember information over time.
Addition is a particularly simple form of linearity,
so we can see that the interaction
from a very distant time step in the past and the present
is highly linear within an LSTM.
Now to be clear, I'm speaking about the mapping
from the input of the model to the output of the model.
That's what I'm saying is close to being linear
or is piecewise linear with relatively few pieces.
The mapping from the parameters of the network
to the output of the network is non-linear
because the weight matrices at each layer of the network
are multiplied together.
So we actually get extremely non-linear reactions
between parameters and the output.
That's what makes training a neural network so difficult.
But the mapping from the input to the output
is much more linear and predictable,
and it means that optimization problems
that aim to optimize the input to the model
are much easier than optimization problems
that aim to optimize the parameters.
If we go and look for this happening in practice
we can take a convolutional network
and trace out a one-dimensional path
through its input space.
So what we're doing here is we're choosing a clean example.
It's an image of a white car on a red background,
and we are choosing a direction
that will travel through space.
We are going to have a coefficient epsilon
that we multiply by this direction.
When epsilon is negative 30,
like at the left end of the plot,
we're subtracting off a lot of this unit vector direction.
When epsilon is zero, like in the middle of the plot,
we're visiting the original image from the data set,
and when epsilon is positive 30,
like at the right end of the plot,
we're adding this direction onto the input.
In the panel on the left, I show you an animation
where we move from epsilon equals negative 30
as up to epsilon equals positive 30.
You read the animation left to right, top to bottom,
and everywhere that there's a yellow box
the input has correctly recognized as being a car.
On the upper left, you see that it looks mostly blue.
On the lower right, it's hard to tell what's going on.
It's kind of reddish and so on.
In the middle row, just after where the yellow boxes end
you can see pretty clearly
that it's a car on a red background,
though the image is small on these slides.
What's interesting to look at here is the logits
that the model outputs.
This is a deep convolutional rectified linear unit network.
Because it uses rectified linear units,
we know that the output is a piecewise linear function
of the input to the model.
The main question we're asking by making this plot
is how many different pieces
does this piecewise linear function have
if we look at one particular cross section.
You might think that maybe a deep net
is going to represent some extremely
wiggly complicated function with lots and lots
of linear pieces no matter which cross section you look in.
Or we might find that it has more or less two pieces
for each function we look at.
Each of the different curves on this plot
is the logits for a different class.
We see that out at the tails of the plot
that the frog class is the most likely,
and the frog class basically looks like
a big v-shaped function.
The logits for the frog class become very high
when epsilon is negative 30 or positive 30,
and they drop down and become a little bit negative
when epsilon is zero.
The car class, listed as automobile here,
it's actually high in the middle,
and the car is correctly recognized.
As we sweep out to very negative epsilon,
the logits for the car class do increase,
but they don't increase nearly as quickly
as the logits for the frog class.
So, we've found a direction
that's associated with the frog class
and as we follow it out to a relatively large perturbation,
we find that the model extrapolates linearly
and begins to make a very unreasonable prediction
that the frog class is extremely likely
just because we've moved for a long time
in this direction that was locally associated
with the frog class being more likely.
When we actually go and construct adversarial examples,
we need to remember that we're able to get
quite a large perturbation
without changing the image very much
as far as a human being is concerned.
So here I show you a handwritten digit three,
and I'm going to change it in several different ways,
and all of these changes have
the same L2 norm perturbation.
In the top row, I'm going to change the three into a seven
just by looking for the nearest seven in the training set.
The difference between those two
is this image that looks a little bit like the seven
wrapped in some black lines.
So here white pixels in the middle image
in the perturbation column,
the white pixels represent adding something
and black pixels represent subtracting something
as you move from the left column to the right column.
So when we take the three and we apply this perturbation
that transforms it into a seven,
we can measure the L2 norm of that perturbation.
And it turns out to have an L2 norm of 3.96.
That gives you kind of a reference
for how big these perturbations can be.
In the middle row, we apply a perturbation
of exactly the same size,
but with the direction chosen randomly.
In this case we don't actually change
the class of the three at all,
we just get some random noise
that didn't really change the class.
A human could still easily read it as being a three.
And then finally at the very bottom row,
we take the three and we just erase a piece of it
with a perturbation of the same norm
and we turn it into something
that doesn't have any class at all.
It's not a three, it's not a seven,
it's just a defective input.
All of these changes can happen
with the same L2 norm perturbation.
And actually a lot of the time with adversarial examples,
you make perturbations that have an even larger L2 norm.
What's going on is that
there are several different pixels in the image,
and so small changes to individual pixels
can add up to relatively large vectors.
For larger datasets like ImageNet,
where there's even more pixels,
you can make very small changes to each pixel
that travel very far in vector space
as measured by the L2 norm.
That means that you can actually make changes
that are almost imperceptible
but actually move you really far
and get a large dot product
with the coefficients of the linear function
that the model represents.
It also means that when
we're constructing adversarial examples,
we need to make sure that the adversarial example procedure
isn't able to do what happened
in the top row of this slide here.
So in the top row of this slide,
we took the three and we actually
just changed it into a seven.
So when the model says that the image
in the upper right is a seven, it's not a mistake.
We actually just changed the input class.
When we build adversarial examples,
we want to make sure that we're measuring real mistakes.
If we're experimenters studying
how easy a network is to fool,
we want to make sure that we're actually fooling it
and not just changing the input class.
And if we're an attacker, we actually want to make sure
that we're causing misbehavior in the system.
To do that, when we build adversarial examples,
we use the maxnorm to constrain the perturbation.
Basically this says that no pixel can change
by more than some amount epsilon.
So the L2 norm can get really big,
but you can't concentrate all the changes
for that L2 norm to erase pieces of the digit,
like in the bottom row here we erased the top of a three.
One very fast way to build an adversarial example
is just to take the gradient of the cost
that you used to train the network
with respect to the input,
and then take the sign of that gradient.
The sign is essentially enforcing the maxnorm constraint.
You're only allowed to change the input by
up to epsilon at each pixel,
so if you just take the sign it tells you
whether you want to add epsilon or subtract epsilon
in order to hurt the network.
You can view this as taking the observation
that the network is more or less linear,
as we showed on this slide,
and using that to motivate
building a first order Taylor series approximation
of the neural network's cost.
And then subject to that Taylor series approximation,
we want to maximize the cost
following this maxnorm constraint.
And that gives us this technique that we call
the fast gradient sign method.
If you want to just get your hands dirty
and start making adversarial examples really quickly,
or if you have an algorithm where you want to train
on adversarial examples in the inner loop of learning,
this method will make adversarial examples for you
very, very quickly.
In practice you should also use other methods,
like Nicholas Carlini's attack based on
multiple steps of the Adam optimizer,
to make sure that you have a very strong attack
that you bring out when you think you have a model
that might be more powerful.
A lot of the time people find that they can defeat
the fast gradient sign method
and think that they've built a successful defense,
but then when you bring out a more powerful method
that takes longer to evaluate,
they find that they can't overcome
the more computationally expensive attack.
I've told you that adversarial examples happen
because the model is very linear.
And then I told you that we could
use this linearity assumption
to build this attack, the fast gradient sign method.
This method, when applied to a regular neural network
that doesn't have any special defenses,
will get over a 99% attack success rate.
So that seems to confirm, somewhat,
this hypothesis that adversarial examples
come from the model being far too linear
and extrapolating in linear fashions when it shouldn't.
Well we can actually go looking for some more evidence.
My friend David Warde-Farley and I built these maps
of the decision boundaries of neural networks.
And we found that they are consistent
with the linearity hypothesis.
So the FGSM is that attack method
that I described in the previous slide,
where we take the sign of the gradient.
We'd like to build a map
of a two-dimensional cross section of input space
and show which classes are assigned
to the data at each point.
In the grid on the right, each different cell,
each little square within the grid,
is a map of a CIFAR-10 classifier's decision boundary,
with each cell corresponding to a different
CIFAR-10 testing sample.
On the left I show you a little legend
where you can understand what each cell means.
The very center of each cell corresponds to
the original example from the CIFAR-10 dataset
with no modification.
As we move left to right in the cell,
we're moving in the direction
of the fast gradient sign method attack.
So just the sign of the gradient.
As we move up and down within the cell,
we're moving in a random direction that's orthogonal to
the fast gradient sign method direction.
So we get to see a cross section, a 2D cross section
of CIFAR-10 decision space.
At each pixel within this map,
we plot a color that tells us which class is assigned there.
We use white pixels to indicate that
the correct class was chosen,
and then we used different colors to represent
all of the other incorrect classes.
You can see that in nearly all
of the grid cells on the right,
roughly the left half of the image is white.
So roughly the left half of the image
has been correctly classified.
As we move to the right, we see that there is usually
a different color on the right half.
And the boundaries between these regions