- Okay, let's get started.
Alright, so welcome to lecture five.
Today we're going to be getting to the title of the class,
Convolutional Neural Networks.
Okay, so a couple of administrative details
before we get started.
Assignment one is due Thursday,
April 20, 11:59 p.m. on Canvas.
We're also going to be releasing assignment two on Thursday.
Okay, so a quick review of last time.
We talked about neural networks, and how we had
the running example of the linear score function
that we talked about through the first few lectures.
And then we turned this into a neural network
by stacking these linear layers on top of each other
with non-linearities in between.
And we also saw that this could help address
the mode problem where we are able to learn
intermediate templates that are looking for,
for example, different types of cars, right.
A red car versus a yellow car and so on.
And to combine these together to come up with
the final score function for a class.
Okay, so today we're going to talk about
convolutional neural networks,
which is basically the same sort of idea,
but now we're going to learn convolutional layers
that reason on top of basically explicitly
trying to maintain spatial structure.
So, let's first talk a little bit about
the history of neural networks, and then also
how convolutional neural networks were developed.
So we can go all the way back to 1957 with Frank Rosenblatt,
who developed the Mark I Perceptron machine,
which was the first implementation of an algorithm
called the perceptron, which had sort of the similar idea
of getting score functions, right, using some,
you know, W times X plus a bias.
But here the outputs are going to be either one or a zero.
And then in this case we have an update rule,
so an update rule for our weights, W,
which also look kind of similar to the type of update rule
that we're also seeing in backprop, but in this case
there was no principled backpropagation technique yet,
we just sort of took the weights and adjusted them
in the direction towards the target that we wanted.
So in 1960, we had Widrow and Hoff,
who developed Adaline and Madaline, which was the first time
that we were able to get, to start to stack
these linear layers into multilayer perceptron networks.
And so this is starting to now look kind of like this idea
of neural network layers, but we still didn't have backprop
or any sort of principled way to train this.
And so the first time backprop was really introduced
was in 1986 with Rumelhart.
And so here we can start seeing, you know, these kinds of
equations with the chain rule and the update rules
that we're starting to get familiar with, right,
and so this is the first time we started
to have a principled way to train
these kinds of network architectures.
And so after that, you know, it still wasn't able to scale
to very large neural networks, and so there was sort of
a period in which there wasn't a whole lot
of new things happening here, or a lot of popular use
of these kinds of networks.
And so this really started being reinvigorated
around the 2000s, so in 2006, there was this paper
by Geoff Hinton and Ruslan Salakhutdinov,
which basically showed that we could train
a deep neural network,
and show that we could do this effectively.
But it was still not quite
the sort of modern iteration of neural networks.
It required really careful initialization
in order to be able to do backprop,
and so what they had here was they would have
this first pre-training stage, where you model
each hidden layer through this kind of,
through a restricted Boltzmann machine,
and so you're going to get some initialized weights
by training each of these layers iteratively.
And so once you get all of these hidden layers
you then use that to initialize your, you know,
your full neural network, and then from there
you do backprop and fine tuning of that.
And so when we really started to get the first really strong
results using neural networks, and what sort of really
sparked the whole craze of starting to use these
kinds of networks really widely was at around 2012,
where we had first the strongest results
using for speech recognition,
and so this is work out of Geoff Hinton's lab
for acoustic modeling and speech recognition.
And then for image recognition, 2012 was the landmark paper
from Alex Krizhevsky in Geoff Hinton's lab,
which introduced the first convolutional neural network
architecture that was able to do,
get really strong results on ImageNet classification.
And so it took the ImageNet, image classification benchmark,
and was able to dramatically reduce
the error on that benchmark.
And so since then, you know, ConvNets have gotten
really widely used in all kinds of applications.
So now let's step back and take a look at what gave rise
to convolutional neural networks specifically.
And so we can go back to the 1950s,
where Hubel and Wiesel did a series of experiments
trying to understand how neurons
in the visual cortex worked,
and they studied this specifically for cats.
And so we talked a little bit about this in lecture one,
but basically in these experiments they put electrodes
in the cat, into the cat brain,
and they gave the cat different visual stimulus.
Right, and so, things like, you know,
different kinds of edges, oriented edges,
different sorts of shapes, and they measured
the response of the neurons to these stimuli.
And so there were a couple of important conclusions
that they were able to make, and observations.
And so the first thing found that, you know,
there's sort of this topographical mapping in the cortex.
So nearby cells in the cortex also represent
nearby regions in the visual field.
And so you can see for example, on the right here
where if you take kind of the spatial mapping
and map this onto a visual cortex
there's more peripheral regions are these blue areas,
you know, farther away from the center.
And so they also discovered that these neurons
had a hierarchical organization.
And so if you look at different types of visual stimuli
they were able to find that at the earliest layers
retinal ganglion cells were responsive to things
that looked kind of like circular regions of spots.
And then on top of that there are simple cells,
and these simple cells are responsive to oriented edges,
so different orientation of the light stimulus.
And then going further, they discover that these
were then connected to more complex cells,
which were responsive to both light orientation
as well as movement, and so on.
And you get, you know, increasing complexity,
for example, hypercomplex cells are now responsive
to movement with kind of an endpoint, right,
and so now you're starting to get the idea of corners
and then blobs and so on.
And so
then in 1980, the neocognitron was the first example
of a network architecture, a model,
that had this idea of simple and complex cells
that Hubel and Wiesel had discovered.
And in this case Fukushima put these into
these alternating layers of simple and complex cells,
where you had these simple cells
that had modifiable parameters, and then complex cells
on top of these that performed a sort of pooling
so that it was invariant to, you know,
different minor modifications from the simple cells.
And so this is work that was in the 1980s, right,
and so by 1998 Yann LeCun
basically showed the first example
of applying backpropagation and gradient-based learning
to train convolutional neural networks
that did really well on document recognition.
And specifically they were able to do a good job
of recognizing digits of zip codes.
And so these were then used pretty widely
for zip code recognition in the postal service.
But beyond that it wasn't able to scale yet
to more challenging and complex data, right,
digits are still fairly simple
and a limited set to recognize.
And so this is where Alex Krizhevsky, in 2012,
gave the modern incarnation of convolutional neural networks
and his network we sort of colloquially call AlexNet.
But this network really didn't look so much different
than the convolutional neural networks
that Yann LeCun was dealing with.
They're now, you know, they were scaled now
to be larger and deeper and able to,
the most important parts were that they were now able
to take advantage of the large amount of data
that's now available, in web images, in ImageNet data set.
As well as take advantage
of the parallel computing power in GPUs.
And so we'll talk more about that later.
But fast forwarding today, so now, you know,
ConvNets are used everywhere.
And so we have the initial classification results
on ImageNet from Alex Krizhevsky.
This is able to do a really good job of image retrieval.
You can see that when we're trying to retrieve a flower
for example, the features that are learned
are really powerful for doing similarity matching.
We also have ConvNets that are used for detection.
So we're able to do a really good job of localizing
where in an image is, for example, a bus, or a boat,
and so on, and draw precise bounding boxes around that.
We're able to go even deeper beyond that to do segmentation,
right, and so these are now richer tasks
where we're not looking for just the bounding box
but we're actually going to label every pixel
in the outline of, you know, trees, and people, and so on.
And these kind of algorithms are used in,
for example, self-driving cars,
and a lot of this is powered by GPUs as I mentioned earlier,
that's able to do parallel processing
and able to efficiently train and run these ConvNets.
And so we have modern powerful GPUs as well as ones
that work in embedded systems, for example,
that you would use in a self-driving car.
So we can also look at some of the other applications
that ConvNets are used for.
So, face-recognition, right, we can put an input image
of a face and get out a likelihood of who this person is.
ConvNets are applied to video, and so this is an example
of a video network that looks at both images
as well as temporal information,
and from there is able to classify videos.
We're also able to do pose recognition.
Being able to recognize, you know,
shoulders, elbows, and different joints.
And so here are some images of our fabulous TA, Lane,
in various kinds of pretty non-standard human poses.
But ConvNets are able to do a pretty good job
of pose recognition these days.
They're also used in game playing.
So some of the work in reinforcement learning,
deeper enforcement learning that you may have seen,
playing Atari games, and Go, and so on,
and ConvNets are an important part of all of these.
Some other applications, so they're being used for
interpretation and diagnosis of medical images,
for classification of galaxies, for street sign recognition.
There's also whale recognition,
this is from a recent Kaggle Challenge.
We also have examples of looking at aerial maps
and being able to draw out where are the streets
on these maps, where are buildings,
and being able to segment all of these.
And then beyond recognition of classification detection,
these types of tasks, we also have tasks
like image captioning, where given an image,
we want to write a sentence description
about what's in the image.
And so this is something that we'll go into
a little bit later in the class.
And we also have, you know, really, really fancy and cool
kind of artwork that we can do using neural networks.
And so on the left is an example of a deep dream,
where we're able to take images and kind of hallucinate
different kinds of objects and concepts in the image.
There's also neural style type work, where we take an image
and we're able to re-render this image
using a style of a particular artist and artwork, right.
And so here we can take, for example, Van Gogh on the right,
Starry Night, and use that to redraw
our original image using that style.
And Justin has done a lot of work in this
and so if you guys are interested,
these are images produced by some of his code
and you guys should talk to him more about it.
Okay, so basically, you know, this is just a small sample
of where ConvNets are being used today.
But there's really a huge amount that can be done with this,
right, and so, you know, for you guys' projects,
sort of, you know, let your imagination go wild
and we're excited to see what sorts of applications
you can come up with.
So today we're going to talk about
how convolutional neural networks work.
And again, same as with neural networks, we're going to first
talk about how they work from a functional perspective
without any of the brain analogies.
And then we'll talk briefly about some of these connections.
Okay, so, last lecture, we talked about
this idea of a fully connected layer.
And how, you know, for a fully connected layer
what we're doing is we operate on top of these vectors,
right, and so let's say we have, you know, an image,
a 3D image, 32 by 32 by three,
so some of the images that we were looking at previously.
We'll take that, we'll stretch all of the pixels out, right,
and then we have this 3072 dimensional vector,
for example in this case.
And then we have these weights, right,
so we're going to multiply this by a weight matrix.
And so here for example our W we're going to say is 10 by 3072.
And then we're going to get the activations,
the output of this layer, right, and so in this case,
we take each of our 10 rows and we do this dot product
with 3072 dimensional input.
And from there we get this one number
that's kind of the value of that neuron.
And so in this case we're going to have
10 of these neuron outputs.
And so a convolutional layer, so the main difference
between this and the fully connected layer
that we've been talking about
is that here we want to preserve spatial structure.
And so taking this 32 by 32 by three image
that we had earlier, instead of stretching this all out
into one long vector, we're now going to keep the structure
of this image, right, this three dimensional input.
And then what we're going to do is
our weights are going to be these small filters,
so in this case for example, a five by five by three filter,
and we're going to take this filter
and we're going to slide it over the image spatially
and compute dot products at every spatial location.
And so we're going to go into detail of exactly how this works.
So, our filters, first of all,
always extend the full depth of the input volume.
And so they're going to be just a smaller spatial area,
so in this case five by five, right,
instead of our full 32 by 32 spatial input,
but they're always going to go through the full depth, right,
so here we're going to take five by five by three.
And then we're going to take this filter
and at a given spatial location
we're going to do a dot product
between this filter and then a chunk of a image.
So we're just going to overlay this filter
on top of a spatial location in the image,
right, and then do the dot product,
the multiplication of each element of that filter
with each corresponding element in that spatial location
that we've just plopped it on top of.
And then this is going to give us a dot product.
So in this case, we have five times five times three,
this is the number of multiplications
that we're going to do, right, plus the bias term.
And so this is basically taking our filter W
and basically doing W transpose times X and plus bias.
So is that clear how this works?
Yeah, question.
[faint speaking]
Yeah, so the question is, when we do the dot product
do we turn the five by five by three into one vector?
Yeah, in essence that's what you're doing.
You can, I mean, you can think of it as just
plopping it on and doing the element-wise multiplication
at each location, but this is going to give you the same result
as if you stretched out the filter at that point,
stretched out the input volume that it's laid over,
and then took the dot product,
and that's what's written here, yeah, question.
[faint speaking]
Oh, this is, so the question is,
any intuition for why this is a W transpose?
And this was just, not really,
this is just the notation that we have here
to make the math work out as a dot product.
So it just depends on whether, how you're representing W
and whether in this case if we look at the W matrix
this happens to be each column and so we're just taking
the transpose to get a row out of it.
But there's no intuition here,
we're just taking the filters of W
and we're stretching it out into a one D vector,
and in order for it to be a dot product
it has to be like a one by, one by N vector.
[faint speaking]
Okay, so the question is,
is W here not five by five by three, it's one by 75.
So that's the case, right, if we're going
to do this dot product of W transpose times X,
we have to stretch it out first
before we do the dot product.
So we take the five by five by three,
and we just take all these values
and stretch it out into a long vector.
And so again, similar to the other question,
the actual operation that we're doing here
is plopping our filter on top of
a spatial location in the image
and multiplying all of the corresponding values together,
but in order just to make it kind of an easy expression
similar to what we've seen before
we can also just stretch each of these out,
make sure that dimensions are transposed correctly
so that it works out as a dot product.
Yeah, question.
[faint speaking]
Okay, the question is,
how do we slide the filter over the image.
We'll go into that next, yes.
[faint speaking]
Okay, so the question is, should we rotate the kernel
by 180 degrees to better match the convolution,
the definition of a convolution.
And so the answer is that we'll also show the equation
for this later, but we're using convolution
as kind of a looser definition of what's happening.
So for people from signal processing,
what we are actually technically doing,
if you want to call this a convolution,
is we're convolving with the flipped version of the filter.
But for the most part, we just don't worry about this
and we just, yeah, do this operation
and it's like a convolution in spirit.
Okay, so...
Okay, so we had a question earlier, how do we, you know,
slide this over all the spatial locations.
Right, so what we're going to do is
we're going to take this filter, we're going to start
at the upper left-hand corner and basically center
our filter on top of every pixel in this input volume.
And at every position, we're going to do this dot product
and this will produce one value
in our output activation map.
And so then we're going to just slide this around.
The simplest version is just at every pixel
we're going to do this operation and fill in
the corresponding point in our output activation.
You can see here that the dimensions are not exactly
what would happen, right, if you're going to do this.
I had 32 by 32 in the input
and I'm having 28 by 28 in the output,
and so we'll go into examples later of the math
of exactly how this is going to work out dimension-wise,
but basically you have a choice
of how you're going to slide this,
whether you go at every pixel or whether you slide,
let's say, you know, two input values over at a time,
two pixels over at a time,
and so you can get different size outputs
depending on how you choose to slide.
But you're basically doing this operation in a grid fashion.
Okay, so what we just saw earlier,
this is taking one filter, sliding it over
all of the spatial locations in the image
and then we're going to get this activation map out, right,
which is the value of that filter at every spatial location.
And so when we're dealing with a convolutional layer,
we want to work with multiple filters, right,
because each filter is kind of looking for a specific
type of template or concept in the input volume.
And so we're going to have a set of multiple filters,
and so here I'm going to take a second filter,
this green filter, which is again five by five by three,
I'm going to slide this over all of the spatial locations
in my input volume, and then I'm going to get out
this second green activation map also of the same size.
And we can do this for as many filters
as we want to have in this layer.
So for example, if we have six filters,
six of these five by five filters,
then we're going to get in total six activation maps out.
All of, so we're going to get this output volume
that's going to be basically six by 28 by 28.
Right, and so a preview of how we're going to use
these convolutional layers in our convolutional network
is that our ConvNet is basically going to be
a sequence of these convolutional layers
stacked on top of each other, same way as what we had
with the simple linear layers in their neural network.
And then we're going to intersperse these
with activation functions,
so for example, a ReLU activation function.
Right, and so you're going to get something like Conv, ReLU,
and usually also some pooling layers,
and then you're just going to get a sequence of these
each creating an output that's now going to be
the input to the next convolutional layer.
Okay, and so each of these layers, as I said earlier,
has multiple filters, right, many filters.
And each of the filter is producing an activation map.
And so when you look at multiple of these layers
stacked together in a ConvNet, what ends up happening
is you end up learning this hierarching of filters,
where the filters at the earlier layers usually represent
low-level features that you're looking for.
So things kind of like edges, right.
And then at the mid-level,
you're going to get more complex kinds of features,
so maybe it's looking more for things
like corners and blobs and so on.
And then at higher-level features,
you're going to get things that are starting
to more resemble concepts than blobs.
And we'll go into more detail later in the class
in how you can actually visualize all these features
and try and interpret what your network,
what kinds of features your network is learning.
But the important thing for now is just to understand
that what these features end up being
when you have a whole stack of these,
is these types of simple to more complex features.
[faint speaking]
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
Oh, okay, so the question is, what's the intuition
for increasing the depth each time.
So here I had three filters in the original layer
and then six filters in the next layer.
Right, and so this is mostly a design choice.
You know, people in practice have found
certain types of these configurations to work better.
And so later on we'll go into case studies of different
kinds of convolutional neural network architectures
and design choices for these
and why certain ones work better than others.
But yeah, basically the choice of,
you're going to have many design choices
in a convolutional neural network,
the size of your filter, the stride,
how many filters you have,
and so we'll talk about this all more later.
Question.
[faint speaking]
Yeah, so the question is, as we're sliding this filter
over the image spatially it looks like we're sampling
the edges and corners less than the other locations.
Yeah, that's a really good point,
and we'll talk I think in a few slides
about how we try and compensate for that.
Okay, so each of these convolutional layers
that we have stacked together, we saw how we're starting
with more simpler features and then aggregating these
into more complex features later on.
And so in practice this is compatible
with what Hubel and Wiesel noticed in their experiments,
right, that we had these simple cells
at the earlier stages of processing,
followed by more complex cells later on.
And so even though we didn't explicitly
force our ConvNet to learn these kinds of features,
in practice when you give it this type of
hierarchical structure and train it using backpropagation,
these are the kinds of filters that end up being learned.
[faint speaking]
Okay, so yeah, so the question is,
what are we seeing in these visualizations.
And so, alright so, in these visualizations, like,
if we look at this Conv1, the first convolutional layer,
each of these grid, each part of this grid is a one neuron.
And so what we've visualized here
is what the input looks like that maximizes
the activation of that particular neuron.
So what sort of image you would get
that would give you the largest value,
make that neuron fire and have the largest value.
And so the way we do this is basically
by doing backpropagation from a particular neuron activation
and seeing what in the input will trigger,
will give you the highest values of this neuron.
And this is something that we'll talk about
in much more depth in a later lecture
about how we create all of these visualizations.
But basically each element of these grids
is showing what in the input would look like
that basically maximizes the activation of the neuron.
So in a sense, what is the neuron looking for?
Okay, so here is an example of some of the activation maps
produced by each filter, right.
So we can visualize up here on the top
we have this whole row of example five by five filters,
and so this is basically a real case from a trained ConvNet
where each of these is what a five by five filter
looks like, and then as we convolve this over an image,
so in this case this I think it's like a corner of a car,
the car light, what the activation looks like.
Right, and so here for example,
if we look at this first one, this red filter,
filter like with a red box around it,
we'll see that it's looking for,
the template looks like an edge, right, an oriented edge.
And so if you slide it over the image,
it'll have a high value, a more white value
where there are edges in this type of orientation.
And so each of these activation maps is kind of the output
of sliding one of these filters over
and where these filters are causing, you know,
where this sort of template is more present in the image.
And so the reason we call these convolutional is because
this is related to the convolution of two signals,
and so someone pointed out earlier
that this is basically this convolution equation over here,
for people who have seen convolutions before
in signal processing, and in practice
it's actually more like a correlation
where we're convolving with the flipped version
of the filter, but this is kind of a subtlety,
it's not really important for the purposes of this class.
But basically if you're writing out what you're doing,
it has an expression that looks something like this,
which is the standard definition of a convolution.
But this is basically just taking a filter,
sliding it spatially over the image
and computing the dot product at every location.
Okay, so you know, as I had mentioned earlier,
like what our total convolutional neural network
is going to look like is we're going to have an input image,
and then we're going to pass it through
this sequence of layers, right,
where we're going to have a convolutional layer first.
We usually have our non-linear layer after that.
So ReLU is something that's very commonly used
that we're going to talk about more later.
And then we have these Conv, ReLU, Conv, ReLU layers,
and then once in a while we'll use a pooling layer
that we'll talk about later as well
that basically downsamples the size of our activation maps.
And then finally at the end of this we'll take our last
convolutional layer output and then we're going to use
a fully connected layer that we've seen before,
connected to all of these convolutional outputs,
and use that to get a final score function
basically like what we've already been working with.
Okay, so now let's work out some examples
of how the spatial dimensions work out.
So let's take our 32 by 32 by three image as before,
right, and we have our five by five by three filter
that we're going to slide over this image.
And we're going to see how we're going to use that
to produce exactly this 28 by 28 activation map.
So let's assume that we actually have a seven by seven input
just to be simpler, and let's assume
we have a three by three filter.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to take this filter,
plop it down in our upper left-hand corner,
right, and we're going to multiply, do the dot product,
multiply all these values together to get our first value,
and this is going to go into the upper left-hand value
of our activation map.
Right, and then what we're going to do next
is we're just going to take this filter,
slide it one position to the right,
and then we're going to get another value out from here.
And so we can continue with this to have another value,
another, and in the end what we're going to get
is a five by five output, right,
because what fit was basically sliding this filter
a total of five spatial locations horizontally
and five spatial locations vertically.
Okay, so as I said before
there's different kinds of design choices that we can make.
Right, so previously I slid it at every single
spatial location and the interval at which I slide
I'm going to call the stride.
And so previously we used the stride of one.
And so now let's see what happens
if we have a stride of two.
Right, so now we're going to take our first location
the same as before, and then we're going to skip
this time two pixels over and we're going to get
our next value centered at this location.
Right, and so now if we use a stride of two,
we have in total three of these that can fit,
and so we're going to get a three by three output.
Okay, and so what happens when we have a stride of three,
what's the output size of this?
And so in this case, right, we have three,