- Okay, it's after 12, so I think
we should get started.
Today we're going to kind of pick up
where we left off last time.
Last time we talked about a lot of
sort of tips and tricks involved
in the nitty gritty details of training
neural networks.
Today we'll pick up where we left off,
and talk about a lot more of these
sort of nitty gritty details about
training these things.
As usual, a couple administrative notes
before we get into the material.
As you all know, assignment one is already due.
Hopefully you all turned it in.
Did it go okay? Was it not okay?
Rough sentiment?
Mostly okay.
Okay, that's good.
Awesome. [laughs]
We're in the process of grading those,
so stay turned.
We're hoping to get grades back for those
before A two is due.
Another reminder, that your project proposals
are due tomorrow.
Actually, no, today at 11:59.
Make sure you send those in.
Details are on the website and on Piazza.
Also a reminder, assignment two is already out.
That'll be due a week from Thursday.
Historically, assignment two has been the
longest one in the class, so if you
haven't started already on assignment two,
I'd recommend you take a look at that
pretty soon.
Another reminder is that for assignment two,
I think of a lot of you will be using
Google Cloud.
Big reminder, make sure to stop your instances
when you're not using them because
whenever your instance is on, you get charged,
and we only have so many coupons
to distribute to you guys.
Anytime your instance is on, even if
you're not SSH to it, even if you're not
running things immediately in your Jupyter Notebook,
any time that instance is on, you're going to be charged.
Just make sure that you explicitly stop
your instances when you're not using them.
In this example, I've got a little screenshot
of my dashboard on Google Cloud.
I need to go in there and explicitly
go to the dropdown and click stop.
Just make sure that you do this when
you're done working each day.
Another thing to remember is it's kind of
up to you guys to keep track of your spending
on Google Cloud.
In particular, instances that use GPUs
are a lot more expensive than those with CPUs.
Rough order of magnitude, those GPU instances
are around 90 cents to a dollar an hour.
Those are actually quite pricey.
The CPU instances are much cheaper.
The general strategy is that you probably
want to make two instances, one with a GPU
and one without, and then only use that
GPU instance when you really need the GPU.
For example, on assignment two,
most of the assignment, you should only need
the CPU, so you should only use your
CPU instance for that.
But then the final question, about TensorFlow
or PyTorch, that will need a GPU.
This'll give you a little bit of practice
with switching between multiple instances
and only using that GPU when it's really necessary.
Again, just kind of watch your spending.
Try not to go too crazy on these things.
Any questions on the administrative stuff
before we move on?
Question.
- [Student] How much RAM should we use?
- Question is how much RAM should we use?
I think eight or 16 gigs is probably good
for everything that you need in this class.
As you scale up the number of CPUs
and the number of RAM, you also end up
spending more money.
If you stick with two or four CPUs
and eight or 16 gigs of RAM, that should
be plenty for all the homework-related stuff
that you need to do.
As a quick recap, last time we talked about
activation functions.
We talked about this whole zoo
of different activation functions and some
of their different properties.
We saw that the sigmoid, which used
to be quite popular when training neural networks
maybe 10 years ago or so, has this problem
with vanishing gradients near the two ends
of the activation function.
tanh has this similar sort of problem.
Kind of the general recommendation is that
you probably want to stick with ReLU
for most cases as sort of a default choice
'cause it tends to work well for a lot
of different architectures.
We also talked about weight initialization.
Remember that up on the top, we have this idea
that when you initialize your weights
at the start of training, if those weights
are initialized to be too small, then if you
look at, then the activations will vanish
as you go through the network because
as you multiply by these small numbers
over and over again, they'll all
sort of decay to zero.
Then everything will be zero, learning won't happen,
you'll be sad.
On the other hand, if you initialize
your weights too big, then as you go through
the network and multiply by your weight matrix
over and over again, eventually they'll explode.
You'll be unhappy, there'll be no learning,
it will be very bad.
But if you get that initialization just right,
for example, using the Xavier initialization
or the MSRA initialization, then you kind of keep
a nice distribution of activations
as you go through the network.
Remember that this kind of gets more
and more important and more and more critical
as your networks get deeper and deeper
because as your network gets deeper,
you're multiplying by those weight matrices
over and over again with these more multiplicative terms.
We also talked last time about data preprocessing.
We talked about how it's pretty typical
in conv nets to zero center and normalize
your data so it has zero mean and unit variance.
I wanted to provide a little bit of extra intuition
about why you might actually want to do this.
Imagine a simple setup where we have
a binary classification problem where we
want to draw a line to separate these red points
from these blue points.
On the left, you have this idea where
if those data points are kind of not normalized
and not centered and far away from the origin,
then we can still use a line to separate them,
but now if that line wiggles just a little bit,
then our classification is going to get
totally destroyed.
That kind of means that in the example
on the left, the loss function is now
extremely sensitive to small perturbations
in that linear classifier in our weight matrix.
We can still represent the same functions,
but that might make learning quite difficult
because, again, their loss is very sensitive
to our parameter vector, whereas in the situation
on the right, if you take that data cloud
and you move it into the origin and you make it
unit variance, then now, again, we can still
classify that data quite well, but now
as we wiggle that line a little bit,
then our loss function is less sensitive
to small perturbations in the parameter values.
That maybe makes optimization a little bit easier,
as we'll see a little bit going forward.
By the way, this situation is not only
in the linear classification case.
Inside a neural network, remember we kind of have
these interleavings of these linear
matrix multiplies, or convolutions, followed by
non-linear activation functions.
If the input to some layer in your
neural network is not centered or not
zero mean, not unit variance, then again,
small perturbations in the weight matrix
of that layer of the network could cause
large perturbations in the output of that layer,
which, again, might make learning difficult.
This is kind of a little bit of extra
intuition about why normalization
might be important.
Because we have this intuition that normalization
is so important, we talked about batch normalization,
which is where we just add this additional layer
inside our networks to just force all
of the intermediate activations to be zero mean
and unit variance.
I've sort of resummarized the
batch normalization equations here
with the shapes a little bit more explicitly.
Hopefully this can help you out
when you're implementing this thing
on assignment two.
But again, in batch normalization, we have
this idea that in the forward pass,
we use the statistics of the mini batch
to compute a mean and a standard deviation,
and then use those estimates to normalize
our data on the forward pass.
Then we also reintroduce the scale
and shift parameters to increase
the expressivity of the layer.
You might want to refer back to this
when working on assignment two.
We also talked last time a little bit about
babysitting the learning process, how you
should probably be looking at your loss curves
during training.
Here's an example of some networks
I was actually training over the weekend.
This is usually my setup when I'm working
on these things.
On the left, I have some plot showing
the training loss over time.
You can see it's kind of going down,
which means my network is reducing the loss.
It's doing well.
On the right, there's this plot where
the X axis is, again, time, or the iteration number,
and the Y axis is my performance measure
both on my training set and on my validation set.
You can see that as we go over time,
then my training set performance goes up
and up and up and up and up as my loss function
goes down, but at some point, my validation set
performance kind of plateaus.
This kind of suggests that maybe
I'm overfitting in this situation.
Maybe I should have been trying to add
additional regularization.
We also talked a bit last time about
hyperparameter search.
All these networks have sort of a large zoo
of hyperparameters.
It's pretty important to set them correctly.
We talked a little bit about grid search
versus random search, and how random search
is maybe a little bit nicer in theory
because in the situation where your performance
might be more sensitive, with respect
to one hyperparameter than other, and random search
lets you cover that space a little bit better.
We also talked about the idea of coarse
to fine search, where when you're doing
this hyperparameter optimization, probably you
want to start with very wide ranges
for your hyperparameters, only train
for a couple iterations, and then based on
those results, you kind of narrow in
on the range of hyperparameters that are good.
Now, again, redo your search in a smaller range
for more iterations.
You can kind of iterate this process
to kind of hone in on the right region
for hyperparameters.
But again, it's really important to,
at the start, have a very coarse range
to start with, where you want very, very wide
ranges for all your hyperparameters.
Ideally, those ranges should be so wide
that your network is kind of blowing up
at either end of the range so that you know
that you've searched a wide enough range
for those things.
Question?
- [Student] How many [speaks too low to hear]
optimize at once?
[speaks too low to hear]
- The question is how many hyperparameters
do we typically search at a time?
Here is two, but there's a lot more than two
in these typical things.
It kind of depends on the exact model
and the exact architecture, but because
the number of possibilities is exponential
in the number of hyperparameters,
you can't really test too many at a time.
It also kind of depends on how many machines
you have available.
It kind of varies from person to person
and from experiment to experiment.
But generally, I try not to do this over more
than maybe two or three or four at a time
at most because, again, this exponential search
just gets out of control.
Typically, learning rate is the really important one
that you need to nail first.
Then other things, like regularization,
like learning rate decay, model size,
these other types of things tend to be a
little bit less sensitive than learning rate.
Sometimes you might do kind of a block
coordinate descent, where you go and find
the good learning rate, then you go back and try
to look at different model sizes.
This can help you cut down on the
exponential search a little bit,
but it's a little bit problem dependent
on exactly which ones you should be searching over
in which order.
More questions?
- [Student] [speaks too low to hear]
Another parameter, but then changing that
other parameter, two or three other parameters,
makes it so that your learning rate or the ideal
learning rate is still [speaks too low to hear].
- Question is how often does it happen where
when you change one hyperparameter,
then the other, the optimal values of the other
hyperparameters change?
That does happen sometimes, although for learning rates,
that's typically less of a problem.
For learning rates, typically you want to get
in a good range, and then set it maybe even
a little bit lower than optimal, and let it go
for a long time.
Then if you do that, combined with some
of the fancier optimization strategies that
we'll talk about today, then a lot of models
tend to be a little bit less sensitive
to learning rate once you get them in a good range.
Sorry, did you have a question in front, as well?
- [Student] [speaks too low to hear]
- The question is what's wrong with having
a small learning rate and increasing
the number of epochs?
The answer is that it might take
a very long time. [laughs]
- [Student] [speaks too low to hear]
- Intuitively, if you set the learning rate
very low and let it go for a very long time,
then this should, in theory, always work.
But in practice, those factors of 10 or 100
actually matter a lot when you're training
these things.
Maybe if you got the right learning rate,
you could train it in six hours, 12 hours
or a day, but then if you just were super safe
and dropped it by a factor of 10
or by a factor of 100, now that one-day training
becomes 100 days of training.
That's three months.
That's not going to be good.
When you're taking these intro
computer science classes, they always kind of sweep
the constants under the rug, but when
you're actually thinking about training things,
those constants end up mattering a lot.
Another question?
- [Student] If you have a low learning rate,
[speaks too low to hear].
- Question is for a low learning rate,
are you more likely to be stuck in local optima?
I think that makes some intuitive sense,
but in practice, that seems not to be much
of a problem.
I think we'll talk a bit more about that later today.
Today I wanted to talk about a couple
other really interesting and important topics
when we're training neural networks.
In particular, I wanted to talk,
we've kind of alluded to this fact
of fancier, more powerful optimization algorithms
a couple times.
I wanted to spend some time today and really
dig into those and talk about what are the
actual optimization algorithms that most people
are using these days.
We also touched on regularization
in earlier lectures.
This concept of making your network
do additional things to reduce the gap
between train and test error.
I wanted to talk about some more strategies
that people are using in practice
of regularization, with respect to neural networks.
Finally, I also wanted to talk a bit
about transfer learning, where you can
sometimes get away with using less data
than you think by transferring from
one problem to another.
If you recall from a few lectures ago,
the kind of core strategy in training
neural networks is an optimization problem
where we write down some loss function,
which defines, for each value of the network weights,
the loss function tells us how good or bad
is that value of the weights doing on our problem.
Then we imagine that this loss function
gives us some nice landscape over the weights,
where on the right, I've shown this maybe
small, two-dimensional problem, where the X
and Y axes are two values of the weights.
Then the color of the plot kind of represents
the value of the loss.
In this kind of cartoon picture
of a two-dimensional problem, we're only
optimizing over these two values, W one, W two.
The goal is to find the most red region
in this case, which corresponds to the setting
of the weights with the lowest loss.
Remember, we've been working so far
with this extremely simple optimization algorithm,
stochastic gradient descent,
where it's super simple, it's three lines.
While true, we first evaluate the loss
in the gradient on some mini batch of data.
Then we step, updating our parameter vector
in the negative direction of the gradient
because this gives, again, the direction
of greatest decrease of the loss function.
Then we repeat this over and over again,
and hopefully we converge to the red region
and we get great errors and we're very happy.
But unfortunately, this relatively simple
optimization algorithm has quite a lot of problems
that actually could come up in practice.
One problem with stochastic gradient descent,
imagine what happens if our objective function
looks something like this, where, again,
we're plotting two values, W one and W two.
As we change one of those values,
the loss function changes very slowly.
As we change the horizontal value, then our loss
changes slowly.
As we go up and down in this landscape,
now our loss is very sensitive to changes
in the vertical direction.
By the way, this is referred to as the loss
having a bad condition number at this point,
which is the ratio between the largest and smallest
singular values of the Hessian matrix
at that point.
But the intuitive idea is that the loss landscape
kind of looks like a taco shell.
It's sort of very sensitive in one direction,
not sensitive in the other direction.
The question is what might SGD,
stochastic gradient descent, do on a function
that looks like this?
If you run stochastic gradient descent
on this type of function, you might get
this characteristic zigzagging behavior,
where because for this type of objective function,
the direction of the gradient does not align
with the direction towards the minima.
When you compute the gradient and take a step,
you might step sort of over this line
and sort of zigzag back and forth.
In effect, you get very slow progress along
the horizontal dimension, which is the
less sensitive dimension, and you get this
zigzagging, nasty, nasty zigzagging behavior
across the fast-changing dimension.
This is undesirable behavior.
By the way, this problem actually becomes
much more common in high dimensions.
In this kind of cartoon picture, we're only
showing a two-dimensional optimization landscape,
but in practice, our neural networks might have
millions, tens of millions, hundreds of millions
of parameters.
That's hundreds of millions of directions
along which this thing can move.
Now among those hundreds of millions
of different directions to move,
if the ratio between the largest one
and the smallest one is bad, then SGD
will not perform so nicely.
You can imagine that if we have 100 million parameters,
probably the maximum ratio between those two
will be quite large.
I think this is actually quite a big problem
in practice for many high-dimensional problems.
Another problem with SGD has to do with this idea
of local minima or saddle points.
Here I've sort of swapped the graph a little bit.
Now the X axis is showing the value
of one parameter, and then the Y axis
is showing the value of the loss.
In this top example, we have kind of this
curvy objective function, where there's a
valley in the middle.
What happens to SGD in this situation?
- [Student] [speaks too low to hear]
- In this situation, SGD will get stuck
because at this local minima, the gradient
is zero because it's locally flat.
Now remember with SGD, we compute the gradient
and step in the direction of opposite gradient,
so if at our current point, the opposite gradient
is zero, then we're not going to make any progress,
and we'll get stuck at this point.
There's another problem with this idea
of saddle points.
Rather than being a local minima,
you can imagine a point where in one direction
we go up, and in the other direction we go down.
Then at our current point, the gradient is zero.
Again, in this situation, the function
will get stuck at the saddle point because
the gradient is zero.
Although one thing I'd like to point out
is that in one dimension, in a one-dimensional problem
like this, local minima seem like a big problem
and saddle points seem like kind of not
something to worry about, but in fact,
it's the opposite once you move to very
high-dimensional problems because, again,
if you think about you're in this
100 million dimensional space,
what does a saddle point mean?
That means that at my current point,
some directions the loss goes up,
and some directions the loss goes down.
If you have 100 million dimensions,
that's probably going to happen more frequently than,
that's probably going to happen almost everywhere, basically.
Whereas a local minima says that of all those
100 million directions that I can move,
every one of them causes the loss to go up.
In fact, that seems pretty rare when
you're thinking about, again, these very
high-dimensional problems.
Really, the idea that has come to light
in the last few years is that when
you're training these very large neural networks,
the problem is more about saddle points
and less about local minima.
By the way, this also is a problem
not just exactly at the saddle point,
but also near the saddle point.
If you look at the example on the bottom,
you see that in the regions around
the saddle point, the gradient isn't zero,
but the slope is very small.
That means that if we're, again, just stepping
in the direction of the gradient,
and that gradient is very small, we're going to make
very, very slow progress whenever our
current parameter value is near a saddle point
in the objective landscape.
This is actually a big problem.
Another problem with SGD comes from the S.
Remember that SGD is stochastic gradient descent.
Recall that our loss function is typically
defined by computing the loss over many,
many different examples.
In this case, if N is your whole training set,
then that could be something like a million.
Each time computing the loss would be very,
very expensive.
In practice, remember that we often estimate
the loss and estimate the gradient
using a small mini batch of examples.
What this means is that we're not actually
getting the true information about the gradient
at every time step.
Instead, we're just getting some noisy estimate
of the gradient at our current point.
Here on the right, I've kind of faked
this plot a little bit.
I've just added random uniform noise
to the gradient at every point, and then
run SGD with these noisy, messed up gradients.
This is maybe not exactly what happens
with the SGD process, but it still give you
the sense that if there's noise in your
gradient estimates, then vanilla SGD
kind of meanders around the space
and might actually take a long time
to get towards the minima.
Now that we've talked about a lot
of these problems.
Sorry, was there a question?
- [Student] [speaks too low to hear]
- The question is do all of these
just go away if we use normal gradient descent?
Let's see.
I think that the taco shell problem
of high condition numbers is still a problem
with full batch gradient descent.
The noise.
As we'll see, we might sometimes introduce
additional noise into the network,
not only due to sampling mini batches,
but also due to explicit stochasticity in the network,
so we'll see that later.
That can still be a problem.
Saddle points, that's still a problem
for full batch gradient descent because
there can still be saddle points
in the full objective landscape.
Basically, even if we go to full batch
gradient descent, it doesn't really solve
these problems.
We kind of need to think about a slightly fancier
optimization algorithm that can try
to address these concerns.
Thankfully, there's a really, really simple strategy
that works pretty well at addressing
many of these problems.
That's this idea of adding a momentum term
to our stochastic gradient descent.
Here on the left, we have our classic
old friend, SGD, where we just always step
in the direction of the gradient.
But now on the right, we have this minor,
minor variance called SGD plus momentum,
which is now two equations and five lines of code,
so it's twice as complicated.
But it's very simple.
The idea is that we maintain a velocity
over time, and we add our gradient estimates
to the velocity.
Then we step in the direction of the velocity,
rather than stepping in the direction of the gradient.
This is very, very simple.
We also have this hyperparameter rho now
which corresponds to friction.
Now at every time step, we take our
current velocity, we decay the current velocity
by the friction constant, rho, which is often
something high, like .9 is a common choice.
We take our current velocity, we decay it
by friction and we add in our gradient.
Now we step in the direction of our velocity vector,
rather than the direction of our
raw gradient vector.
This super, super simple strategy
actually helps for all of these problems
that we just talked about.
If you think about what happens at local minima
or saddle points, then if we're imagining
velocity in this system, then you kind of have
this physical interpretation of this ball
kind of rolling down the hill, picking up speed
as it comes down.
Now once we have velocity, then even when we
pass that point of local minima,
the point will still have velocity,
even if it doesn't have gradient.
Then we can hopefully get over this local minima
and continue downward.
There's this similar intuition near saddle points,
where even though the gradient around
the saddle point is very small, we have
this velocity vector that we've built up
as we roll downhill.
That can hopefully carry us through
the saddle point and let us continue rolling
all the way down.
If you think about what happens in
poor conditioning, now if we were to have
these kind of zigzagging approximations
to the gradient, then those zigzags
will hopefully cancel each other out pretty fast
once we're using momentum.
This will effectively reduce the amount
by which we step in the sensitive direction,
whereas in the horizontal direction,
our velocity will just keep building up,
and will actually accelerate our descent
across that less sensitive dimension.
Adding momentum here can actually help us
with this high condition number problem, as well.
Finally, on the right, we've repeated
the same visualization of gradient descent with noise.
Here, the black is this vanilla SGD,
which is sort of zigzagging all over the place,
where the blue line is showing now SGD
with momentum.
You can see that because we're adding it,
we're building up this velocity over time,
the noise kind of gets averaged out
in our gradient estimates.
Now SGD ends up taking a much smoother path
towards the minima, compared with the SGD,
which is kind of meandering due to noise.
Question?
- [Student] [speaks too low to hear]
- The question is how does SGD momentum
help with the poorly conditioned coordinate?
The idea is that if you go back and look
at this velocity estimate and look
at the velocity computation, we're adding in
the gradient at every time step.
It kind of depends on your setting of rho,
that hyperparameter, but you can imagine
that if the gradient is relatively small,
and if rho is well behaved in this situation,
then our velocity could actually monotonically increase
up to a point where the velocity could now
be larger than the