- Okay let's get started.
Alright, so welcome to lecture 14,
and today we'll be talking about reinforcement learning.
So some administrative details first,
update on grades.
Midterm grades were released last night,
so see Piazza for more information
and statistics about that.
And we also have A2 and milestone grades
scheduled for later this week.
Also, about your projects, all teams
must register your projects.
So on Piazza we have a form posted,
so you should go there and this is required, every team
should go and fill out this form with information
about your project, that we'll use for final grading
and the poster session.
And the Tiny ImageNet evaluation servers are also now
online for those of you who are
doing the Tiny ImageNet challenge.
We also have a link to a course survey on Piazza
that was released a few days ago,
so, please fill it out if you guys haven't already.
We'd love to have your feedback and know how
we can improve this class.
Okay, so the topic of today, reinforcement learning.
Alright, so so far we've talked about supervised learning,
which is about a type of problem where we have data x
and then we have labels y and our goal is to learn
a function that is mapping from x to y.
So, for example, the classification problem
that we've been working with.
We also talked last lecture about unsupervised learning,
which is the problem where we have just data
and no labels, and our goal is to learn
some underlying, hidden structure of the data.
So, an example of this is the generative models
that we talked about last lecture.
And so today we're going to talk about a different
kind of problem set-up, the reinforcement learning problem.
And so here we have an agent
that can take actions in its environment,
and it can receive rewards for for its action.
And its goal is going to be to learn how to take actions
in a way that can maximize its reward.
And so we'll talk about this in a lot more detail today.
So, the outline for today, we're going to first
talk about the reinforcement learning problem,
and then we'll talk about Markov decision processes,
which is a formalism of the reinforcement learning problem,
and then we'll talk about two major classes
of RL algorithms, Q-learning and policy gradients.
So, in the reinforcement learning set up, what we have
is we have an agent and we have an environment.
And so the environment gives the agent a state.
In turn, the agent is going to take an action,
and then the environment is going to give back a reward,
as well as the next state.
And so this is going to keep going on in this loop,
on and on, until the environment
gives back a terminal state,
which then ends the episode.
So, let's see some examples of this.
First we have here the cart-pole problem,
which is a classic problem that some of you may have seen,
in, for example, 229 before.
And so this objective here is that you want to
balance a pole on top of a movable cart.
Alright, so the state that you have here is
your current description of the system.
So, for example, angular, angular speed
of your pole, your position, and the horizontal
velocity of your cart.
And the actions you can take are horizontal forces
that you apply onto the cart, right?
So you're basically trying to move this cart around
to try and balance this pole on top of it.
And the reward that you're getting
from this environment is one at each time step
if your pole is upright.
So you basically want to keep this pole
balanced for as long as you can.
Okay, so here's another example of a classic RL problem.
Here is robot locomotion.
So we have here an example of a humanoid robot,
as well as an ant robot model.
And our objective here is to make the robot move forward.
And so the state that we have
describing our system is the angle and the positions
of all the joints of our robots.
And then the actions that we can take are
the torques applied onto these joints,
right, and so these are
trying to make the robot
move forward and then the reward that we get is
our forward movement as well as, I think, in the time of,
in the case of the humanoid, also, you can have something
like a reward of one for each time step that this
robot is upright.
So, games are also
a big class of problems that can be formulated with RL.
So, for example, here we have Atari games
which are a classic success of deep reinforcement learning
and so here the objective is to complete these games
with the highest possible score, right.
So, your agent is basically a player
that's trying to play these games.
And the state that you have is going to be
the raw pixels of the game state.
Right, so these are just the
pixels on the screen that you would see
as you're playing the game.
And then the actions that you have
are your game controls, so for example,
in some games maybe moving left to right, up or down.
And then the score that you have is your score increase
or decrease at each time step, and your goal is going to be
to maximize your total score over the course of the game.
And, finally, here we have another example of a game here.
It's
Go, which is
something that was a
huge achievement of deep reinforcement learning last year,
when Deep Minds AlphaGo beats Lee Sedol,
which is one of the
best Go players of the last few years,
and this is actually in the news again
for, as some of you may have seen, there's another Go
competition going on now with
AlphaGo versus a top-ranked Go player.
And so the objective here is to
win the game, and our state is the position
of all the pieces, the action is where to put the next
piece down, and the reward is, one, if you win at the end
of the game, and zero otherwise.
And we'll also talk about this one
in a little bit more detail, later.
Okay, so
how can we mathematically formalize
the RL problem, right?
This loop that we talked about earlier,
of environments giving agents states,
and then agents taking actions.
So, a Markov decision process is
the mathematical formulation of the RL problem,
and an MDP satisfies the Markov property,
which is that the current state completely
characterizes the state of the world.
And an MDP here is defined by tuple of objects,
consisting of S, which is the set of possible states.
We have A, our set of possible actions,
we also have R, our distribution of our reward,
given a state, action pair,
so it's a function mapping from state action
to your reward.
You also have P, which is a transition probability
distribution over your next state, that you're
going to transition to given your state, action pair.
And then finally we have a Gamma, a discount factor,
which is basically saying how much we value
rewards coming up soon versus later on.
So, the way the Markov Decision Process works is that
at our initial time step t equals zero,
the environment is going to sample some
initial state as zero, from the initial state distribution,
p of s zero.
And then, once it has that, then from time t equals zero
until it's done, we're going to iterate through this loop
where the agent is going to select an action, a sub t.
The environment is going to sample a reward from here,
so reward given your state and the
action that you just took.
It's also going to sample the next state,
at time t plus one, given your probability distribution
and then the agent is going to receive
the reward, as well as the next state, and then we're
going to through this process again,
and keep looping; agent will select the next action,
and so on until the episode is over.
Okay, so
now based on this, we can define a policy pi,
which is a function from your states to your actions
that specifies what action to take in each state.
And this can be either deterministic or stochastic.
And our objective now is to going to be to find
your optimal policy pi star, that maximizes your
cumulative discounted reward.
So we can see here we have our
some of our future rewards, which can be also
discounted by your discount factor.
So, let's look at an example of a simple MDP.
And here we have Grid World, which is this
task where we have this grid of states.
So you can be in any of these
cells of your grid, which are your states.
And you can take actions from your states,
and so these actions are going to be
simple movements, moving to your right,
to your left, up or down.
And you're going to get a negative reward for each
transition or each time step, basically, that happens.
Each movement that you take,
and this can be something like R equals negative one.
And so your objective is going to be
to reach one of the terminal states,
which are the gray states shown here,
in the least number of actions.
Right, so the longer that you take to reach
your terminal state, you're going to keep
accumulating these negative rewards.
Okay, so if you look at a random policy here,
a random policy would consist of, basically,
at any given state or cell that you're in
just sampling randomly which direction
that you're going to move in next.
Right, so all of these have equal probability.
On the other hand, an optimal policy that
we would like to have is
basically taking the action, the direction
that will move us closest to a terminal state.
So you can see here,
if we're right next to one of the
terminal states we should
always move in the direction
that gets us to this terminal state.
And otherwise, if you're in one of these other states,
you want to take the direction that will take you
closest to one of these states.
Okay, so now given this
description of our MDP, what we want to do
is we want to find our optimal policy pi star.
Right, our policy that's maximizing the sum of the rewards.
And so this optimal policy is going to tell us,
given any state that we're in, what is the action that
we should take in order to maximize the sum
of the rewards that we'll get.
And so one question is how do we
handle the randomness in the MDP, right?
We have randomness in
terms of our initial state that we're sampling,
in therms of this transition probability
distribution that will give us
distribution of our next states, and so on.
Also what we'll do is we'll work, then, with maximizing
our expected sum of the rewards.
So, formally, we can write our optimal policy pi star
as maximizing this expected sum of future rewards
over policy's pi, where we have our initial state
sampled from our state distribution.
We have our actions,
sampled from our policy, given the state.
And then we have our next states sampled
from our transition probability distributions.
Okay, so
before we talk about
exactly how we're going to find this policy,
let's first talk about a few definitions
that's going to be helpful for us in doing so.
So, specifically, the value function
and the Q-value function.
So, as we follow the policy,
we're going to sample trajectories
or paths, right, for every episode.
And we're going to have our initial state as zero,
a-zero, r-zero, s-one, a-one, r-one, and so on.
We're going to have this trajectory
of states, actions, and rewards that we get.
And so, how good is a state that we're currently in?
Well, the value function at any state s,
is the expected cumulative reward
following the policy from state s, from here on out.
Right, so it's going to be expected value
of our expected cumulative reward,
starting from our current state.
And then how good is a state, action pair?
So how good is taking action a in state s?
And we define this using a Q-value function,
which is, the expected cumulative reward from taking
action a in state s and then following the policy.
Right, so then, the optimal Q-value function
that we can get is going to be Q star, which is the maximum
expected cumulative reward that we can get
from a given state action pair, defined here.
So now we're going to see one important thing
in reinforcement learning,
which is called the Bellman equation.
So let's consider this a Q-value function
from the optimal policy Q star,
which is then going to satisfy this Bellman equation,
which is this identity shown here,
and what this means is that
given any state, action pair, s and a,
the value of this pair is going to be the reward
that you're going to get, r, plus the value of whatever
state that you end up in.
So, let's say, s prime.
And since we know that we have the optimal policy,
then we also know that we're going to
play the best action that we can,
right, at our state s prime.
And so then, the value at state s prime
is just going to be the maximum over our actions,
a prime, of Q star at s prime, a prime.
And so then we get this
identity here, for optimal Q-value.
Right, and then also, as always, we have
this expectation here,
because we have randomness over what state
that we're going to end up in.
And then we can also infer, from here, that our
optimal policy, right, is going to consist
of taking the best action in any state,
as specified by Q star.
Q star is going to tell us
of the maximum
future reward that we can get from any of our actions,
so we should just
take a policy that's following this
and just taking the action that's
going to lead to best reward.
Okay, so how can we solve for this optimal policy?
So, one way we can solve for this is
something called a value iteration algorithm,
where we're going to use this Bellman equation
as an iterative update.
So at each step, we're going to refine our approximation
of Q star by trying to enforce the Bellman equation.
And so, under some mathematical conditions,
we also know that this sequence Q, i
of our Q-function is going to converge to our optimal
Q star as i approaches infinity.
And so this, this works well,
but what's the problem with this?
Well, an important problem is that this is not scalable.
Right?
We have to compute
Q of s, a here for every state, action pair
in order to make our iterative updates.
Right, but then this is a problem if,
for example, if we look at these
the state of, for example, an Atari game
that we had earlier, it's going to be
your screen of pixels.
And this is a huge state space, and it's basically
computationally infeasible
to compute this for the entire state space.
Okay, so what's the solution to this?
Well, we can use a function approximator
to estimate Q of s, a
so, for example, a neural network, right.
So, we've seen before that any time, if we have some
really complex function that don't know, that we want
to estimate, a neural network is
a good way to estimate this.
Okay, so this is going to take us to our
formulation of Q-learning that we're going to look at.
And so, what we're going to do is we're going
to use a function approximator
in order to estimate our action value function.
Right?
And if this function approximator
is a deep neural network, which is
what's been used recently,
then this is going to be called deep Q-learning.
And so this is something that
you'll hear around as one of the common approaches
to deep reinforcement learning that's in use.
Right, and so in this case,
we also have our function parameters
theta here, so our Q-value function
is determined by these weights,
theta, of our neural network.
Okay, so given this function approximation,
how do we solve for our optimal policy?
So remember that we want to find
a Q-function that's satisfying the Bellman equation.
Right, and so we want to enforce this Bellman equation
to happen, so what we can do when we have this
neural network approximating our Q-function is that
we can train this where our loss function
is going to try and minimize
the error of our Bellman equation, right?
Or how far q of s, a is from its target,
which is the Y_i here, the right hand side
of the Bellman equation that we saw earlier.
So, we're basically going to take these
forward passes of our
loss function, trying to minimize this error
and then our backward pass, our gradient update,
is just going to be
you just take the gradient of this
loss, with respect to our network parameter's theta.
Right, and so our goal is again to
have this effect as we're taking gradient steps
of iteratively trying to make our Q-function
closer to our target value.
So, any questions about this?
Okay.
So let's look at a case study of an example where
one of the classic examples of deep reinforcement learning
where this approach was applied.
And so we're going to look at this problem that we saw earlier
of playing Atari games, where our objective was
to complete the game with the highest score
and remember our state is going to be the raw pixel
inputs of the game state,
and we can take these actions
of moving left, right, up, down,
or whatever actions of the particular game.
And our reward at each time step, we're going to get
a reward of our score increase or decrease that we
got at this time step, and so our cumulative total
reward is this total reward that we'll usually see
at the top of the screen.
Okay, so the network that we're going to use for our
Q-function is going to look something like this,
right, where we have our Q-network, with weight's theta.
And then our input, our state s, is going to be
our current game screen.
And in practice we're going to take
a stack of the last four frames, so we have some history.
And so we'll take these raw pixel values,
we'll do some, you know, RGB to gray-scale conversions,
some down-sampling, some cropping,
so, some pre-processing.
And what we'll get out of this is this 84 by 84 by four
stack of the last four frames.
Yeah, question.
[inaudible question from audience]
Okay, so the question is, are we saying here
that our network is going to approximate our
Q-value function for different state, action pairs,
for example, four of these?
Yeah, that's correct.
We'll see,
we'll talk about that in a few slides.
[inaudible question from audience]
So, no.
So, we don't have a Softmax layer after the connected,
because here our goal is to directly predict
our Q-value functions.
[inaudible question from audience]
Q-values.
Yes, so it's more doing regression to our Q-values.
Okay, so we have our input to this network
and then on top of this, we're going to have
a couple of familiar convolutional layers,
and a fully-connected layer,
so here we have
an eight-by-eight convolutions and we have some
four-by-four convolutions.
Then we have a FC 256 layer,
so this is just a standard kind of networK
that you've seen before.
And then, finally, our last fully-connected layer has
a vector of outputs, which is corresponding to your
Q-value for each action, right, given
the state that you've input.
And so, for example, if you have four actions,
then here we have this four-dimensional output
corresponding to Q of current s, as well as a-one,
and then a-two, a-three, and a-four.
Right so this is going to be one scalar value
for each of our actions.
And then the number of actions that we have
can vary between,
for example, 4 to 18, depending on the Atari game.
And one nice thing here is that
using this network structure,
a single feedforward pass is able to compute
the Q-values for all functions
from the current state.
And so this is really efficient.
Right, so basically we take our current state
in and then because we have this output of an action
for each, or Q-value for each action, as our output layer,
we're able to do one pass and get all of these values out.
And then in order to train this,
we're just going to use our loss function from before.
Remember, we're trying to enforce this Bellman equation
and so, on our forward pass, our loss function
we're going to try and iteratively make our Q-value
close to our target value,
that it should have.
And then our backward pass is just
directly taking the gradient of this
loss function that we have and then taking
a gradient step based on that.
So one other thing that's used here that I want to mention
is something called experience replay.
And so this addresses a problem with just using
the plain two network that I just described,
which is that learning from batches
of consecutive samples is bad.
And so the reason
because of this, right, is so for just
playing the game, taking samples
of state action rewards that we have
and just taking consecutive samples of these
and training with these,
well all of these samples are correlated
and so this leads to
inefficient learning, first of all,
and also, because of this, our current Q-network
parameters, right, this determines the policy
that we're going to follow, it determines our next
samples that we're going to get that
we're going to use for training.
And so this leads to problems where
you can have bad feedback loops.
So, for example, if currently the maximizing
action that's going to take left,
well this is going to bias all of my
upcoming training examples to be dominated
by samples from the left-hand side.
And so this is a problem, right?
And so the way that we are going to address these
problems is by using something called
experience replay, where we're going to keep this
replay memory table of transitions of state,
as state, action, reward, next state,
transitions that we have, and we're going
to continuously update this table with new transitions
that we're getting as game episodes are played,
as we're getting more experience.
Right, and so now what we can do
is that we can now train our Q-network on random,
mini-batches of transitions from the replay memory.
Right, so instead of using consecutive samples,
we're now going to sample across these
transitions that we've accumulated random samples of these,
and this breaks all of the,
these correlation problems that we had earlier.
And then also, as another
side benefit is that each of these transitions
can also contribute to potentially multiple weight updates.
We're just sampling from this table and so
we could sample one multiple times.
And so, this is going to lead
also to greater data efficiency.
Okay, so let's put this all together
and let's look at the full algorithm
for deep Q-learning with experience replay.
So we're going to start off with initializing our replay memory
to some capacity that we choose, N, and then we're also
going to initialize our
Q-network, just with our random weights
or initial weights.
And then we're going to play M episodes, or full games.
This is going to be our training episodes.
And then what we're going to do
is we're going to initialize our state,
using the starting game screen pixels
at the beginning of each episode.
And remember, we go through the pre-processing step
to get to our actual input state.
And then for each time step
of a game that we're currently playing,
we're going to, with a small probability,
select a random action,
so one thing that's important in these algorithms
is to have sufficient exploration,
so we want to make sure that
we are sampling different parts of the state space.
And then otherwise, we're going
to select from the greedy action
from the current policy.
Right, so most of the time we'll take the greedy action
that we think is
a good policy of the type of actions that we want to take
and states that we want to see, and with a small probability
we'll sample something random.
Okay, so then we'll take this action,
a, t, and we'll observe the next reward and the next state.
So r, t and s, t plus one.
And then we'll take this and we'll store this transition
in our replay memory that we're building up.
And then we're going to take,
we're going to train a network a little bit.
So we're going to do experience replay
and we'll take a sample of a random mini-batches
of transitions that we have
from the replay memory, and then we'll perform
a gradient descent step on this.
Right, so this is going to be our full training loop.
We're going to be continuously playing this game
and then also sampling
minibatches, using experienced replay to update
our weights of our Q-network and then
continuing in this fashion.
Okay, so let's see.
Let's see if I can,
is this playing?
Okay, so let's take a look
at this deep Q-learning algorithm
from Google DeepMind, trained on an Atari game of Breakout.
Alright, so it's saying here that our input
is just going to be our state are raw game pixels.
And so here we're looking at what's happening
at the beginning of training.
So we've just started training a bit.
And
right, so it's going to look to
it's learned to kind of hit the ball,
but it's not doing a very good job of sustaining it.
But it is looking for the ball.
Okay, so now after some more training,
it looks like a couple hours.
Okay, so now it's learning to do a pretty good job here.
So it's able to continuously follow
this ball and be able to
to remove most of the blocks.
Right, so after 240 minutes.
Okay, so here it's found the pro strategy, right?
You want to get all the way to the top and then
have it go by itself.
Okay, so
this is an example of using
deep Q-learning in order to
train an agent to be able to play Atari games.
It's able to do this on many Atari games
and so you can check out
some more of this online.
Okay, so we've talked about Q-learning.
But there is a problem with Q-learning, right?
It can be challenging and what's the problem?
Well, the problem can be that
the Q-function is very complicated.
Right, so we have to, we're saying that we want to learn
the value of every state action pair.
So, if, let's say you have something, for example,
a robot grasping, wanting to grasp an object.
Right, you're going to have a really high dimensional state.
You have, I mean, let's say you have all of your
even just joint, joint positions, and angles.
Right, and so learning the exact value of every state
action pair that you have, right,
can be really, really hard to do.
But on the other hand, your policy can be much simpler.
Right, like what you want this robot to do
maybe just to have this simple motion
of just closing your hand, right?
Just, move your fingers in this
particular direction and keep going.
And so, that leads to the question of
can we just learn this policy directly?
Right, is it possible, maybe, to just find the best
policy from a collection of policies,
without trying to go through this process
of estimating your Q-value
and then using that to infer your policy.
So, this is an approach that
oh,
so, okay, this is an approach that
we're going to call policy gradients.
And so, formally, let's define a
class of parametrized policies.
Parametrized by weights theta,
and so for each policy
let's define the value of the policy.
So, J, our value J, given parameters theta,
is going to be, or expected
some cumulative sum of future rewards that we care about.
So, the same reward that we've been using.
And so our goal then, under this setup
is that we want to find an optimal policy,
theta star, which is the maximum, right,
arg max over theta of J of theta.
So we want to find the policy, the policy parameters
that gives our best expected reward.
So, how can we do this?
Any ideas?
Okay, well, what we can do
is just a gradient assent on our policy parameters, right?
We've learned that given some objective that we have,
some parameters we can just use gradient asscent
and gradient assent in order
to continuously improve our parameters.
And so let's talk more specifically about how
we can do this, which we're going to call
here the reinforce algorithm.
So, mathematically, we can write
out our expected future reward
over trajectories, and so we're going to sample
these trajectories of experience, right,
like for example episodes of game play
that we talked about earlier.
S-zero, a-zero, r-zero, s-one,
a-one, r-one, and so on.
Using some policy pi of theta.
Right, and then so, for each trajectory
we can compute a reward for tha