- Hello, hi. So I want to get started.
Welcome to CS 231N Lecture 11.
We're going to talk about today detection segmentation and a whole bunch
of other really exciting topics around core computer vision tasks.
But as usual, a couple
administrative notes.
So last time you obviously took the midterm, we
didn't have lecture, hopefully that went okay
for all of you but so we're going to work on grading the midterm this week, but as a reminder
please don't make any public discussions about the midterm questions or answers or whatever
until at least tomorrow because there are still some people
taking makeup midterms today and throughout the rest of the week
so we just ask you that you refrain from
talking publicly about midterm questions.
Why don't you wait until Monday?
[laughing] Okay, great.
So we're also starting to work on midterm grading. We'll get
those back to you as soon as you can, as soon as we can.
We're also starting to work on grading assignment two so there's
a lot of grading being done this week. The TA's are pretty busy.
Also a reminder for you guys, hopefully you've been
working hard on your projects now that most of you
are done with the midterm so your project milestones will be due on
Tuesday so any sort of last minute changes that you had in your projects,
I know some people decided to switch projects after
the proposal, some teams reshuffled a little bit,
that's fine but your milestone should reflect the project that you're actually
doing for the rest of the quarter. So hopefully that's going out well.
I know there's been a lot of worry and stress
on Piazza, wondering about assignment three.
So we're working on that as hard as we can but that's actually
a bit of a new assignment, it's changing a bit from last year
so it will be out as soon as possible,
hopefully today or tomorrow.
Although we promise that whenever it comes out you'll have two
weeks to finish it so try not to stress out about that too much.
But I'm pretty excited, I think assignment
three will be really cool, has a lot of cool,
it'll cover a lot of really cool material.
So another thing, last time in lecture we
mentioned this thing called the Train Game
which is this really cool thing we've been working
on sort of as a side project a little bit.
So this is an interactive tool that you guys can
go on and use to explore a little bit the process
of tuning hyperparameters
in practice so we hope that,
so this is again totally not required for the course.
Totally optional, but if you do we will offer
a small amount of extra
credit for those of you
who want to do well and
participate on this.
And we'll send out exactly some more
details later this afternoon on Piazza.
But just a bit of a demo for what exactly is this thing.
So you'll get to go in and we've changed the name
from Train Game to HyperQuest
because you're questing
to solve, to find the best
hyperparameters for your model
so this is really cool, it'll be an interactive tool that
you can use to explore the training of hyperparameters
interactively in your browser.
So you'll login with
your student ID and name.
You'll fill out a little survey with some
of your experience on deep learning
then you'll read some instructions. So in this
game you'll be shown some random data set
on every trial.
This data set might be images or it might be vectors
and your goal is to train a model by picking
the right hyperparameters interactively to
perform as well as you can on the validation set
of this random data set.
And it'll sort of keep track of your performance
over time and there'll be a leaderboard,
it'll be really cool.
So every time you play the game, you'll
get some statistics about your data set.
In this case we're doing a
classification problem with 10 classes.
You can see down at the bottom you have these
statistics about random data set, we have 10 classes.
The input data size is three by 32 by 32 so
this is some image data set and we can see
that in this case we have 8500 examples in the
training set and 1500 examples in the validation set.
These are all random, they'll change
a little bit every time.
Based on these data set statistics you'll make some choices
on your initial learning rate, your initial network size,
and your initial dropout rate.
Then you'll see a screen like this where it'll
run one epoch with those chosen hyperparameters,
show you on the right here you'll see two
plots. One is your training and validation loss
for that first epoch.
Then you'll see your training
and validation accuracy
for that first epoch and based on the gaps that you see in these two graphs you
can make choices interactively to change the learning rates and hyperparameters
for the next epoch.
So then you can either choose to continue training
with the current or changed hyperparameters,
you can also stop training, or you can
revert to go back to the previous checkpoint
in case things got really messed up.
So then you'll get to make some choice,
so here we'll decide to continue training
and in this case you could
go and set new learning rates
and new hyperparameters for
the next epoch of training.
You can also, kind of interesting here, you
can actually grow the network interactively
during training in this demo.
There's this cool trick from a couple recent
papers where you can either take existing layers
and make them wider or add new layers to the network
in the middle of training while still maintaining
the same function in the
network so you can do that
to increase the size of your network in the
middle of training here which is kind of cool.
So then you'll make choices over several epochs
and eventually your final validation accuracy
will be recorded and we'll
have some leaderboard
that compares your score on that data set
to some simple baseline models.
And depending on how well you do on this leaderboard
we'll again offer some small amounts of extra credit
for those of you who
choose to participate.
So this is again, totally
optional, but I think
it can be a really cool learning experience for you guys
to play around with and explore how hyperparameters
affect the learning process.
Also, it's really useful for us. You'll help
science out by participating in this experiment.
We're pretty interested in seeing how people behave when
they train neural networks so you'll be helping us out
as well if you decide to play this.
But again, totally optional, up to you.
Any questions on that?
Hopefully at some point but it's.
So the question was will this be a paper
or whatever eventually?
Hopefully but it's really early stages of this
project so I can't make any promises but I hope so.
But I think it'll be really cool.
[laughing]
Yeah, so the question is how can
you add layers during training?
I don't really want to get into that right now but
the paper to read is Net2Net by Ian Goodfellow's
one of the authors and
there's another paper
from Microsoft called Network Morphism.
So if you read those two papers
you can see how this works.
Okay, so last time, a bit of a reminder
before we had the midterm last time we talked
about recurrent neural networks.
We saw that recurrent neural networks can
be used for different types of problems.
In addition to one to one we can do one
to many, many to one, many to many.
We saw how this can apply
to language modeling
and we saw some cool examples of applying neural networks to
model different sorts of languages at the character level
and we sampled these artificial math
and Shakespeare and C source code.
We also saw how similar things could be applied to
image captioning by connecting a CNN feature extractor
together with an RNN language model.
And we saw some really
cool examples of that.
We also talked about the different types of
RNN's. We talked about this Vanilla RNN.
I also want to mention that this is sometimes
called a Simple RNN or an Elman RNN so you'll see
all of these different
terms in literature.
We also talked about the Long
Short Term Memory or LSTM.
And we talked about how the gradient,
the LSTM has this crazy set of equations
but it makes sense because it
helps improve gradient flow
during back propagation
and helps this thing model
more longer term dependencies
in our sequences.
So today we're going to switch gears and talk
about a whole bunch of different exciting tasks.
We're going to talk about, so so far we've been talking
about mostly the image classification problem.
Today we're going to talk about various types of other
computer vision tasks where you actually want to go in
and say things about the spatial pixels inside your images
so we'll see segmentation, localization, detection,
a couple other different
computer vision tasks
and how you can approach these
with convolutional neural networks.
So as a bit of refresher, so far the main
thing we've been talking about in this class
is image classification so
here we're going to have
some input image come in.
That input image will go through
some deep convolutional network,
that network will give us some feature vector of
maybe 4096 dimensions in the case of AlexNet RGB
and then from that final feature vector
we'll have some fully-connected,
some final fully-connected layer
that gives us 1000 numbers
for the different class scores
that we care about where 1000 is maybe the
number of classes in ImageNet in this example.
And then at the end of the day
what the network does is we input an image
and then we output a single category label
saying what is the content of
this entire image as a whole.
But this is maybe the most basic possible task
in computer vision and there's a whole bunch
of other interesting types of tasks
that we might want to
solve using deep learning.
So today we're going to talk about several of these
different tasks and step through each of these
and see how they all
work with deep learning.
So we'll talk about these more in detail
about what each problem is as we get to it
but this is kind of a summary slide
that we'll talk first about
semantic segmentation.
We'll talk about classification and localization,
then we'll talk about object detection,
and finally a couple brief words
about instance segmentation.
So first is the problem
of semantic segmentation.
In the problem of semantic segmentation, we want
to input an image and then output a decision
of a category for every
pixel in that image
so for every pixel in this, so this input image for example
is this cat walking through the field, he's very cute.
And in the output we want to say for every pixel
is that pixel a cat or grass or sky or trees
or background or some
other set of categories.
So we're going to have some set of categories
just like we did in the image classification case
but now rather than assigning a single category
labeled to the entire image, we want to produce
a category label for each
pixel of the input image.
And this is called semantic segmentation.
So one interesting thing about semantic segmentation
is that it does not differentiate instances
so in this example on the right we have this image
with two cows where they're standing right next
to each other and when we're talking about semantic
segmentation we're just labeling all the pixels
independently for what is
the category of that pixel.
So in the case like this where we have two cows
right next to each other the output does not make
any distinguishing, does not distinguish
between these two cows.
Instead we just get a whole mass of pixels
that are all labeled as cow.
So this is a bit of a shortcoming of semantic
segmentation and we'll see how we can fix this later
when we move to instance segmentation.
But at least for now we'll just talk about
semantic segmentation first.
So you can imagine maybe using a class,
so one potential approach for attacking
semantic segmentation might
be through classification.
So there's this, you could use this idea of a
sliding window approach to semantic segmentation.
So you might imagine that we take our input image and
we break it up into many many small, tiny local crops
of the image so in this
example we've taken
maybe three crops from
around the head of this cow
and then you could imagine taking each of those crops
and now treating this as a classification problem.
Saying for this crop, what is the category
of the central pixel of the crop?
And then we could use all the same machinery that
we've developed for classifying entire images
but now just apply it on crops rather than
on the entire image.
And this would probably work to some extent
but it's probably not a very good idea.
So this would end up being super super
computationally expensive because we want to label
every pixel in the image, we would need a separate
crop for every pixel in that image and this would be
super super expensive to
run forward and backward
passes through.
And moreover, we're actually, if you think about this
we can actually share computation between different
patches so if you're trying
to classify two patches
that are right next to each
other and actually overlap
then the convolutional
features of those patches
will end up going through the same convolutional layers
and we can actually share a lot of the computation
when applying this to separate passes
or when applying this type of approach
to separate patches in the image.
So this is actually a terrible idea and nobody
does this and you should probably not do this
but it's at least the first thing you might think of if
you were trying to think about semantic segmentation.
Then the next idea that works a bit better is
this idea of a fully convolutional network right.
So rather than extracting individual patches from the
image and classifying these patches independently,
we can imagine just having our network be a whole giant
stack of convolutional layers with no fully connected
layers or anything so in this
case we just have a bunch
of convolutional layers that are all maybe three
by three with zero padding or something like that
so that each convolutional
layer preserves the spatial size
of the input and now if we pass our image
through a whole stack of
these convolutional layers,
then the final convolutional layer could just
output a tensor of something by C by H by W
where C is the number of
categories that we care about
and you could see this tensor as just giving
our classification scores for every pixel
in the input image at every
location in the input image.
And we could compute this all at once with
just some giant stack of convolutional layers.
And then you could imagine training this thing
by putting a classification loss at every pixel
of this output, taking an
average over those pixels
in space, and just training this kind of network
through normal, regular back propagation.
Question?
Oh, the question is how do you develop
training data for this?
It's very expensive right.
So the training data for this would be
we need to label every
pixel in those input images
so there's tools that people sometimes have online
where you can go in and sort of draw contours
around the objects and
then fill in regions
but in general getting this kind of
training data is very expensive.
Yeah, the question is
what is the loss function?
So here since we're making a classification
decision per pixel then we put a cross entropy loss
on every pixel of the output.
So we have the ground truth category label
for every pixel in the output,
then we compute across entropy loss
between every pixel in the output
and the ground truth pixels and then
take either a sum or an average over space
and then sum or average over the mini-batch.
Question?
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, the question is do we assume
that we know the categories?
So yes, we do assume that we
know the categories up front
so this is just like the
image classification case.
So an image classification we know at the start of
training based on our data set that maybe there's 10 or 20
or 100 or 1000 classes that we care about
for this data set and then here we are fixed to that
set of classes that are fixed for the data set.
So this model is relatively simple and you
can imagine this working reasonably well
assuming that you tuned all
the hyperparameters right
but it's kind of a problem right.
So in this setup, since we're applying a bunch
of convolutions that are all keeping the same
spatial size of the input image,
this would be super super expensive right.
If you wanted to do convolutions that maybe have 64 or
128 or 256 channels for those convolutional filters
which is pretty common in
a lot of these networks,
then running those convolutions on this high resolution
input image over a sequence of layers would be
extremely computationally expensive
and would take a ton of memory.
So in practice, you don't usually see
networks with this architecture.
Instead you tend to see networks that look something
like this where we have some downsampling
and then some upsampling
of the feature map
inside the image.
So rather than doing all the convolutions of
the full spatial resolution of the image,
we'll maybe go through a small number of
convolutional layers at the original resolution
then downsample that feature map using something
like max pooling or strided convolutions
and sort of downsample, downsample,
so we have convolutions in downsampling
and convolutions in downsampling
that look much like a lot of the classification
networks that you see but now the difference is that
rather than transitioning to a fully connected layer
like you might do in an image classification setup,
instead we want to increase
the spatial resolution
of our predictions in the
second half of the network
so that our output image can now be the same
size as our input image and this ends up being
much more computationally efficient
because you can make the network very deep
and work at a lower spatial resolution
for many of the layers at
the inside of the network.
So we've already seen examples of downsampling
when it comes to convolutional networks.
We've seen that you can do strided convolutions or
various types of pooling to reduce the spatial size
of the image inside a
network but we haven't
really talked about
upsampling and the question
you might be wondering is what are these upsampling
layers actually look like inside the network?
And what are our strategies for increasing the
size of a feature map inside the network?
Sorry, was there a question in the back?
Yeah, so the question
is how do we upsample?
And the answer is that's the topic
of the next couple slides.
[laughing]
So one strategy for upsampling is something like
unpooling so we have this notion of pooling
to downsample so we talked
about average pooling
or max pooling so when we
talked about average pooling
we're kind of taking a spatial average within
a receptive field of each pooling region.
One kind of analog for upsampling is
this idea of nearest neighbor unpooling.
So here on the left we see this example of
nearest neighbor unpooling where our input
is maybe some two by
two grid and our output
is a four by four grid
and now in our output
we've done a two by two stride two nearest neighbor
unpooling or upsampling where we've just duplicated
that element for every
point in our two by two
receptive field of the unpooling region.
Another thing you might see is this bed of nails unpooling
or bed of nails upsampling where you'll just take,
again we have a two by two receptive field for
our unpooling regions and then you'll take the,
in this case you make it all zeros except for one element of the unpooling region so in this case we've taken all of
our inputs and always put them in the upper left hand corner of this unpooling region and everything else is zeros.
And this is kind of like a bed of nails
because the zeros are very flat, then you've got these things
poking up for the values at these various non-zero regions.
Another thing that you see sometimes which was alluded to
by the question a minute ago is this idea of max unpooling
so in a lot of these networks they tend to be symmetrical where we have a downsampling portion of the network
and then an upsampling portion of the network with a symmetry between those two portions of the network.
So sometimes what you'll see is this idea of max unpooling where for each unpooling, for each upsampling layer,
it is associated with one of the pooling layers in the first half of the network and now in the first half,
in the downsampling when we do max pooling we'll actually remember which element
of the receptive field during max pooling was used to do the max pooling
and now when we go through the rest of the network then we'll do something that looks like this bed of nails
upsampling except rather than always putting the elements in the same position, instead we'll stick it
into the position that was used in the corresponding
max pooling step earlier in the network.
I'm not sure if that explanation was clear
but hopefully the picture makes sense.
Yeah, so then you just end up
filling the rest with zeros.
So then you fill the rest with zeros and then you stick the elements
from the low resolution patch up into the high resolution patch
at the points where the max pooling took place
at the corresponding max pooling there.
Okay, so that's kind
of an interesting idea.
Sorry, question?
Oh yeah, so the question is why is this
a good idea? Why might this matter?
So the idea is that when we're doing semantic segmentation
we want our predictions to be pixel perfect right.
We kind of want to get those sharp boundaries and
those tiny details in our predictive segmentation
so now if you're doing this max pooling, there's this sort of heterogeneity
that's happening inside the feature map due to the max pooling
where from the low resolution image you don't know, you're sort of losing spatial information in some sense
by you don't know where that feature vector came from in the local receptive field after max pooling.
So if you actually unpool by putting the vector in the same slot you might
think that that might help us handle these fine details a little bit better
and help us preserve some of that spatial
information that was lost during max pooling.
Question?
The question is does this make
things easier for back prop?
Yeah, I guess, I don't think it changes the back prop dynamics too much
because storing these indices is not a huge computational overhead.
They're pretty small in
comparison to everything else.
So another thing that you'll see sometimes
is this idea of transpose convolution.
So transpose convolution, so for these various
types of unpooling that we just talked about,
these bed of nails, this nearest neighbor,
this max unpooling, all of these are kind of
a fixed function, they're not really learning exactly how
to do the upsampling so if you think about something
like strided convolution,
strided convolution
is kind of like a learnable layer that learns the way that
the network wants to perform downsampling at that layer.
And by analogy with that there's this type of layer called a
transpose convolution that lets us do kind of learnable upsampling.
So it will both upsample the feature map and learn
some weights about how it wants to do that upsampling.
And this is really just another type of convolution
so to see how this works remember how a normal
three by three stride one pad
one convolution would work.
That for this kind of normal convolution that
we've seen many times now in this class,
our input might by four by four,
our output might be four by four,
and now we'll have this three by three kernel and we'll take an inner
product between, we'll plop down that kernel at the corner of the image,
take an inner product, and that inner product will give us the value
and the activation in the upper left hand corner of our output.
And we'll repeat this for every
receptive field in the image.
Now if we talk about strided convolution then
strided convolution ends up looking pretty similar.
However, our input is maybe a four by four
region and our output is a two by two region.
But we still have this idea of taking, of there being some three by three filter or kernel that we plop down in
the corner of the image, take an inner product and use that to compute a value of the activation and the output.
But now with strided convolution the idea is that we're moving that,
rather than popping down that filter at every possible point in the input,
instead we're going to move the filter by two pixels in the input every time we
move the filter by one pixel, every time we move by one pixel in the output.
Right so this stride of two gives us a ratio between how much do
we move in the input versus how much do we move in the output.
So when you do a strided convolution with stride two this ends up downsampling
the image or the feature map by a factor of two in kind of a learnable way.
And now a transpose convolution is sort of the opposite in a way so here our
input will be a two by two region and our output will be a four by four region.
But now the operation that we perform with
transpose convolution is a little bit different.
Now so rather than taking an inner product instead what we're going
to do is we're going to take the value of our input feature map
at that upper left hand corner and that'll be
some scalar value in the upper left hand corner.
We're going to multiply the filter by that scalar value
and then copy those values over to this three by three
region in the output so rather than taking an inner
product with our filter and the input, instead our input
gives weights that we will use to weight the filter and then our output will
be weighted copies of the filter that are weighted by the values in the input.
And now we can do this sort of same ratio trick in order to upsample so now when we move one pixel
in the input now we can plop our filter down two pixels away in the output and it's the same trick
that now the blue pixel in the input is some scalar value and we'll
take that scalar value, multiply it by the values in the filter,
and copy those weighted filter values
into this new region in the output.
The tricky part is that sometimes these receptive
fields in the output can overlap now and now when these
receptive fields in the output overlap
we just sum the results in the output.
So then you can imagine repeating this everywhere and repeating this
process everywhere and this ends up doing sort of a learnable upsampling
where we use these learned convolutional filter weights
to upsample the image and increase the spatial size.
By the way, you'll see this operation go
by a lot of different names in literature.
Sometimes this gets called
things like deconvolution
which I think is kind of a
bad name but you'll see it
out there in papers so from a signal processing perspective
deconvolution means the inverse operation to convolution
which this is not however you'll frequently see
this type of layer called a deconvolution layer
in some deep learning papers so be aware
of that, watch out for that terminology.
You'll also sometimes see this called
upconvolution which is kind of a cute name.
Sometimes it gets called
fractionally strided convolution
because if we think of the stride as the ratio in step between the input and the output
then now this is something like a stride one half convolution because of this ratio
of one to two between steps in the input
and steps in the output.
This also sometimes gets called a backwards
strided convolution because if you think about it
and work through the math this ends up being the
same, the forward pass of a transpose convolution
ends up being the same mathematical operation
as the backwards pass in a normal convolution
so you might have to take my word for it, that might not be super obvious when you first
look at this but that's kind of a neat fact so you'll sometimes see that name as well.
And as maybe a bit of a more concrete example of what this looks like I
think it's maybe a little easier to see in one dimension so if we imagine,
so here we're doing a three by three
transpose convolution in one dimension.
Sorry, not three by three, a three by one
So our filter here is just three numbers. Our
input is two numbers and now you can see
that in our output we've taken the values in the input, used them to weight the
values of the filter and plopped down those weighted filters in the output
with a stride of two and now where these receptive
fields overlap in the output then we sum.
So you might be wondering, this is kind of a funny name. Where does the name transpose
convolution come from and why is that actually my preferred name for this operation?
So that comes from this kind of
neat interpretation of convolution.
So it turns out that any time you do convolution you can
always write convolution as a matrix multiplication.
So again, this is kind of easier to see
with a one-dimensional example
but here we've got some weight. So we're doing a one-dimensional
convolution of a weight vector x which has three elements,
and an input vector, a vector, which
has four elements, A, B, C, D.
So here we're doing a three by one convolution with stride one and you can
see that we can frame this whole operation as a matrix multiplication
where we take our convolutional kernel x
and turn it into some matrix capital X
which contains copies of that convolutional
kernel that are offset by different regions.
And now we can take this giant weight matrix X and do a matrix vector multiplication
between x and our input a and this just produces the same result as convolution.
And now with transpose convolution means that we're going to take this same weight
matrix but now we're going to multiply by the transpose of that same weight matrix.
So here you can see the same example for this stride one convolution on the
left and the corresponding stride one transpose convolution on the right.
And if you work through the details you'll
see that when it comes to stride one,
a stride one transpose convolution also ends up being a
stride one normal convolution so there's a little bit
of details in the way that the border and the padding
are handled but it's fundamentally the same operation.
But now things look different
when you talk about a stride of two.
So again, here on the left we can take a stride two convolution and
write out this stride two convolution as a matrix multiplication.
And now the corresponding transpose convolution
is no longer a convolution so if you look
through this weight matrix and think about how
convolutions end up getting represented in this way
then now this transposed matrix for the stride two convolution is something
fundamentally different from the original normal convolution operation
so that's kind of the reasoning behind the name and that's why I
think that's kind of the nicest name to call this operation by.
Sorry, was there a question?
Sorry?
It's very possible there's a typo in the slide so please point
out on Piazza and I'll fix it but I hope the idea was clear.
Is there another question? Okay, thank you
[laughing]. Yeah, so, oh no lots of questions.
Yeah, so the issue is why
do we sum and not average?
So the reason we sum is due to this transpose convolution
formula zone so that's the reason why we sum
but you're right that you actually, this is kind of a problem that the magnitudes will
actually vary in the output depending on how many receptive fields were in the output.
So actually in practice this is something that people
started to point out very recently and somewhat
switched away from this stride, so using three by three stride two transpose convolution upsampling
can sometimes produce some checkerboard artifacts in the output exactly due to that problem.
So what I've seen in a couple more recent papers is maybe to use four by four stride two or two by two
stride two transpose convolution for upsampling and that helps alleviate that problem a little bit.
- Yeah, so the question is what is a stride half convolution
- and where does that terminology come from?
I think that was from my paper. So that was
actually, yes that was definitely this.
So at the time I was writing that paper I was kind
of into the name fractionally strided convolution
but after thinking about it a bit more I think
transpose convolution is probably the right name.
So then this idea of semantic segmentation
actually ends up being pretty natural.
You just have this giant convolutional network with
downsampling and upsampling inside the network
and now our downsampling will
be by strided convolution
or pooling, our upsampling will be by transpose
convolution or various types of unpooling or upsampling
and we can train this whole thing end to end with back
propagation using this cross entropy loss over every pixel.
So this is actually pretty cool that we can take a lot of the same machinery
that we already learned for image classification and now just apply it
very easily to extend to new types
of problems so that's super cool.
So the next task that I want to talk about is
this idea of classification plus localization.
So we've talked about
image classification a lot
where we want to just assign a category label to the input image but
sometimes you might want to know a little bit more about the image.
In addition to predicting what the category is, in this case the
cat, you might also want to know where is that object in the image?
So in addition to predicting the category label cat, you might also
want to draw a bounding box around the region of the cat in that image.
And classification plus localization, the
distinction here between this and object detection
is that in the localization scenario you assume ahead of time that you know there's
exactly one object in the image that you're looking for or maybe more than one
but you know ahead of time that we're going to make some classification decision about this image and
we're going to produce exactly one bounding box that's going to tell us where that object is located
in the image so we sometimes call that
task classification plus localization.
And again, we can reuse a lot of the same machinery that we've already
learned from image classification in order to tackle this problem.
So kind of a basic architecture for
this problem looks something like this.
So again, we have our input image, we feed our input image through some giant convolutional network, this is
Alex, this is AlexNet for example, which will give us some final vector summarizing the content of the image.
Then just like before we'll have some fully connected layer
that goes from that final vector to our class scores.
But now we'll also have another fully connected
layer that goes from that vector to four numbers.
Where the four numbers are something like the height, the
width, and the x and y positions of that bounding box.
And now our network will produce these two different
outputs, one is this set of class scores,
and the other are these four numbers giving the
coordinates of the bounding box in the input image.
And now during training time, when we train this network
we'll actually have two losses so in this scenario
we're sort of assuming a
fully supervised setting
so we assume that each of our training images is annotated with both a category
label and also a ground truth bounding box for that category in the image.
So now we have two loss functions.
We have our favorite softmax loss that we compute using the
ground truth category label and the predicted class scores,
and we also have some kind of loss that gives us some measure of dissimilarity between our
predicted coordinates for the bounding box and our actual coordinates for the bounding box.
So one very simple thing is to just take an L2 loss between those two and that's
kind of the simplest thing that you'll see in practice although sometimes
people play around with this and maybe use L1 or smooth L1 or they parametrize
the bounding box a little bit differently but the idea is always the same,
that you have some regression loss between your predicted bounding
box coordinates and the ground truth bounding box coordinates.
Question?
Sorry, go ahead.
So the question is, is this a good idea
to do all at the same time?
Like what happens if you misclassify, should
you even look at the box coordinates?
So sometimes people get fancy with it,
so in general it works okay.
It's not a big problem, you can actually train a
network to do both of these things at the same time
and it'll figure it out but sometimes things can get tricky
in terms of misclassification so sometimes what you'll see
for example is that rather than predicting a single box you might make predictions
like a separate prediction of the box for each category and then only apply loss
to the predicted box corresponding
to the ground truth category.
So people do get a little bit fancy with these
things that sometimes helps a bit in practice.
But at least this basic setup, it might not be perfect or it
might not be optimal but it will work and it will do something.
Was there a question in the back?
Yeah, so that's the question is do these losses have
different units, do they dominate the gradient?
So this is what we call a multi-task loss
so whenever we're taking derivatives we always want to take derivative of a scalar
with respect to our network parameters and use that derivative to take gradient steps.
But now we've got two scalars
that we want to both minimize
so what you tend to do in practice is have some additional hyperparameter that gives you some weighting between
these two losses so you'll take a weighted sum of these two different loss functions to give our final scalar loss.
And then you'll take your gradients with respect
to this weighted sum of the two losses.
And this ends up being really really tricky because this weighting parameter
is a hyperparameter that you need to set but it's kind of different
from some of the other hyperparameters
that we've seen so far in the past right
because this weighting hyperparameter actually
changes the value of the loss function
so one thing that you might often look at when you're trying to set hyperparameters is you might make
different hyperparameter choices and see what happens to the loss under different choices of hyperparameters.
But in this case because the loss actually, because the hyperparameter affects
the absolute value of the loss making those comparisons becomes kind of tricky.
So setting that hyperparameter
is somewhat difficult.
And in practice, you kind of need to take it on a case by case basis for
exactly the problem you're solving but my general strategy for this
is to have some other metric of performance that
you care about other than the actual loss value
which then you actually use that final performance metric to make your cross
validation choices rather than looking at the value of the loss to make those choices.
Question?
So the question is why do we do this all
at once? Why not do this separately?
Yeah, so the question is why don't we fix the big network and then
just only learn separate fully connected layers for these two tasks?
People do do that sometimes and in fact that's probably the first thing
you should try if you're faced with a situation like this but in general
whenever you're doing transfer learning you always get better performance if you fine tune
the whole system jointly because there's probably some mismatch between the features,
if you train on ImageNet and then you use that network for your data set you're going
to get better performance on your data set if you can also change the network.
But one trick you might see in practice sometimes is that you might freeze
that network then train those two things separately until convergence
and then after they converge then you go
back and jointly fine tune the whole system.
So that's a trick that sometimes people do
in practice in that situation.
And as I've kind of alluded to this big network is often a
pre-trained network that is taken from ImageNet for example.
So a bit of an aside, this idea of predicting
some fixed number of positions in the image
can be applied to a lot of different problems
beyond just classification plus localization.
One kind of cool example
is human pose estimation.
So here we want to take an input image
is a picture of a person.
We want to output the positions of the joints for that person and this
actually allows the network to predict what is the pose of the human.
Where are his arms, where are
his legs, stuff like that,
and generally most people have the same number of
joints. That's a bit of a simplifying assumption,
it might not always be true
but it works for the network.
So for example one
parameterization that you might see
in some data sets is
define a person's pose
by 14 joint positions.
Their feet and their knees and their hips
and something like that and
now when we train the network
then we're going to input
this image of a person
and now we're going to output
14 numbers in this case
giving the x and y coordinates
for each of those 14 joints.
And then you apply some
kind of regression loss
on each of those 14
different predicted points
and just train this network
with back propagation again.
Yeah, so you might see an L2
loss but people play around
with other regression losses here as well.
Question?
So the question is what do I mean
when I say regression loss?
So I mean something
other than cross entropy
or softmax right.
When I say regression loss I usually mean
like an L2 Euclidean loss or an L1 loss
or sometimes a smooth L1 loss.
But in general classification
versus regression
is whether your output is
categorical or continuous
so if you're expecting
a categorical output
like you ultimately want to
make a classification decision
over some fixed number of categories
then you'll think about
a cross entropy loss,
softmax loss or these
SVM margin type losses
that we talked about already in the class.
But if your expected output is
to be some continuous value,
in this case the position of these points,
then your output is
continuous so you tend to use
different types of losses
in those situations.
Typically an L2, L1, different
kinds of things there.
So sorry for not clarifying that earlier.
But the bigger point
here is that for any time
you know that you want
to make some fixed number
of outputs from your network,
if you know for example.
Maybe you knew that you wanted to,
you knew that you always
are going to have pictures
of a cat and a dog and
you want to predict both
the bounding box of the cat
and the bounding box of the dog
in that case you'd know
that you have a fixed number
of outputs for each input
so you might imagine
hooking up this type of regression
classification plus localization framework
for that problem as well.
So this idea of some fixed
number of regression outputs
can be applied to a lot
of different problems
including pose estimation.
So the next task that I want to
talk about is object detection
and this is a really meaty topic.
This is kind of a core
problem in computer vision
and you could probably
teach a whole seminar class
on just the history of object detection
and various techniques applied there.
So I'll be relatively
brief and try to go over
the main big ideas of object
detection plus deep learning
that have been used in
the last couple of years.
But the idea in object detection is that
we again start with some
fixed set of categories
that we care about, maybe cats
and dogs and fish or whatever
but some fixed set of categories
that we're interested in.
And now our task is that
given our input image,
every time one of those
categories appears in the image,
we want to draw a box around
it and we want to predict
the category of that
box so this is different
from classification plus localization
because there might be a
varying number of outputs
for every input image.
You don't know ahead of time
how many objects you expect
to find in each image so that's,
this ends up being a
pretty challenging problem.
So we've seen graphs, so
this is kind of interesting.
We've seen this graph
many times of the ImageNet
classification performance
as a function of years
and we saw that it just got
better and better every year
and there's been a similar
trend with object detection
because object detection
has again been one
of these core problems in computer vision
that people have cared
about for a very long time.
So this slide is due to Ross Girshick
who's worked on this
problem a lot and it shows
the progression of object
detection performance
on this one particular
data set called PASCAL VOC
which has been relatively
used for a long time
in the object detection community.
And you can see that up until about 2012
performance on object
detection started to stagnate
and slow down a little
bit and then in 2013
was when some of the first
deep learning approaches
to object detection came
around and you could see
that performance just shot up very quickly
getting better and better year over year.
One thing you might notice is that this plot ends in
2015 and it's actually continued to go up since then
so the current state of the art in this data set is well over 80 and in fact a lot of recent
papers don't even report results on this data set anymore because it's considered too easy.
So it's a little bit hard to know, I'm not actually sure what is the state
of the art number on this data set but it's off the top of this plot.
Sorry, did you have a question?
Nevermind.
Okay, so as I already said this is different from localization
because there might be differing numbers of objects for each image.
So for example in this cat on the upper left there's only one object so
we only need to predict four numbers but now for this image in the middle
there's three animals there so we need our network to
predict 12 numbers, four coordinates for each bounding box.
Or in this example of many many ducks then you want your network to
predict a whole bunch of numbers. Again, four numbers for each duck.
So this is quite different from object detection. Sorry
object detection is quite different from localization
because in object detection you might have varying numbers of objects in
the image and you don't know ahead of time how many you expect to find.
So as a result, it's kind of tricky if you want to
think of object detection as a regression problem.
So instead, people tend to work, use kind of a different
paradigm when thinking about object detection.
So one approach that's very common and has been used for a long time in
computer vision is this idea of sliding window approaches to object detection.
So this is kind of similar to this idea of taking small patches and applying that
for semantic segmentation and we can apply a similar idea for object detection.
So the ideas is that we'll take different crops from
the input image, in this case we've got this crop
in the lower left hand corner of our image and now we
take that crop, feed it through our convolutional network
and our convolutional network does a
classification decision on that input crop.
It'll say that there's no dog
here, there's no cat here,
and then in addition to the categories that we care about
we'll add an additional category called background
and now our network can predict background in case it doesn't see any
of the categories that we care about, so then when we take this crop
from the lower left hand corner here then our network would hopefully
predict background and say that no, there's no object here.
Now if we take a different crop then our network
would predict dog yes, cat no, background no.
We take a different crop we get dog yes,
cat no, background no.
Or a different crop, dog no, cat yes,
background no. Does anyone see a problem here?
Yeah, the question is how do you choose the
crops? So this is a huge problem right.
Because there could be any number of objects in this image,
these objects could appear at any location in the image,
these objects could appear at any size in the image,
these objects could also appear at any aspect ratio
in the image, so if you want to do kind of a brute force sliding window approach you'd end up having to test thousands, tens
of thousands, many many many many different crops in order to tackle this problem with a brute force sliding window approach.
And in the case where every one of those crops is going to be fed through a giant
convolutional network, this would be completely computationally intractable.
So in practice people don't ever do this sort of brute force sliding
window approach for object detection using convolutional networks.
Instead there's this cool line of work called region proposals
that comes from, this is not using deep learning typically.
These are slightly more
traditional computer vision
techniques but the idea is that a region proposal network kind of uses more
traditional signal processing, image processing type things to make some list
of proposals for where, so given an input image, a region proposal network will
then give you something like a thousand boxes where an object might be present.
So you can imagine that maybe we do some local, we look for edges in the image
and try to draw boxes that contain closed edges or something like that.
These various types of image processing approaches, but these region proposal
networks will basically look for blobby regions in our input image and then give us
some set of candidate proposal regions where objects might be
potentially found. And these are relatively fast-ish to run
so one common example of a region proposal method that
you might see is something called Selective Search
which I think actually gives you 2000 region
proposals, not the 1000 that it says on the slide.
So you kind of run this thing and then after about two seconds of turning on your CPU it'll
spit out 2000 region proposals in the input image where objects are likely to be found
so there'll be a lot of noise in those. Most of them will
not be true objects but there's a pretty high recall.
If there is an object in the image then it does tend to get
covered by these region proposals from Selective Search.
So now rather than applying our classification network
to every possible location and scale in the image
instead what we can do is first apply one of these region proposal networks
to get some set of proposal regions where objects are likely located
and now apply a convolutional network for classification to each of these
proposal regions and this will end up being much more computationally tractable
than trying to do all
possible locations and scales.
And this idea all came together in this paper called
R-CNN from a few years ago that does exactly that.
So given our input image in this case we'll run some region proposal
network to get our proposals, these are also sometimes called
regions of interest or ROI's
so again Selective Search
gives you something like
2000 regions of interest.
Now one of the problems here is that these input, these
regions in the input image could have different sizes
but if we're going to run them all through a convolutional network
our classification, our convolutional networks for classification
all want images of the same input size typically
due to the fully connected net layers and whatnot
so we need to take each of these region proposals and warp them to that
fixed square size that is expected as input to our downstream network.
So we'll crop out those region proposal, those regions corresponding
to the region proposals, we'll warp them to that fixed size,
and then we'll run each of them
through a convolutional network
which will then use in this case an SVM to make a classification decision
for each of those, to predict categories for each of those crops.
And then I lost a slide.
But it'll also, not shown in the slide right now but in addition R-CNN also predicts a regression,
like a correction to the bounding box in addition for each of these input region proposals
because the problem is that your input region proposals are kind of generally in the
right position for an object but they might not be perfect so in addition R-CNN will,
in addition to category labels for each of these proposals, it'll also predict four numbers that
are kind of an offset or a correction to the box that was predicted at the region proposal stage.
So then again, this is a multi-task loss
and you would train this whole thing.
Sorry was there a question?
The question is how much does the change
in aspect ratio impact accuracy?
It's a little bit hard to say.
I think there's some controlled experiments
in some of these papers but I'm not sure
I can give a generic answer to that.
Question?
The question is is it necessary
for regions of interest to be rectangles?
So they typically are because it's tough to
warp these non-region things but once you move
to something like instant segmentation then you
sometimes get proposals that are not rectangles.
If you actually do care about predicting
things that are not rectangles.
Is there another question?
Yeah, so the question is are the region proposals
learned so in R-CNN it's a traditional thing.
These are not learned, this is kind of some fixed algorithm
that someone wrote down but we'll see in a couple minutes
that we can actually, we've changed that a
little bit in the last couple of years.
Is there another question?
The question is is the offset always
inside the region of interest?
The answer is no, it doesn't have to be.
You might imagine that suppose the region of interest put a box around a
person but missed the head then you could imagine the network inferring
that oh this is a person but people usually have heads so
the network showed the box should be a little bit higher.
So sometimes the final predicted boxes
will be outside the region of interest.
Question?
Yeah. Yeah the question is you have a lot of
ROI's that don't correspond to true objects?
And like we said, in addition to the classes that you actually care about
you add an additional background class so your class scores can also
predict background to say
that there was no object here.
Question?
Yeah, so the question is
what kind of data do we need
and yeah, this is fully supervised in the sense that our training data has each image, consists of images.
Each image has all the object categories marked with bounding boxes for each instance of that category.
There are definitely papers that try to approach this like oh what if you don't have the data.
What if you only have that data for some images? Or what if that data is noisy but at least
in the generic case you assume full supervision
of all objects in the images at training time.
Okay, so I think we've kind of alluded to this but there's
kind of a lot of problems with this R-CNN framework.
And actually if you look at the figure here on the right you
can see that additional bounding box head so I'll put it back.
But this is kind of still
computationally pretty expensive
because if we've got 2000 region proposals, we're running each
of those proposals independently, that can be pretty expensive.
There's also this question of relying on this fixed region proposal network, this
fixed region proposals, we're not learning them so that's kind of a problem.
And just in practice it
ends up being pretty slow
so in the original implementation R-CNN would actually dump all the features to
disk so it'd take hundreds of gigabytes of disk space to store all these features.
Then training would be super slow since you have to
make all these different forward and backward passes
through the image and it took something like 84 hours is one number
they've recorded for training time so this is super super slow.
And now at test time it's also super slow,
something like roughly 30 seconds minute per image
because you need to run thousands of forward passes through the convolutional
network for each of these region proposals so this ends up being pretty slow.
Thankfully we have fast R-CNN that fixed a lot of these problems
so when we do fast R-CNN then it's going to look kind of the same.
We're going to start with our input image but now rather than processing each
region of interest separately instead we're going to run the entire image
through some convolutional layers all at once to give this high
resolution convolutional feature map corresponding to the entire image.
And now we still are using some region proposals
from some fixed thing like Selective Search
but rather than cropping out the pixels of the
image corresponding to the region proposals,
instead we imagine projecting those region proposals onto this convolutional feature map and then taking crops from
the convolutional feature map corresponding to each proposal rather than taking crops directly from the image.
And this allows us to reuse a lot of this expensive convolutional
computation across the entire image when we have many many crops per image.
But again, if we have some fully connected layers downstream
those fully connected layers are expecting some fixed-size input
so now we need to do some reshaping of those
crops from the convolutional feature map
and they do that in a differentiable way using
something they call an ROI pooling layer.
Once you have these warped crops from the convolutional
feature map then you can run these things through some
fully connected layers and predict your classification scores
and your linear regression offsets to the bounding boxes.
And now when we train this thing then we again have a multi-task loss
that trades off between these two constraints and during back propagation
we can back prop through this entire thing
and learn it all jointly.
This ROI pooling, it looks kind of like max pooling. I don't
really want to get into the details of that right now.
And in terms of speed if we look at R-CNN versus fast R-CNN versus
this other model called SPP net which is kind of in between the two,
then you can see that at training time fast R-CNN
is something like 10 times faster to train
because we're sharing all this computation
between different feature maps.
And now at test time
fast R-CNN is super fast
and in fact fast R-CNN is so fast at test time that its computation
time is actually dominated by computing region proposals.
So we said that computing these 2000 region proposals
using Selective Search takes something like two seconds
and now once we've got all these region proposals then because we're processing them all sort of in a shared way by sharing these
expensive convolutions across the entire image that we can process all of these region proposals in less than a second altogether.
So fast R-CNN ends up being bottlenecked by
just the computing of these region proposals.
Thankfully we've solved this
problem with faster R-CNN.
So the idea in faster R-CNN is to just make, so the problem was the
computing the region proposals using this fixed function was a bottleneck.
So instead we'll just make the network
itself predict its own region proposals.
And so the way that this sort of works is that again, we take our input image, run the entire input image altogether
through some convolutional layers to get some convolutional feature map representing the entire high resolution image
and now there's a separate
region proposal network
which works on top of those convolutional features and
predicts its own region proposals inside the network.
Now once we have those predicted region
proposals then it looks just like fast R-CNN
where now we take crops from those region proposals from the
convolutional features, pass them up to the rest of the network.
And now we talked about multi-task losses and multi-task
training networks to do multiple things at once.
Well now we're telling the network to do four things all at once
so balancing out this four-way multi-task loss is kind of tricky.
But because the region proposal network needs to do two things: it needs to say for
each potential proposal is it an object or not an object, it needs to actually regress
the bounding box coordinates
for each of those proposals,
and now the final network at the end
needs to do these two things again.
Make final classification decisions for what are
the class scores for each of these proposals,
and also have a second round of bounding box regression to again
correct any errors that may have come from the region proposal stage.
Question?
So the question is that sometimes multi-task learning might be
seen as regularization and are we getting that affect here?
I'm not sure if there's been
super controlled studies
on that but actually in the original version of the faster R-CNN
paper they did a little bit of experimentation like what if we share
the region proposal network,
what if we don't share?
What if we learn separate convolutional networks for the
region proposal network versus the classification network?
And I think there were minor differences but
it wasn't a dramatic difference either way.
So in practice it's kind of nicer to only learn
one because it's computationally cheaper.
Sorry, question?
Yeah the question is how do you train this region proposal network because you don't
know, you don't have ground truth region proposals for the region proposal network.
So that's a little bit hairy. I don't
want to get too much into those details
but the idea is that at any time you have a region proposal which has
more than some threshold of overlap with any of the ground truth objects
then you say that that is the positive region proposal
and you should predict that as the region proposal
and any potential proposal which has very low overlap with
any ground truth objects should be predicted as a negative.
But there's a lot of dark magic hyperparameters
in that process and that's a little bit hairy.
Question?
Yeah, so the question is what is the classification
loss on the region proposal network and the answer is
that it's making a binary, so I didn't want to get into too much of the details of
that architecture 'cause it's a little bit hairy but it's making binary decisions.
So it has some set of potential regions that it's
considering and it's making a binary decision for each one.
Is this an object or not an object?
So it's like a binary classification loss.
So once you train this thing then faster
R-CNN ends up being pretty darn fast.
So now because we've eliminated this overhead from
computing region proposals outside the network,
now faster R-CNN ends up being very very
fast compared to these other alternatives.
Also, one interesting thing is that because we're
learning the region proposals here you might imagine
maybe what if there was some mismatch between
this fixed region proposal algorithm and my data?
So in this case once you're learning your own region proposals then you can overcome that
mismatch if your region proposals are somewhat weird or different than other data sets.
So this whole family of R-CNN methods, R stands
for region, so these are all region-based methods
because there's some kind of region proposal and then we're doing some
processing, some independent processing for each of those potential regions.
So this whole family of methods are called these
region-based methods for object detection.
But there's another family of methods that
you sometimes see for object detection
which is sort of all feed
forward in a single pass.
So one of these is YOLO
for You Only Look Once.
And another is SSD for
Single Shot Detection
and these two came out
somewhat around the same time.
But the idea is that rather than doing independent processing for each of these potential
regions instead we want to try to treat this like a regression problem and just make
all these predictions all at once
with some big convolutional network.
So now given our input image you imagine dividing that input image
into some coarse grid, in this case it's a seven by seven grid
and now within each of those grid cells you
imagine some set of base bounding boxes.
Here I've drawn three base bounding boxes like a tall one, a wide
one, and a square one but in practice you would use more than three.
So now for each of these grid cells and for each of these
base bounding boxes you want to predict several things.
One, you want to predict an offset off the base bounding box to predict
what is the true location of the object off this base bounding box.
And you also want to predict classification scores so maybe a
classification score for each of these base bounding boxes.
How likely is it that an object of this
category appears in this bounding box.
So then at the end we end up predicting from our input image, we end
up predicting this giant tensor of seven by seven grid by 5B + C.
So that's just where we have B base bounding boxes, we have five numbers
for each giving our offset and our confidence for that base bounding box
and C classification scores
for our C categories.
So then we kind of see object detection as this input
of an image, output of this three dimensional tensor
and you can imagine just training this whole
thing with a giant convolutional network.
And that's kind of what
these single shot methods do
where they just, and again matching the ground truth objects into these potential
base boxes becomes a little bit hairy but that's what these methods do.
And by the way, the region proposal network that gets used in faster
R-CNN ends up looking quite similar to these where they have some set
of base bounding boxes over some gridded image, another region
proposal network does some regression plus some classification.
So there's kind of some
overlapping ideas here.
So in faster R-CNN we're kind of treating the object, the region proposal step as kind of this fixed end-to-end
regression problem and then we do the separate per region processing but now with these single shot methods
we only do that first step and just do all of our
object detection with a single forward pass.
So object detection has a
ton of different variables.
There could be different
base networks like VGG,
ResNet, we've seen different metastrategies for
object detection including this faster R-CNN
type region based family of methods,
this single shot detection
family of methods.
There's kind of a hybrid that I didn't talk about
called R-FCN which is somewhat in between.
There's a lot of different hyperparameters
like what is the image size,
how many region proposals do you use.
And there's actually this really cool paper that
will appear at CVPR this summer that does a really
controlled experimentation around a lot of these different variables and tries
to tell you how do these methods all perform under these different variables.
So if you're interested I'd
encourage you to check it out
but kind of one of the key takeaways is that the faster R-CNN style of
region based methods tends to give higher accuracies but ends up being
much slower than the single shot methods
because the single shot methods don't
require this per region processing.
But I encourage you to check out
this paper if you want more details.
Also as a bit of aside, I had this fun paper with Andre a couple years
ago that kind of combined object detection with image captioning
and did this problem
called dense captioning
so now the idea is that rather than predicting
a fixed category label for each region,
instead we want to write
a caption for each region.
And again, we had some data set that had this sort of data
where we had a data set of regions together with captions
and then we sort of trained this giant end-to-end
model that just predicted these captions all jointly.
And this ends up looking somewhat like faster
R-CNN where you have some region proposal stage
then a bounding box, then
some per region processing.
But rather than a SVM or a softmax loss instead those per region processing
has a whole RNN language model that predicts a caption for each region.
So that ends up looking quite
a bit like faster R-CNN.
There's a video here but I think
we're running out of time so I'll skip it.
But the idea here is that once you have this, you
can kind of tie together a lot of these ideas
and if you have some new problem that you're
interested in tackling like dense captioning,
you can recycle a lot of the components that you've learned
from other problems like object detection and image captioning
and kind of stitch together one end-to-end network that
produces the outputs that you care about for your problem.
So the last task that I want to talk about
is this idea of instance segmentation.
So here instance segmentation is
in some ways like the full problem
We're given an input image and we want to predict one, the locations and identities
of objects in that image similar to object detection, but rather than just
predicting a bounding box for each of those objects,
instead we want to predict a whole segmentation mask
for each of those objects and predict which pixels in
the input image corresponds to each object instance.
So this is kind of like a hybrid between
semantic segmentation and object detection
because like object detection we can handle multiple objects and we
differentiate the identities of different instances so in this example
since there are two dogs in the image and instance segmentation
method actually distinguishes between the two dog instances
and the output and kind of like semantic segmentation we have this pixel wise accuracy
where for each of these objects we want to say which pixels belong to that object.
So there's been a lot of different methods that people
have tackled, for instance segmentation as well,
but the current state of the art is this new paper called Mask R-CNN that actually just came
out on archive about a month ago so this is not yet published, this is like super fresh stuff.
And this ends up looking
a lot like faster R-CNN.
So it has this multi-stage
processing approach
where we take our whole input image, that whole input image goes into some convolutional
network and some learned region proposal network that's exactly the same as faster R-CNN
and now once we have our learned region proposals then we project those proposals
onto our convolutional feature map just like we did in fast and faster R-CNN.
But now rather than just making a classification and a bounding box
for regression decision for each of those boxes we in addition
want to predict a segmentation mask for each of those
bounding box, for each of those region proposals.
So now it kind of looks like a mini, like a semantic segmentation problem inside
each of the region proposals that we're getting from our region proposal network.
So now after we do this ROI aligning to warp our features corresponding to the
region of proposal into the right shape, then we have two different branches.
One branch will come up that looks exact, and this first branch at the top
looks just like faster R-CNN and it will predict classification scores
telling us what is the category corresponding to that region
of proposal or alternatively whether or not it's background.
And we'll also predict some bounding box coordinates
that regressed off the region proposal coordinates.
And now in addition we'll have this branch at the bottom which looks basically
like a semantic segmentation mini network which will classify for each pixel
in that input region proposal
whether or not it's an object
so this mask R-CNN problem, this mask R-CNN architecture just kind of unifies all of these different
problems that we've been talking about today into one nice jointly end-to-end trainable model.
And it's really cool and it actually works really really well so
when you look at the examples in the paper they're kind of amazing.
They look kind of indistinguishable
from ground truth.
So in this example on the left you can see that there are these two people standing in front of motorcycles, it's drawn
the boxes around these people, it's also gone in and labeled all the pixels of those people and it's really small
but actually in the background on that image on the left there's
also a whole crowd of people standing very small in the background.
It's also drawn boxes around each of those and
grabbed the pixels of each of those images.
And you can see that this is just, it ends up working really really well and
it's a relatively simple addition on top of the existing faster R-CNN framework.
So I told you that mask R-CNN unifies everything we talked
about today and it also does pose estimation by the way.
So we talked about, you can do pose estimation by predicting
these joint coordinates for each of the joints of the person
so you can do mask R-CNN to do joint object detection,
pose estimation, and instance segmentation.
And the only addition we need to make is that for each of
these region proposals we add an additional little branch
that predicts these coordinates of the joints for
the instance of the current region proposal.
So now this is just another loss, like another layer that we add, another
head coming out of the network and an additional term in our multi-task loss.
But once we add this one little branch then you can do all of these
different problems jointly and you get results looking something like this.
Where now this network, like
a single feed forward network
is deciding how many people are in the image, detecting where
those people are, figuring out the pixels corresponding to each
of those people and also drawing a skeleton estimating the pose of those people and this works really well even in crowded scenes
like this classroom where there's a ton of people sitting and they all overlap each other and it just seems to work incredibly well.
And because it's built on the faster R-CNN framework
it also runs relatively close to real time
so this is running something like five frames per second on a GPU because
this is all sort of done in the single forward pass of the network.
So this is again, a super new paper but I think that this
will probably get a lot of attention in the coming months.
So just to recap, we've talked.
Sorry question?
The question is how much
training data do you need?
So all of these instant segmentation results
were trained on the Microsoft Coco data set
so Microsoft Coco is roughly 200,000 training
images. It has 80 categories that it cares about
so in each of those 200,000 training images it has
all the instances of those 80 categories labeled.
So there's something like 200,000 images for training and there's something like I think
an average of fivee or six instances per image. So it actually is quite a lot of data.
And for Microsoft Coco for all the people in Microsoft Coco they also have
all the joints annotated as well so this actually does have quite a lot
of supervision at training time you're right, and
actually is trained with quite a lot of data.
So I think one really interesting topic to
study moving forward is that we kind of know
that if you have a lot of data to solve some problem, at this point we're relatively confident that
you can stitch up some convolutional network that can probably do a reasonable job at that problem
but figuring out ways to get performance like this with less training data is a super
interesting and active area of research and I think that's something people will be spending
a lot of their efforts working
on in the next few years.
So just to recap, today we had kind of a whirlwind tour
of a whole bunch of different computer vision topics
and we saw how a lot of the machinery that we built up from image classification
can be applied relatively easily to tackle these different computer vision topics.
And next time we'll talk about, we'll have a
really fun lecture on visualizing CNN features.