- All right welcome to lecture nine. So today
we will be talking about CNN Architectures.
And just a few administrative points before we
get started, assignment two is due Thursday.
The mid term will be in class on Tuesday May ninth, so next week and it will
cover material through Tuesday through this coming Thursday May fourth.
So everything up to recurrent neural
networks are going to be fair game.
The poster session we've decided on a time, it's going to be Tuesday June
sixth from twelve to three p.m. So this is the last week of classes.
So we have our our poster session a little bit
early during the last week so that after that,
once you guys get feedback you still have some time to
work for your final report which will be due finals week.
Okay, so just a quick review of last time.
Last time we talked about different
kinds of deep learning frameworks.
We talked about you know
PyTorch, TensorFlow, Caffe2
and we saw that using these kinds of frameworks we
were able to easily build big computational graphs,
for example very large neural networks and comm nets, and
be able to really easily compute gradients in these graphs.
So to compute all of the gradients for all the intermediate
variables weights inputs and use that to train our models
and to run all this efficiently on GPUs
And we saw that for a lot of these frameworks the way this works is by working
with these modularized layers that you guys have been working writing with,
in your home works as well where we have
a forward pass, we have a backward pass,
and then in our final model architecture, all we need to do then
is to just define all of these sequence of layers together.
So using that we're able to very easily be able
to build up very complex network architectures.
So today we're going to talk about some specific kinds of CNN Architectures
that are used today in cutting edge applications and research.
And so we'll go into depth in some of the most
commonly used architectures for these that are winners
of ImageNet classification benchmarks.
So in chronological order AlexNet,
VGG net, GoogLeNet, and ResNet.
And so these will go into a lot of depth. And then I'll also after that, briefly go through some other architectures that are
not as prominently used these days, but are interesting either from a historical perspective, or as recent areas of research.
Okay, so just a quick review.
We talked a long time ago about LeNet,
which was one of the first instantiations of a
comNet that was successfully used in practice.
And so this was the comNet that took an input image, used com filters five
by five filters applied at stride one and had a couple of conv layers,
a few pooling layers and then some
fully connected layers at the end.
And this fairly simple comNet was very
successfully applied to digit recognition.
So AlexNet from 2012 which you guys have also
heard already before in previous classes,
was the first large scale convolutional neural network
that was able to do well on the ImageNet classification
task so in 2012 AlexNet was entered in the competition, and was able to
outperform all previous non deep learning based models by a significant margin,
and so this was the comNet that started the
spree of comNet research and usage afterwards.
And so the basic comNet AlexNet architecture is a conv layer
followed by pooling layer, normalization, com pool norm,
and then a few more conv
layers, a pooling layer,
and then several fully
connected layers afterwards.
So this actually looks very similar to the LeNet network
that we just saw. There's just more layers in total.
There is five of these conv layers, and two fully connected layers
before the final fully connected layer going to the output classes.
So let's first get a sense of the
sizes involved in the AlexNet.
So if we look at the input to the AlexNet this was trained
on ImageNet, with inputs at a size 227 by 227 by 3 images.
And if we look at this first layer which is a conv layer for the
AlexNet, it's 11 by 11 filters, 96 of these applied at stride 4.
So let's just think about this for a moment.
What's the output volume size of this first layer?
And there's a hint.
So remember we have our input size, we have our convolutional filters, ray. And we have this formula,
which is the hint over here that gives you the size of the output dimensions after applying com right?
So remember it was the full image, minus the
filter size, divided by the stride, plus one.
So given that that's written up here for you 55, does anyone have
a guess at what's the final output size after this conv layer?
[student speaks off mic]
- So I had 55 by 55 by 96, yep.
That's correct.
Right so our spatial dimensions at the output are
going to be 55 in each dimension and then we have
96 total filters so the depth after our conv layer
is going to be 96. So that's the output volume.
And what's the total number
of parameters in this layer?
So remember we have 96 11 by 11 filters.
[student speaks off mic]
- [Lecturer] 96 by 11 by 11, almost.
So yes, so I had another by three,
yes that's correct.
So each of the filters is going to see through a local region
of 11 by 11 by three, right because the input depth was three.
And so, that's each filter size,
times we have 96 of these total.
And so there's 35K parameters
in this first layer.
Okay, so now if we look at the second layer
this is a pooling layer right and in this case
we have three three by three
filters applied at stride two.
So what's the output volume
of this layer after pooling?
And again we have a hint, very
similar to the last question.
Okay, 27 by 27 by 96.
Yes that's correct.
Right so the pooling layer is basically
going to use this formula that we had here.
Again because these are pooling applied at a stride of two so we're going to use the same formula to determine
the spatial dimensions and so the spatial dimensions are going to be 27 by 27, and pooling preserves the depth.
So we had 96 as depth as input, and it's
still going to be 96 depth at output.
And next question. What's the
number of parameters in this layer?
I hear some muttering.
[student answers off mic]
- Nothing.
Okay.
Yes, so pooling layer has no parameters,
so, kind of a trick question.
Okay, so we can basically, yes, question?
[student speaks off mic]
- The question is, why are there no
parameters in the pooling layer?
The parameters are the weights right,
that we're trying to learn.
And so convolutional layers
have weights that we learn
but pooling all we do is have a rule, we look
at the pooling region, and we take the max.
So there's no parameters that are learned.
So we can keep on doing this and you can just repeat the process and it's kind of a good
exercise to go through this and figure out the sizes, the parameters, at every layer.
And so if you do this all the way, you can look at
this is the final architecture that you can work with.
There's 11 by 11 filters at the beginning, then five by five and some three
by three filters. And so these are generally pretty familiar looking sizes
that you've seen before and then at the end we have a couple of
fully connected layers of size 4096 and finally the last layer,
is FC8 going to the soft max,
which is going to the
1000 ImageNet classes.
And just a couple of details about this, it was the first use of the ReLu
non-linearity that we've talked about that's the most commonly used non-linearity.
They used local response normalization layers basically trying to normalize the response
across neighboring channels but this is something that's not really used anymore.
It turned out not to, other people showed
that it didn't have so much of an effect.
There's a lot of heavy data augmentation, and so you can look in the paper for more details,
but things like flipping, jittering, jittering, color normalization all of these things
which you'll probably find useful for you when you're working on
your projects for example, so a lot of data augmentation here.
They also use dropout batch size of 128,
and learned with SGD with
momentum which we talked about
in an earlier lecture, and basically just started
with a base learning rate of 1e negative 2.
Every time it plateaus, reduce by a factor of 10 and
then just keep going. Until they finish training
and a little bit of weight decay and in the end, in order to get the best numbers
they also did an ensembling of models and so training multiple of these,
averaging them together and this also
gives an improvement in performance.
And so one other thing I want to point out is
that if you look at this AlexNet diagram up here,
it looks kind of like the normal comNet diagrams
that we've been seeing, except for one difference,
which is that it's, you can see it's kind of split
in these two different rows or columns going across.
And so the reason for this is mostly historical note, so AlexNet was
trained on GTX580 GPUs older GPUs that only had three gigs of memory.
So it couldn't actually fit
this entire network on here,
and so what they ended up doing, was
they spread the network across two GPUs.
So on each GPU you would have half of the
neurons, or half of the feature maps.
And so for example if you look at this first
conv layer, we have 55 by 55 by 96 output,
but if you look at this diagram carefully, you can zoom in later in the actual
paper, you can see that, it's actually only 48 depth-wise, on each GPU,
and so they just spread it, the
feature maps, directly in half.
And so what happens is that for most of these layers, for example com
one, two, four and five, the connections are only with feature maps
on the same GPU, so you would take as input, half of the feature maps that were on the
the same GPU as before and you don't look at the full 96 feature maps for example.
You just take as input the
48 in that first layer.
And then there's a few layers so com three, as well as FC six, seven and eight, where here are the
GPUs do talk to each other and so there's connections with all feature maps in the preceding layer.
so there's communication across the GPUs, and each of these neurons
are then connected to the full depth of the previous input layer.
Question.
- [Student] It says the full simplified
AlexNetwork architecture. [mumbles]
- Oh okay, so the question is why does it say
full simplified AlexNet architecture here?
It just says that because I didn't put all the details on here, so for example
this is the full set of layers in the architecture, and the strides and so on,
but for example the normalization layer, there's
other, these details are not written on here.
And then just one little note, if you look at the paper and
try and write out the math and architectures and so on,
there's a little bit of an issue on the very first layer they'll say if you'll look in the figure they'll say 224 by 224 ,
but there's actually some kind of funny pattern going on and so the numbers actually work out if you look at it as 227.
AlexNet was the winner of the ImageNet classification benchmark in
2012, you can see that it cut the error rate by quite a large margin.
It was the first CNN base winner, and it was widely used as a base to our
architecture almost ubiquitously from then until a couple years ago.
It's still used quite a bit.
It's used in transfer learning for lots of different
tasks and so it was used for basically a long time,
and it was very famous and now though there's been some more recent architectures
that have generally just had better performance and so we'll talk about these
next and these are going to be the more common
architectures that you'll be wanting to use in practice.
So just quickly first in 2013 the ImageNet
challenge was won by something called a ZFNet.
Yes, question.
[student speaks off mic]
- So the question is intuition why AlexNet was
so much better than the ones that came before,
DefLearning comNets [mumbles] this is just a
very different kind of approach in architecture.
So this was the first deep learning based
approach first comNet that was used.
So in 2013 the challenge was won by something called a
ZFNet [Zeller Fergus Net] named after the creators.
And so this mostly was improving
hyper parameters over the AlexNet.
It had the same number of layers, the same general structure and they made a few changes things like changing
the stride size, different numbers of filters and after playing around with these hyper parameters more,
they were able to improve the error rate.
But it's still basically the same idea.
So in 2014 there are a couple of architectures that were now more
significantly different and made another jump in performance,
and the main difference with these networks
first of all was much deeper networks.
So from the eight layer network that was in 2012 and 2013, now in 2014 we had two
very close winners that were around 19 layers and 22 layers. So significantly deeper.
And the winner of this
was GoogleNet, from Google
but very close behind was
something called VGGNet
from Oxford, and on actually the localization challenge
VGG got first place in some of the other tracks.
So these were both very,
very strong networks.
So let's first look at VGG
in a little bit more detail.
And so the VGG network is the idea of much
deeper networks and with much smaller filters.
So they increased the number of layers from eight layers in AlexNet
right to now they had models with 16 to 19 layers in VGGNet.
And one key thing that they did was they kept very small filter so only three by three conv all the way,
which is basically the smallest com filter size that is looking at a little bit of the neighboring pixels.
And they just kept this very simple structure of three by three
convs with the periodic pooling all the way through the network.
And it's very simple elegant network architecture, was
able to get 7.3% top five error on the ImageNet challenge.
So first the question of
why use smaller filters.
So when we take these small filters now we have
fewer parameters and we try and stack more of them
instead of having larger filters, have smaller filters with
more depth instead, have more of these filters instead,
what happens is that you end up having the same effective receptive
field as if you only have one seven by seven convolutional layer.
So here's a question, what is the effective receptive field
of three of these three by three conv layers with stride one?
So if you were to stack three three by three conv layers
with Stride one what's the effective receptive field,
the total area of the input, spatial area of the input that
enure at the top layer of the three layers is looking at.
So I heard fifteen pixels,
why fifteen pixels?
- [Student] Okay, so the
reason given was because
they overlap-- - Okay, so the reason given was
because they overlap. So it's on the right track.
What actually is happening though is you have to see, at the first
layer, the receptive field is going to be three by three right?
And then at the second layer, each of these neurons in the second
layer is going to look at three by three other first layer
filters, but the corners of these three by three have an additional
pixel on each side, that is looking at in the original input layer.
So the second layer is actually looking at five by
five receptive field and then if you do this again,
the third layer is looking at three by three
in the second layer but this is going to,
if you just draw out this pyramid is looking
at seven by seven in the input layer.
So the effective receptive field here is going to be seven by
seven. Which is the same as one seven by seven conv layer.
So what happens is that this has the same effective receptive
field as a seven by seven conv layer but it's deeper.
It's able to have more non-linearities in
there, and it's also fewer parameters.
So if you look at the total number of parameters, each of these conv filters for
the three by threes is going to have nine parameters in each conv [mumbles]
three times three, and then times the input depth, so
three times three times C, times this total number
of output feature maps, which is again C is we're
going to preserve the total number of channels.
So you get three times three, times C times C for each of these layers,
and we have three layers so it's going to be three times this number,
compared to if you had a single seven by seven layer then you
get, by the same reasoning, seven squared times C squared.
So you're going to have fewer
parameters total, which is nice.
So now if we look at this full network here there's a lot of numbers up
here that you can go back and look at more carefully but if we look at all
of the sizes and number of parameters the same
way that we calculated the example for AlexNet,
this is a good exercise to go through,
we can see that you know going the same way we have a couple of these conv layers and a pooling layer a
couple more conv layers, pooling layer, several more conv layers and so on. And so this just keeps going up.
And if you counted the total number of convolutional and fully
connected layers, we're going to have 16 in this case for VGG 16,
and then VGG 19, it's just a very similar architecture,
but with a few more conv layers in there.
And so the total memory
usage of this network,
so just making a forward pass through counting up all of these numbers so in the
memory numbers here written in terms of the total numbers, like we calculated earlier,
and if you look at four bytes per number,
this is going to be about 100 megs per image,
and so this is the scale of the memory usage that's
happening and this is only for a forward pass right,
when you do a backward pass you're going to have to
store more and so this is pretty heavy memory wise.
100 megs per image, if you have on five gigs of total memory,
then you're only going to be able to store about 50 of these.
And so also the total number of parameters here we have is 138 million
parameters in this network, and this compares with 60 million for AlexNet.
Question?
[student speaks off mic]
- So the question is what do we mean by deeper,
is it the number of filters, number of layers?
So deeper in this case is
always referring to layers.
So there are two usages of the word depth which is confusing one is the depth
rate per channel, width by height by depth, you can use the word depth here,
but in general we talk about the depth of a network, this is going to
be the total number of layers in the network, and usually in particular
we're counting the total number of weight layers. So the total number of layers
with trainable weight, so convolutional layers and fully connected layers.
[student mumbles off mic]
- Okay, so the question is, within each
layer what do different filters need?
And so we talked about this back in the comNet
lecture, so you can also go back and refer to that,
but each filter is a set of let's say three by three convs, so each filter is looking at a, is a set
of weight looking at a three by three value input input depth, and this produces one feature map,
one activation map of all the responses
of the different spatial locations.
And then we have we can have as many filters as we want right so for
example 96 and each of these is going to produce a feature map.
And so it's just like each filter corresponds to a different pattern that we're looking for
in the input that we convolve around and we see the responses everywhere in the input,
we create a map of these and then another filter will
we convolve over the image and create another map.
Question.
[student speaks off mic]
- So question is, is there intuition behind, as you go deeper into the network
we have more channel depth so more number of filters right and so you can have
any design that you want so
you don't have to do this.
In practice you will see this
happen a lot of the times
and one of the reasons is people try and maintain
kind of a relatively constant level of compute,
so as you go higher up or deeper into your network,
you're usually also using basically down sampling
and having smaller total spatial area and then so then
they also increase now you increase by depth a little bit,
it's not as expensive now to increase by depth because
it's spatially smaller and so, yeah that's just a reason.
Question.
[student speaks off mic]
- So performance-wise is there any reason to use
SBN [mumbles] instead of SouthMax [mumbles],
so no, for a classifier you can use either one,
and you did that earlier in the class as well,
but in general SouthMax losses, have generally worked
well and been standard use for classification here.
Okay yeah one more question.
[student mumbles off mic]
- Yes, so the question is, we don't have to store all of the memory
like we can throw away the parts that we don't need and so on?
And yes this is true.
Some of this you don't need to keep,
but you're also going to be doing a backwards pass through ware for the most part, when you were doing the chain rule
and so on you needed a lot of these activations as part of it and so in large part a lot of this does need to be kept.
So if we look at the distribution of where memory is used and where parameters are,
you can see that a lot of memories in these early layers right where you still have
spatial dimensions you're going to have more memory usage and then a lot of
the parameters are actually in the last layers, the fully connected layers
have a huge number of parameters right, because
we have all of these dense connections.
And so that's something just to know and then keep
in mind so later on we'll see some networks actually
get rid of these fully connected layers and be
able to save a lot on the number of parameters.
And then just one last thing to point out, you'll also
see different ways of calling all of these layers right.
So here I've written out exactly what the layers are.
conv3-64 means three by three convs with 64 total filters.
But for VGGNet on this diagram on the right here there's also
common ways that people will look at each group of filters,
so each orange block here, as in conv1
part one, so conv1-1, conv1-2, and so on.
So just something to keep in mind.
So VGGNet ended up getting second place in
the ImageNet 2014 classification challenge,
first in localization.
They followed a very similar training
procedure as Alex Krizhevsky for the AlexNet.
They didn't use local response normalization, so as I mentioned earlier,
they found out this didn't really help them, and so they took it out.
You'll see VGG 16 and VGG 19 are common variants of the cycle here,
and this is just the number of layers, 19 is slightly deeper than 16.
In practice VGG 19 works very little bit better, and there's a little bit
more memory usage, so you can use either but 16 is very commonly used.
For best results, like AlexNet, they did ensembling in order
to average several models, and you get better results.
And they also showed in their work that the FC7 features of the last
fully connected layer before going to the 1000 ImageNet classes.
The 4096 size layer just before that,
is a good feature representation,
that can even just be used as is, to extract these features
from other data, and generalized these other tasks as well.
And so FC7 is a good
feature representation.
Yeah question.
[student speaks off mic]
- Sorry what was the question?
Okay, so the question is
what is localization here?
And so this is a task, and we'll talk about it a little bit more in
a later lecture on detection and localization so I don't want to
go into detail here but it's basically an image, not
just classifying What's the class of the image,
but also drawing a bounding box around
where that object is in the image.
And the difference with detection, which is a very related task is that
detection there can be multiple instances of this object in the image
localization we're assuming there's just one, this
classification but we just how this additional bounding box.
So we looked at VGG which was one of the deep networks
from 2014 and then now we'll talk about GoogleNet
which was the other one that won
the classification challenge.
So GoogleNet again was a much deeper network with 22 layers but one of
the main insights and special things about GoogleNet is that it really
looked at this problem of computational efficiency and it tried to design
a network architecture that was very efficient in the amount of compute.
And so they did this using this inception module which
we'll go into more detail and basically stacking
a lot of these inception
modules on top of each other.
There's also no fully connected layers in this network, so they got rid of that were able to save a lot of
parameters and so in total there's only five million parameters which is twelve times less than AlexNet,
which had 60 million even
though it's much deeper now.
It got 6.7% top five error.
So what's the inception module?
So the idea behind the inception module
is that they wanted to design
a good local network typology
and it has this idea of this local topology that's you know you can think of it as a network
within a network and then stack a lot of these local typologies one on top of each other.
And so in this local network that they're calling an
inception module what they're doing is they're basically
applying several different kinds of filter operations in
parallel on top of the same input coming into this same layer.
So we have our input coming in from the previous layer and
then we're going to do different kinds of convolutions.
So a one by one conv, right a three by three conv, five by five conv, and then they also have a pooling operation
in this case three by three pooling, and so you get all of these different outputs from these different layers,
and then what they do is they concatenate all
these filter outputs together depth wise, and so
then this creates one tenser output at the end
that is going tom pass on to the next layer.
So if we look at just a naive way of doing this we just do exactly that we have all
of these different operations we get the outputs we concatenate them together.
So what's the problem with this?
And it turns out that computational
complexity is going to be a problem here.
So if we look more carefully at an example, so here just for as an example I've put one by
one conv, 128 filter so three by three conv 192 filters, five by five convs and 96 filters.
Assume everything has basically the stride that's going to maintain
the spatial dimensions, and that we have this input coming in.
So what is the output size of the one by one filter with
128 , one by one conv with 128 filters? Who has a guess?
OK so I heard 28 by 28,
by 128 which is correct.
So right by one by one conv we're going to maintain spatial dimensions and then on top
of that, each conv filter is going to look through the entire 256 depth of the input,
but then the output is going to be, we have a 28 by 28 feature
map for each of the 128 filters that we have in this conv layer.
So we get 28 by 28 by 128.
OK and then now if we do the same thing and we look at the filter sizes
of the output sizes sorry of all of the different filters here, after the
three by three conv we're going to have this volume
of 28 by 28 by 192 right after five by five conv
we have 96 filters here.
So 28 by 28 by 96,
and then out pooling layer is just going to keep the same spatial
dimension here, so pooling layer will preserve it in depth,
and here because of our stride, we're also
going to preserve our spatial dimensions.
And so now if we look at the output size after filter concatenation what we're
going to get is 28 by 28, these are all 28 by 28, and we concatenating depth wise.
So we get 28 by 28 times all of these added together, and
the total output size is going to be 28 by 28 by 672.
So the input to our inception module was 28 by 28 by 256,
then the output from this module is 28 by 28 by 672.
So we kept the same spatial dimensions,
and we blew up the depth.
Question.
[student speaks off mic]
OK So in this case, yeah, the question is,
how are we getting 28 by 28 for everything?
So here we're doing all the zero padding in
order to maintain the spatial dimensions,
and that way we can do this filter
concatenation depth-wise.
Question in the back.
[student speaks off mic]
- OK The question is what's
the 256 deep at the input,
and so this is not the input to the network, this is the
input just to this local module that I'm looking at.
So in this case 256 is the depth of the previous
inception module that came just before this.
And so now coming out we have 28 by 28 by 672, and that's
going to be the input to the next inception module.
Question.
[student speaks off mic]
- Okay the question is, how did we get 28 by
28 by 128 for the first one, the first conv,
and this is basically it's a one by one convolution right, so we're going to take
this one by one convolution slide it across our 28 by 28 by 256 input spatially
where it's at each location, it's going to multiply, it's going
to do a [mumbles] through the entire 256 depth, and so we do this
one by one conv slide it over spatially and we
get a feature map out that's 28 by 28 by one.
There's one number at each spatial location coming out, and each filter produces
one of these 28 by 28 by one maps, and we have here a total 128 filters,
and that's going to
produce 28 by 28, by 128.
OK so if you look at the number of operations
that are happening in the convolutional layer,
let's look at the first one for example this one by one conv as I was just
saying at each each location we're doing a one by one by 256 dot product.
So there's 256 multiply
operations happening here
and then for each filter map we have 28 by 28 spatial locations, so
that's the first 28 times 28 first two numbers that are multiplied here.
These are the spatial locations for each filter map, and so we have to do this to 25 60 multiplication
each one of these then we have 128 total filters at this layer, or we're producing 128 total feature maps.
And so the total number of these operations here
is going to be 28 times 28 times 128 times 256.
And so this is going to be the same for, you can think about this for the three
by three conv, and the five by five conv, that's exactly the same principle.
And in total we're going to get 854 million
operations that are happening here.
- [Student] And the 128,
192, and 96 are just values
- Question the 128, 192 and 256 are values that I picked.
Yes, these are not values that I just came up with.
They are similar to the ones that you will see
in like a particular layer of inception net,
so in GoogleNet basically, each module has a different set of these
kinds of parameters, and I picked one that was similar to one of these.
And so this is very expensive computationally
right, these these operations.
And then the other thing that I also want to note is that the pooling layer
also adds to this problem because it preserves the whole feature depth.
So at every layer your total depth can only grow
right, you're going to take the full featured depth
from your pooling layer, as well as all the additional
feature maps from the conv layers and add these up together.
So here our input was 256 depth and our output is 672 depth
and you're just going to keep increasing this as you go up.
So how do we deal with this and how
do we keep this more manageable?
And so one of the key insights that GoogleNet used was that well we can we can
address this by using bottleneck layers and try and project these feature maps
to lower dimension before our our convolutional
operations, so before our expensive layers.
And so what exactly does that mean?
So reminder one by one convolution, I guess we were just going through this but it's taking your input volume,
it's performing a dot product at each spatial location and what it does is it preserves spatial dimension
but it reduces the depth and it reduces that by
projecting your input depth to a lower dimension.
It just takes it's basically like a linear
combination of your input feature maps.
And so this main idea is that it's projecting
your depth down and so the inception module
takes these one by one convs and adds these at a bunch of places in these modules
where there's going to be, in order to alleviate this expensive compute.
So before the three by three and five by five conv
layers, it puts in one of these one by one convolutions.
And then after the pooling layer it also
puts an additional one by one convolution.
Right so these are the one by one
bottleneck layers that are added in.
And so how does this change the math
that we were looking at earlier?
So now basically what's happening is that we
still have the same input here 28 by 28 by 256,
but these one by one convs are going to reduce the depth dimension and so you can see before the three by
three convs, if I put a one by one conv with 64 filters, my output from that is going to be, 28 by 28 by 64.
So instead of now going into the three by three convs afterwards instead of
28 by 28 by 256 coming in, we only have a 28 by 28, by 64 block coming in.
And so this is now reducing the smaller input
going into these conv layers, the same thing for
the five by five conv, and then for the pooling layer, after the
pooling comes out, we're going to reduce the depth after this.
And so, if you work out the math the same way for all of the convolutional ops here,
adding in now all these one by one convs on top of the three by threes and five by fives,
the total number of operations is 358 million operations, so it's much less than
the 854 million that we had in the naive version, and so you can see how you
can use this one by one conv, and the filter
size for that to control your computation.
Yes, question in the back.
[student speaks off mic]
- Yes, so the question is, have you looked into what information
might be lost by doing this one by one conv at the beginning.
And so there might be
some information loss,
but at the same time if you're doing these projections you're taking a linear combination of
these input feature maps which has redundancy in them, you're taking combinations of them,
and you're also introducing an additional non-linearity after the one by one conv, so it also actually
helps in that way with adding a little bit more depth and so, I don't think there's a rigorous analysis
of this, but basically in general this works
better and there's reasons why it helps as well.
OK so here we have, we're basically using these one by
one convs to help manage our computational complexity,
and then what GooleNet does is it takes these inception
modules and it's going to stack all these together.
So this is a full inception architecture.
And if we look at this a little bit more detail, so here I've flipped it,
because it's so big, it's not going to fit vertically any more on the slide.
So what we start with is we first have this stem network, so this is more the kind
of vanilla plain conv net that we've seen earlier [mumbles] six sequence of layers.
So conv pool a couple of convs in another
pool just to get started and then after that
we have all of our different our multiple inception
modules all stacked on top of each other,
and then on top we have
our classifier output.
And notice here that they've really removed the expensive fully connected layers it turns
out that the model works great without them, even and you reduce a lot of parameters.
And then what they also have here is, you can see these couple of
extra stems coming out and these are auxiliary classification outputs
and so these are also you know
just a little mini networks
with an average pooling, a one by one conv, a
couple of fully connected layers here going to
the soft Max and also a 1000 way SoftMax
with the ImageNet classes.
And so you're actually using your ImageNet training
classification loss in three separate places here.
The standard end of the network, as well as in these two places earlier on
in the network, and the reason they do that is just this is a deep network
and they found that having these additional auxiliary classification
outputs, you get more gradient training injected at the earlier layers,
and so more just helpful signal flowing in because these intermediate layers should also
be helpful. You should be able to do classification based off some of these as well.
And so this is the full architecture,
there's 22 total layers with weights and so
within each of these modules each of those one by one, three by three, five
by five is a weight layer, just including all of these parallel layers,
and in general it's a relatively more carefully designed architecture and part of
this is based on some of these intuitions that we're talking about and part of them
also is just you know Google the authors they had huge clusters and they're cross
validating across all kinds of design choices and this is what ended up working well.
Question?
[student speaks off mic]
- Yeah so the question is, are the auxiliary outputs actually
useful for the final classification, to use these as well?
I think when they're training them they do average all
these for the losses coming out. I think they are helpful.
I can't remember if in the final architecture, whether they average all of these or just take
one, it seems very possible that they would use all of them, but you'll need to check on that.
[student speaks off mic]
- So the question is for the bottleneck layers, is it possible to use some other types
of dimensionality reduction and yes you can use other kinds of dimensionality reduction.
The benefits here of this one by one conv is, you're getting this
effect, but it's all, you know it's a conv layer just like any other.
You have the soul network of these, you just train it this full network back [mumbles]
through everything, and it's learning how to combine the previous feature maps.
Okay yeah, question in the back.
[student speaks off mic]
- Yes so, question is are any weights
shared or all they all separate and yeah,
all of these layers have separate weights.
Question.
[student speaks off mic]
- Yes so the question is why do we have
to inject gradients at earlier layers?
So our classification output at the very end, where we get a gradient
on this, it's passed all the way back through the chain roll
but the problem is when you have very deep networks and you're going all the way back through these, some
of this gradient signal can become minimized and lost closer to the beginning, and so that's why having
these additional ones in earlier parts
can help provide some additional signal.
[student mumbles off mic]
- So the question is are you doing back
prop all the times for each output.
No it's just one back prop all the way
through, and you can think of these three,
you can think of there being kind of like an addition at the end of these
if you were to draw up your computational graph, and so you get your
final signal and you can just take all of these
gradients and just back plot them all the way through.
So it's as if they were added together
at the end in a computational graph.
OK so in the interest of time because we still have a
lot to get through, can take other questions offline.
Okay so GoogleNet basically 22 layers.
It has an efficient inception module,
there's no fully connected layers.
12 times fewer parameters than AlexNet, and
it's the ILSVRC 2014 classification winner.
And so now let's look at the 2015 winner,
which is the ResNet network and so here
this idea is really, this revolution of depth net right.
We were starting to increase depth in 2014, and here we've
just had this hugely deeper model at 152
layers was the ResNet architecture.
And so now let's look at that
in a little bit more detail.
So the ResNet architecture, is getting extremely
deep networks, much deeper than any other networks
before and it's doing this using this idea of
residual connections which we'll talk about.
And so, they had 152
layer model for ImageNet.
They were able to get 3.5
of 7% top 5 error with this
and the really special thing is that they swept all classification and detection
contests in the ImageNet mart benchmark and this other benchmark called COCO.
It just basically won everything. So it was
just clearly better than everything else.
And so now let's go into a little bit of the motivation
behind ResNet and residual connections that we'll talk about.
And the question that they started off by trying to answer is what happens when we
try and stack deeper and deeper layers on a plain convolutional neural network?
So if we take something like VGG or some normal network that's just stacks of conv and pool layers
on top of each other can we just continuously extend these, get deeper layers and just do better?
And and the answer is no.
So if you so if you look at what happens when you get deeper, so here I'm
comparing a 20 layer network and a 56 layer network and so this is just a plain
kind of network you'll see that in the test error here on the right
the 56 layer network is doing worse than the 28 layer network.
So the deeper network was
not able to do better.
But then the really weird thing is now if you look at the training error
right we here have again the 20 layer network and a 56 layer network.
The 56 layer network, one of the obvious problems you think, I have a really deep network,
I have tons of parameters maybe it's probably starting to over fit at some point.
But what actually happens is that when you're over fitting you would expect
to have very good, very low training error rate, and just bad test error,
but what's happening here is that in the training error the 56
layer network is also doing worse than the 20 layer network.
And so even though the deeper model performs
worse, this is not caused by over-fitting.
And so the hypothesis of the ResNet creators is that
the problem is actually an optimization problem.
Deeper models are just harder to optimize,
than more shallow networks.
And the reasoning was that well,
a deeper model should be
able to perform at least
as well as a shallower model.
You can have actually a
solution by construction
where you just take the learned layers
from your shallower model, you just
copy these over and then
for the remaining additional
deeper layers you just
add identity mappings.
So by construction this
should be working just as well
as the shallower layer.
And your model that weren't
able to learn properly,
it should be able to learn at least this.
And so motivated by
this their solution was
well how can we make it
easier for our architecture,
our model to learn these
kinds of solutions,
or at least something like this?
And so their idea is well
instead of just stacking
all these layers on top
of each other and having
every layer try and learn
some underlying mapping
of a desired function, lets
instead have these blocks,
where we try and fit a residual mapping,
instead of a direct mapping.
And so what this looks
like is here on this right
where the input to these block
is just the input coming in
and here we are going to
use our, here on the side,
we're going to use our
layers to try and fit
some residual of our desire to H of X,
minus X instead of the desired
function H of X directly.
And so basically at the
end of this block we take
the step connection on
this right here, this loop,
where we just take our input,
we just use pass it through
as an identity, and so if
we had no weight layers
in between it was just
going to be the identity
it would be the same thing
as the output, but now we use
our additional weight
layers to learn some delta,
for some residual from our X.
And so now the output
of this is going to be
just our original R X plus some residual
that we're going to call it.
It's basically a delta
and so the idea is that
now the output it should
be easy for example,
in the case where identity is ideal,
to just squash all of
these weights of F of X
from our weight layers
just set it to all zero
for example, then we're
just going to get identity
as the output, and we can get something,
for example, close to this
solution by construction
that we had earlier.
Right, so this is just
a network architecture
that says okay, let's try and fit this,
learn how our weight layers
residual, and be something
close, that way it'll more
likely be something close to X,
it's just modifying X,
than to learn exactly
this full mapping of what it should be.
Okay, any questions about this?
[student speaks off mic]
- Question is is there the same dimension?
So yes these two paths
are the same dimension.
In general either it's the same dimension,
or what they actually
do is they have these
projections and shortcuts
and they have different ways
of padding to make things work
out to be the same dimension.
Depth wise.
Yes
- [Student] When you use the word residual
you were talking about [mumbles off mic]
- So the question is what
exactly do we mean by
residual this output
of this transformation
is a residual?
So we can think of our output
here right as this F of X
plus X, where F of X is the
output of our transformation
and then X is our input,
just passed through
by the identity.
So we'd like to using a plain layer,
what we're trying to do is learn something
like H of X, but what we saw
earlier is that it's hard
to learn H of X.
It's a good H of X as we
get very deep networks.
And so here the idea is
let's try and break it down
instead of as H of X is
equal to F of X plus,
and let's just try and learn F of X.
And so instead of learning
directly this H of X
we just want to learn what
is it that we need to add
or subtract to our input as
we move on to the next layer.
So you can think of it as
kind of modifying this input,
in place in a sense.
We have--
[interrupted by student mumbling off mic]
- The question is, when we're
saying the word residual
are we talking about F of X?
Yeah.
So F of X is what we're
calling the residual.
And it just has that meaning.
Yes another question.
[student mumbles off mic]
- So the question is in
practice do we just sum
F of X and X together, or
do we learn some weighted
combination and you just do a direct sum.
Because when you do a direct sum,
this is the idea of let
me just learn what is it
I have to add or subtract onto X.
Is this clear to everybody,
the main intuition?
Question.
[student speaks off mic]
- Yeah, so the question
is not clear why is it
that learning the
residual should be easier
than learning the direct mapping?
And so this is just their hypotheses,
and a hypotheses is that if
we're learning the residual
you just have to learn
what's the delta to X right?
And if our hypotheses is that generally
even something like our
solution by construction,
where we had some number
of these shallow layers
that were learned and we had
all these identity mappings
at the top this was a
solution that should have been
good, and so that implies that
maybe a lot of these layers,
actually something just close to identity,
would be a good layer
And so because of that,
now we formulate this
as being able to learn the identity
plus just a little delta.
And if really the identity
is best we just make
F of X squashes transformation
to just be zero,
which is something that's relatively,
might seem easier to learn,
also we're able to get
things that are close
to identity mappings.
And so again this is not
something that's necessarily
proven or anything it's just
the intuition and hypothesis,
and then we'll also see
later some works where people
are actually trying to
challenge this and say oh maybe
it's not actually the residuals
that are so necessary,
but at least this is the
hypothesis for this paper,
and in practice using this model,
it was able to do very well.
Question.
[student speaks off mic]
- Yes so the question is
have people tried other ways
of combining the inputs
from previous layers and yes
so this is basically a very
active area of research
on and how we formulate
all these connections,
and what's connected to what
in all of these structures.
So we'll see a few more
examples of different network
architectures briefly later
but this is an active area
of research.
OK so we basically have all
of these residual blocks
that are stacked on top of each other.
We can see the full resident architecture.
Each of these residual blocks
has two three by three conv
layers as part of this block
and there's also been work
just saying that this happens
to be a good configuration
that works well.
We stack all these blocks
together very deeply.
Another thing like with
this very deep architecture
it's basically also
enabling up to 150 layers
deep of this, and then
what we do is we stack
all these and periodically we also double
the number of filters
and down sample spatially
using stride two when we do that.
And then we have this additional [mumbles]
at the very beginning of our network
and at the end we also hear,
don't have any fully connected layers
and we just have a global
average pooling layer
that's going to average
over everything spatially,
and then be input into the
last 1000 way classification.
So this is the full ResNet architecture
and it's very simple and
elegant just stacking up
all of these ResNet blocks
on top of each other,
and they have total depths
of up to 34, 50, 100,
and they tried up to 152 for ImageNet.
OK so one additional
thing just to know is that
for a very deep network,
so the ones that are more
than 50 layers deep, they
also use bottleneck layers
similar to what GoogleNet did
in order to improve efficiency
and so within each block
now you're going to,
what they did is, have this
one by one conv filter,
that first projects it
down to a smaller depth.
So again if we are looking
at let's say 28 by 28
by 256 implant, we do
this one by one conv,
it's taking it's
projecting the depth down.
We get 28 by 28 by 64.
Now your convolution
your three by three conv,
in here they only have
one, is operating over this
reduced step so it's going
to be less expensive,
and then afterwards they have another
one by one conv that
projects the depth back up
to 256, and so, this is
the actual block that
you'll see in deeper networks.
So in practice the ResNet
also uses batch normalization
after every conv layer, they
use Xavier initialization
with an extra scaling factor
that they helped introduce
to improve the initialization
trained with SGD + momentum.
Their learning rate they
use a similar learning rate
type of schedule where you
decay your learning rate
when your validation error plateaus.
Mini batch size 256, a
little bit of weight decay
and no drop out.
And so experimentally they
were able to show that they
were able to train these
very deep networks,
without degrading.
They were able to have
basically good gradient flow
coming all the way back
down through the network.
They tried up to 152 layers on ImageNet,
1200 on Cifar, which is a,
you have played with it,
but a smaller data set
and they also saw that now
you're deeper networks are
able to achieve lower training
errors as expected.
So you don't have the same strange plots
that we saw earlier where the behavior
was in the wrong direction.
And so from here they were
able to sweep first place
at all of the ILSVRC competitions,
and all of the COCO competitions in 2015
by a significant margins.
Their total top five error
was 3.6 % for a classification
and this is actually better
than human performance
in the ImageNet paper.
There was also a human
metric that came from
actually [mumbles] our
lab Andre Kapathy spent
like a week training
himself and then basically
did all of, did this task himself
and was I think somewhere around 5-ish %,
and so I was basically able to do
better than the then that human at least.
Okay, so these are kind
of the main networks
that have been used recently.
We had AlexNet starting off with first,
VGG and GoogleNet are still very popular,
but ResNet is the most
recent best performing model
that if you're looking for
something training a new network
ResNet is available, you should try
working with it.
So just quickly looking at
some of this getting a better
sense of the complexity involved.
So here we have some
plots that are sorted by
performance so this is
top one accuracy here,
and higher is better.
And so you'll see a lot
of these models that we
talked about, as well as
some different versions
of them so, this
GoogleNet inception thing,
I think there's like V2,
V3 and the best one here
is V4, which is actually
a ResNet plus inception
combination, so these are just kind of
more incremental, smaller
changes that they've
built on top of them,
and so that's the best
performing model here.
And if we look on the
right, these plots of their
computational complexity here it's sorted.
The Y axis is your top one accuracy
so higher is better.
The X axis is your operations
and so the more to the right,
the more ops you're doing,
the more computationally
expensive and then the bigger the circle,
your circle is your memory usage,
so the gray circles are referenced here,
but the bigger the circle
the more memory usage
and so here we can see
that VGG these green ones
are kind of the least efficient.
They have the biggest memory,
the most operations,
but they they do pretty well.
GoogleNet is the most efficient here.
It's way down on the operation side,
as well as a small little
circle for memory usage.
AlexNet, our earlier
model, has lowest accuracy.
It's relatively smaller compute, because
it's a smaller network, but
it's also not particularly
memory efficient.
And then ResNet here, we
have moderate efficiency.
It's kind of in the middle,
both in terms of memory
and operations, and it
has the highest accuracy.
And so here also are
some additional plots.
You can look at these
more on your own time,
but this plot on the left is
showing the forward pass time
and so this is in milliseconds
and you can up at the top
VGG forward passes about 200
milliseconds you can get about
five frames per second with this,
and this is sorted in order.
There's also this plot on
the right looking at power
consumption and if you look
more at this paper here,
there's further analysis of
these kinds of computational
comparisons.
So these were the main
architectures that you should
really know in-depth and be familiar with,
and be thinking about actively using.
But now I'm going just
to go briefly through
some other architectures
that are just good
to know either historical inspirations
or more recent areas of research.
So the first one Network in Network,
this is from 2014, and
the idea behind this
is that we have these
vanilla convolutional layers
but we also have these,
this introduces the idea of
MLP conv layers they call
it, which are micro networks
or basically network within networth, the
name of the paper.
Where within each conv
layer trying to stack an MLP
with a couple of fully
connected layers on top of
just the standard conv
and be able to compute
more abstract features for these local
patches right.
So instead of sliding
just a conv filter around,
it's sliding a slightly
more complex hierarchical
set of filters around
and using that to get the
activation maps.
And so, it uses these fully connected,
or basically one by one
conv kind of layers.
It's going to stack them all up like the
bottom diagram here where
we just have these networks
within networks stacked
in each of the layers.
And the main reason to know this is just
it was kind of a precursor
to GoogleNet and ResNet
in 2014 with this idea
of bottleneck layers
that you saw used very heavily in there.
And it also had a little bit
of philosophical inspiration
for GoogleNet for this idea
of a local network typology
network in network that they also used,
with a different kind of structure.
Now I'm going to talk
about a series of works,
on, or works since ResNet
that are mostly geared
towards improving resNet
and so this is more recent
research has been done since then.
I'm going to go over these pretty fast,
and so just at a very high level.
If you're interested in
any of these you should
look at the papers, to have more details.
So the authors of ResNet
a little bit later on
in 2016 also had this paper
where they improved the
ResNet block design.
And so they basically
adjusted what were the layers
that were in the ResNet block path,
and showed this new
structure was able to have
a more direct path in order
for propagating information
throughout the network,
and you want to have a good
path to propagate
information all the way up,
and then back up all the way down again.
And so they showed that this
new block was better for that
and was able to give better performance.
There's also a Wide Residual
networks which this paper
argued that while ResNets
made networks much deeper
as well as added these
residual connections
and their argument was
that residuals are really
the important factor.
Having this residual construction,
and not necessarily having
extremely deep networks.
And so what they did was they
used wider residual blocks,
and so what this means is
just more filters in every
conv layer.
So before we might have
F filters per layer
and they use these factors
of K and said well,
every layer it's going to be
F times K filters instead.
And so, using these
wider layers they showed
that their 50 layer wide
ResNet was able to out-perform
the 152 layer original ResNet,
and it also had the
additional advantages of
increasing with this,
even with the same amount
of parameters, tit's more
computationally efficient
because you can parallelize
these with operations
more easily.
Right just convolutions with more neurons
just spread across more kernels
as opposed to depth
that's more sequential,
so it's more computationally
efficient to increase
your width.
So here you can see
this work is starting to
trying to understand the
contributions of width
and depth and residual connections,
and making some arguments
for one way versus the other.
And this other paper around the same time,
I think maybe a little
bit later, is ResNeXt,
and so this is again,
the creators of ResNet
continuing to work on
pushing the architecture.
And here they also had
this idea of okay, let's
indeed tackle this width
thing more but instead of just
increasing the width
of this residual block
through more filters they have structure.
And so within each residual
block, multiple parallel
pathways and they're going to call
the total number of these
pathways the cardinality.
And so it's basically
taking the one ResNet block
with the bottlenecks and having
it be relatively thinner,
but having multiple of
these done in parallel.
And so here you can also
see that this both have some
relation to this idea of wide networks,
as well as to has some connection
to the inception module
as well right where we
have these parallel,
these layers operating in parallel.
And so now this ResNeXt has
some flavor of that as well.
So another approach
towards improving ResNets
was this idea called Stochastic
Depth and in this work
the motivation is well let's look more
at this depth problem.
Once you get deeper and
deeper the typical problems
that you're going to have
vanishing gradients right.
You're not able to, your
gradients will get smaller
and eventually vanish as
you're trying to back propagate
them over very long layers,
or a large number of layers.
And so what their motivation
is well let's try to have
short networks during training
and they use this idea
of dropping out a subset of
the layers during training.
And so for a subset of the
layers they just drop out
the weights and they just set
it to identity connection,
and now what you get is you
have these shorter networks
during training, you can pass back your
gradients better.
It's also a little more
efficient, and then it's
kind of like the drop out right.
It has this sort of flavor
that you've seen before.
And then at test time you want
to use the full deep network
that you've trained.
So these are some of the
works that looking at the
resident architecture, trying
to understand different
aspects of it and trying
to improve ResNet training.
And so there's also some
works now that are going
beyond ResNet that are
saying well what are some non
ResNet architectures that
maybe can also work better,
or comparable or better to ResNets.
And so one idea is
FractalNet, which came out
pretty recently, and the
argument in FractalNet
is that while residual
representations maybe
are not actually necessary,
so this goes back
to what we were talking about earlier.
What's the motivation of
residual networks and it seems
to make sense and there's, you know,
good reasons for why this
should help but in this paper
they're saying that well here
is a different architecture
that we're introducing, there's
no residual representations.
We think that the key is
more about transitioning
effectively from shallow to deep networks,
and so they have this fractal architecture
which has if you look on the right here,
these layers where they compose
it in this fractal fashion.
And so there's both
shallow and deep pathways
to your output.
And so they have these
different length pathways,
they train them with
dropping out sub paths,
and so again it has this
dropout kind of flavor,
and then at test time they'll
use the entire fractal network
and they show that this was able to
get very good performance.
There's another idea
called Densely Connected
convolutional Networks,
DenseNet, and this idea
is now we have these
blocks that are called
dense blocks.
And within each block
each layer is going to be
connected to every other layer after it,
in this feed forward fashion.
So within this block,
your input to the block
is also the input to
every other conv layer,
and as you compute each conv output,
those outputs are now connected to every
layer after and then,
these are all concatenated
as input to the conv
layer, and they do some
they have some other
processes for reducing
the dimensions and keeping efficient.
And so their main takeaway from this,
is that they argue that
this is alleviating
a vanishing gradient problem
because you have all of these
very dense connections.
It strengthens feature propagation
and then also encourages
future use right because
there are so many of these
connections each feature
map that you're learning
is input in multiple
later layers and being
used multiple times.
So these are just a
couple of ideas that are
you know alternatives or
what can we do that's not
ResNets and yet is still performing either
comparably or better to
ResNets and so this is
another very active area
of current research.
You can see that a lot of this is looking
at the way how different layers
are connected to each other
and how depth is managed
in these networks.
And so one last thing
that I wanted to mention
quickly, is just efficient networks.
So this idea of efficiency
and you saw that GoogleNet
was a work that was
looking into this direction
of how can we have efficient
networks which are important
for you know a lot of
practical usage both training
as well as especially
deployment and so this is
another recent network
that's called SqueezeNet
which is looking at
very efficient networks.
They have these things
called fire modules,
which consists of a
squeeze layer with a lot of
one by one filters and
then this feeds then into
an expand layer with one by
one and three by three filters,
and they're showing that with
this kind of architecture
they're able to get AlexNet
level accuracy on ImageNet,
but with 50 times fewer parameters,
and then you can further do
network compression on this
to get up to 500 times
smaller than AlexNet
and just have the whole
network just be 0.5 megs.
And so this is a direction
of how do we have
efficient networks model compression
that we'll cover more in a lecture later,
but just giving you a hint of that.
OK so today in summary we've
talked about different kinds
of CNN Architectures.
We looked in-depth at four
of the main architectures
that you'll see in wide usage.
AlexNet, one of the early,
very popular networks.
VGG and GoogleNet which
are still widely used.
But ResNet is kind of
taking over as the thing
that you should be
looking most when you can.
We also looked at these other networks
in a little bit more depth at a brief
level overview.
And so the takeaway that these
models that are available
they're in a lot of
[mumbles] so you can use them
when you need them.
There's a trend toward
extremely deep networks,
but there's also significant
research now around
the design of how do we connect layers,
skip connections, what
is connected to what,
and also using these to
design your architecture
to improve gradient flow.
There's an even more recent
trend towards examining
what's the necessity
of depth versus width,
residual connections.
Trade offs, what's
actually helping matters,
and so there's a lot of these recent works
in this direction that you can look into
some of the ones I pointed
out if you are interested.
And next time we'll talk about
Recurrent neural networks.