- Okay let's get started.
Alright, so welcome to lecture 14,
and today we'll be talking
about reinforcement learning.
So some administrative details first,
update on grades. Midterm grades were released last night, so
see Piazza for more information and statistics about that.
And we also have A2 and milestone grades
scheduled for later this week.
Also, about your projects, all teams
must register your projects.
So on Piazza we have a form posted, so you should go there and this is
required, every team should go and fill out this form with information
about your project, that we'll use for
final grading and the poster session.
And the Tiny ImageNet evaluation servers are also now online
for those of you who are doing the Tiny ImageNet challenge.
We also have a link to a course survey on
Piazza that was released a few days ago,
so, please fill it out if you guys haven't already. We'd love
to have your feedback and know how we can improve this class.
Okay, so the topic of today,
reinforcement learning.
Alright, so so far we've talked
about supervised learning,
which is about a type of problem where we have data x and then we have
labels y and our goal is to learn a function that is mapping from x to y.
So, for example, the classification
problem that we've been working with.
We also talked last lecture
about unsupervised learning,
which is the problem where we have just data and no labels, and our
goal is to learn some underlying, hidden structure of the data.
So, an example of this is the generative
models that we talked about last lecture.
And so today we're going to talk about a different kind
of problem set-up, the reinforcement learning problem.
And so here we have an agent
that can take actions in its environment,
and it can receive rewards
for for its action.
And its goal is going to be to learn how to take
actions in a way that can maximize its reward.
And so we'll talk about this
in a lot more detail today.
So, the outline for today, we're going to first
talk about the reinforcement learning problem,
and then we'll talk about
Markov decision processes,
which is a formalism of the
reinforcement learning problem,
and then we'll talk about two major classes of
RL algorithms, Q-learning and policy gradients.
So, in the reinforcement learning set up, what we
have is we have an agent and we have an environment.
And so the environment
gives the agent a state.
In turn, the agent is
going to take an action,
and then the environment is going to give
back a reward, as well as the next state.
And so this is going to keep going on in this loop, on and on, until the
environment gives back a terminal state, which then ends the episode.
So, let's see some examples of this.
First we have here the cart-pole problem,
which is a classic problem that some of you
may have seen, in, for example, 229 before.
And so this objective here is that you want
to balance a pole on top of a movable cart.
Alright, so the state that you have here
is your current description of the system.
So, for example, angular, angular speed of your pole,
your position, and the horizontal velocity of your cart.
And the actions you can take are horizontal
forces that you apply onto the cart, right?
So you're basically trying to move this cart
around to try and balance this pole on top of it.
And the reward that you're getting from this environment
is one at each time step if your pole is upright.
So you basically want to keep this pole
balanced for as long as you can.
Okay, so here's another example
of a classic RL problem.
Here is robot locomotion.
So we have here an example of a humanoid
robot, as well as an ant robot model.
And our objective here is to
make the robot move forward.
And so the state that we have describing our system is the
angle and the positions of all the joints of our robots.
And then the actions that we can take are
the torques applied onto these joints,
right, and so these are trying to make the robot
move forward and then the reward that we get is
our forward movement as well as, I think, in the time of, in the case of the humanoid, also,
you can have something like a reward of one for each time step that this robot is upright.
So, games are also a big class of
problems that can be formulated with RL.
So, for example, here we have Atari games
which are a classic success
of deep reinforcement learning
and so here the objective is to complete these
games with the highest possible score, right.
So, your agent is basically a player
that's trying to play these games.
And the state that you have is going to be
the raw pixels of the game state.
Right, so these are just the pixels on the screen
that you would see as you're playing the game.
And then the actions that you have are your game controls, so for
example, in some games maybe moving left to right, up or down.
And then the score that you have is your score increase or
decrease at each time step, and your goal is going to be
to maximize your total score over the course of the game. And, finally,
here we have another example of a game here. It's Go, which is
something that was a huge achievement of
deep reinforcement learning last year,
when Deep Minds AlphaGo beats Lee Sedol, which is
one of the best Go players of the last few years,
and this is actually in the news again for, as some of you may have seen, there's
another Go competition going on now with AlphaGo versus a top-ranked Go player.
And so the objective here is to win
the game, and our state is the position
of all the pieces, the action is where to put the next piece down, and the
reward is, one, if you win at the end of the game, and zero otherwise.
And we'll also talk about this one
in a little bit more detail, later.
Okay, so how can we mathematically
formalize the RL problem, right?
This loop that we talked about earlier,
of environments giving agents states,
and then agents taking actions.
So, a Markov decision process is the
mathematical formulation of the RL problem,
and an MDP satisfies the Markov property,
which is that the current state completely
characterizes the state of the world.
And an MDP here is defined
by tuple of objects,
consisting of S, which is
the set of possible states.
We have A, our set of possible actions,
we also have R, our distribution of
our reward, given a state, action pair,
so it's a function mapping from
state action to your reward.
You also have P, which is
a transition probability
distribution over your next state, that you're going
to transition to given your state, action pair.
And then finally we have a
Gamma, a discount factor,
which is basically saying how much we value
rewards coming up soon versus later on.
So, the way the Markov
Decision Process works is that
at our initial time step t equals zero,
the environment is going to sample some initial state as
zero, from the initial state distribution, p of s zero.
And then, once it has that, then from time t equals zero
until it's done, we're going to iterate through this loop
where the agent is going to
select an action, a sub t.
The environment is going to
sample a reward from here,
so reward given your state and the
action that you just took.
It's also going to sample the next state, at time
t plus one, given your probability distribution
and then the agent is going to receive the reward, as well as the
next state, and then we're going to through this process again,
and keep looping; agent will select the next
action, and so on until the episode is over.
Okay, so
now based on this, we
can define a policy pi,
which is a function from your states to your actions
that specifies what action to take in each state.
And this can be either
deterministic or stochastic.
And our objective now is to going to be to find your optimal
policy pi star, that maximizes your cumulative discounted reward.
So we can see here we have our some of our future rewards,
which can be also discounted by your discount factor.
So, let's look at an
example of a simple MDP.
And here we have Grid World, which is this
task where we have this grid of states.
So you can be in any of these
cells of your grid, which are your states.
And you can take actions from your states,
and so these actions are going to be simple movements,
moving to your right, to your left, up or down.
And you're going to get a negative reward for each transition or each
time step, basically, that happens. Each movement that you take,
and this can be something
like R equals negative one.
And so your objective is going to be to reach one of the terminal states,
which are the gray states shown here, in the least number of actions.
Right, so the longer that you take to reach your terminal state,
you're going to keep accumulating these negative rewards.
Okay, so if you look at
a random policy here,
a random policy would consist of, basically, at any given state or cell that you're
in just sampling randomly which direction that you're going to move in next.
Right, so all of these
have equal probability.
On the other hand, an optimal policy that
we would like to have is
basically taking the action, the direction
that will move us closest to a terminal state.
So you can see here, if we're right next to one of the terminal states we
should always move in the direction that gets us to this terminal state.
And otherwise, if you're in one of these other states, you want to
take the direction that will take you closest to one of these states.
Okay, so now given this description of our MDP, what we
want to do is we want to find our optimal policy pi star.
Right, our policy that's
maximizing the sum of the rewards.
And so this optimal policy is going to tell us, given any state that we're in, what is the
action that we should take in order to maximize the sum of the rewards that we'll get.
And so one question is how do we
handle the randomness in the MDP, right?
We have randomness in terms of our
initial state that we're sampling,
in therms of this transition probability distribution that
will give us distribution of our next states, and so on.
Also what we'll do is we'll work, then, with
maximizing our expected sum of the rewards.
So, formally, we can write our optimal policy pi star as maximizing this
expected sum of future rewards over policy's pi, where we have our initial state
sampled from our state distribution.
We have our actions,
sampled from our policy, given the state.
And then we have our next states sampled from
our transition probability distributions.
Okay, so before we talk about exactly
how we're going to find this policy,
let's first talk about a few definitions
that's going to be helpful for us in doing so.
So, specifically, the value function
and the Q-value function.
So, as we follow the policy, we're going to sample
trajectories or paths, right, for every episode.
And we're going to have our initial state as zero,
a-zero, r-zero, s-one, a-one, r-one, and so on.
We're going to have this trajectory of
states, actions, and rewards that we get.
And so, how good is a state
that we're currently in?
Well, the value function at any state s, is the expected cumulative reward following the policy from state s, from here
on out. Right, so it's going to be expected value of our expected cumulative reward, starting from our current state.
And then how good is a state, action pair?
So how good is taking action a in state s?
And we define this using
a Q-value function,
which is, the expected cumulative reward from taking
action a in state s and then following the policy.
Right, so then, the optimal Q-value function that we can get is going to be Q star, which is the
maximum expected cumulative reward that we can get from a given state action pair, defined here.
So now we're going to see one important thing in reinforcement
learning, which is called the Bellman equation.
So let's consider this a Q-value function
from the optimal policy Q star,
which is then going to
satisfy this Bellman equation,
which is this identity shown here,
and what this means is that
given any state, action pair, s and a, the
value of this pair is going to be the reward
that you're going to get, r, plus the value of whatever
state that you end up in. So, let's say, s prime.
And since we know that we have the optimal
policy, then we also know that we're going to
play the best action that we can,
right, at our state s prime.
And so then, the value at state s prime is
just going to be the maximum over our actions,
a prime, of Q star at s prime, a prime.
And so then we get this
identity here, for optimal Q-value.
Right, and then also, as always, we have this expectation here, because
we have randomness over what state that we're going to end up in.
And then we can also infer, from here, that our optimal policy, right, is going
to consist of taking the best action in any state, as specified by Q star.
Q star is going to tell us of the maximum future
reward that we can get from any of our actions,
so we should just take a policy that's following this and
just taking the action that's going to lead to best reward.
Okay, so how can we solve
for this optimal policy?
So, one way we can solve for this is something
called a value iteration algorithm,
where we're going to use this Bellman
equation as an iterative update.
So at each step, we're going to refine our approximation
of Q star by trying to enforce the Bellman equation.
And so, under some mathematical conditions, we also know that this sequence Q, i of
our Q-function is going to converge to our optimal Q star as i approaches infinity.
And so this, this works well,
but what's the problem with this?
Well, an important problem
is that this is not scalable.
Right?
We have to compute Q of s, a here for every state,
action pair in order to make our iterative updates.
Right, but then this is a problem if, for example, if we look at these the state of, for
example, an Atari game that we had earlier, it's going to be your screen of pixels.
And this is a huge state space, and it's basically computationally
infeasible to compute this for the entire state space.
Okay, so what's the solution to this? Well, we can
use a function approximator to estimate Q of s, a
so, for example, a neural network, right.
So, we've seen before that any time, if we have some really complex function that don't
know, that we want to estimate, a neural network is a good way to estimate this.
Okay, so this is going to take us to our formulation
of Q-learning that we're going to look at.
And so, what we're going to do is we're going to use a function
approximator in order to estimate our action value function.
Right?
And if this function approximator is a deep neural
network, which is what's been used recently,
then this is going to be
called deep Q-learning.
And so this is something that you'll hear around as one of the
common approaches to deep reinforcement learning that's in use.
Right, and so in this case, we also have our function parameters theta here, so our
Q-value function is determined by these weights, theta, of our neural network.
Okay, so given this function approximation,
how do we solve for our optimal policy?
So remember that we want to find a Q-function
that's satisfying the Bellman equation.
Right, and so we want to enforce this Bellman equation to happen, so what we
can do when we have this neural network approximating our Q-function is that
we can train this where our loss function is going to try
and minimize the error of our Bellman equation, right?
Or how far q of s, a is from its target,
which is the Y_i here, the right hand side
of the Bellman equation that we saw earlier.
So, we're basically going to take these forward passes
of our loss function, trying to minimize this error
and then our backward pass, our gradient update, is just going to be you just
take the gradient of this loss, with respect to our network parameter's theta.
Right, and so our goal is again to have this effect as we're taking gradient
steps of iteratively trying to make our Q-function closer to our target value.
So, any questions about this?
Okay.
So let's look at a case study of an example where one of the classic
examples of deep reinforcement learning where this approach was applied.
And so we're going to look at this problem that we saw earlier of playing Atari
games, where our objective was to complete the game with the highest score
and remember our state is going to be
the raw pixel inputs of the game state,
and we can take these actions of moving left, right,
up, down, or whatever actions of the particular game.
And our reward at each time step, we're going to get a reward of our score
increase or decrease that we got at this time step, and so our cumulative total
reward is this total reward that we'll
usually see at the top of the screen.
Okay, so the network that we're going to use for our
Q-function is going to look something like this,
right, where we have our
Q-network, with weight's theta.
And then our input, our state s, is
going to be our current game screen.
And in practice we're going to take a stack of
the last four frames, so we have some history.
And so we'll take these raw pixel values, we'll do some, you know, RGB to
gray-scale conversions, some down-sampling, some cropping, so, some pre-processing.
And what we'll get out of this is this 84 by
84 by four stack of the last four frames.
Yeah, question.
[inaudible question from audience]
Okay, so the question is, are we saying here that our network is going
to approximate our Q-value function for different state, action pairs,
for example, four of these?
Yeah, that's correct.
We'll see,
we'll talk about that in a few slides.
[inaudible question from audience]
So, no. So, we don't have a Softmax layer after the connected,
because here our goal is to directly predict our Q-value functions.
[inaudible question from audience] Q-values.
[inaudible question from audience]
Yes, so it's more doing
regression to our Q-values.
Okay, so we have our input to this network and then on top of this, we're going
to have a couple of familiar convolutional layers, and a fully-connected layer,
so here we have an eight-by-eight convolutions
and we have some four-by-four convolutions.
Then we have a FC 256 layer, so this is just a
standard kind of networK that you've seen before.
And then, finally, our last fully-connected layer has a vector of outputs, which is
corresponding to your Q-value for each action, right, given the state that you've input.
And so, for example, if you have four actions,
then here we have this four-dimensional output
corresponding to Q of current s, as well as
a-one, and then a-two, a-three, and a-four.
Right so this is going to be one
scalar value for each of our actions.
And then the number of actions that we have can vary
between, for example, 4 to 18, depending on the Atari game.
And one nice thing here is that
using this network structure,
a single feedforward pass is able to compute the
Q-values for all functions from the current state.
And so this is really efficient.
Right, so basically we take our current state in and then because we have this
output of an action for each, or Q-value for each action, as our output layer,
we're able to do one pass and
get all of these values out.
And then in order to train this, we're just
going to use our loss function from before.
Remember, we're trying to
enforce this Bellman equation
and so, on our forward pass, our loss function we're going to try and
iteratively make our Q-value close to our target value, that it should have.
And then our backward pass is just directly taking the gradient of this
loss function that we have and then taking a gradient step based on that.
So one other thing that's used here that I want
to mention is something called experience replay.
And so this addresses a problem with just using
the plain two network that I just described,
which is that learning from batches
of consecutive samples is bad.
And so the reason because of this, right, is so for just playing the game, taking samples of state
action rewards that we have and just taking consecutive samples of these and training with these,
well all of these samples are correlated and so
this leads to inefficient learning, first of all,
and also, because of this, our current Q-network parameters, right, this
determines the policy that we're going to follow, it determines our next
samples that we're going to get that
we're going to use for training.
And so this leads to problems where
you can have bad feedback loops.
So, for example, if currently the maximizing
action that's going to take left,
well this is going to bias all of my upcoming training
examples to be dominated by samples from the left-hand side.
And so this is a problem, right?
And so the way that we are going to address these problems is by using
something called experience replay, where we're going to keep this
replay memory table of transitions of state, as state, action,
reward, next state, transitions that we have, and we're going
to continuously update this table with new transitions that we're
getting as game episodes are played, as we're getting more experience.
Right, and so now what we can do is that we can now train our Q-network
on random, mini-batches of transitions from the replay memory.
Right, so instead of using consecutive samples, we're now going to sample
across these transitions that we've accumulated random samples of these,
and this breaks all of the, these
correlation problems that we had earlier.
And then also, as another side benefit is that each of these transitions
can also contribute to potentially multiple weight updates.
We're just sampling from this table and so
we could sample one multiple times.
And so, this is going to lead
also to greater data efficiency.
Okay, so let's put this all together and let's look at the
full algorithm for deep Q-learning with experience replay.
So we're going to start off with
initializing our replay memory
to some capacity that we choose, N, and then we're also going to
initialize our Q-network, just with our random weights or initial weights.
And then we're going to play M episodes, or full
games. This is going to be our training episodes.
And then what we're going to do is we're going to initialize our state,
using the starting game screen pixels at the beginning of each episode.
And remember, we go through the pre-processing
step to get to our actual input state.
And then for each time step
of a game that we're currently playing,
we're going to, with a small probability,
select a random action,
so one thing that's important in these
algorithms is to have sufficient exploration,
so we want to make sure that we are sampling
different parts of the state space.
And then otherwise, we're going to select from
the greedy action from the current policy.
Right, so most of the time we'll take the greedy action that we think is a good policy of the
type of actions that we want to take and states that we want to see, and with a small probability
we'll sample something random.
Okay, so then we'll take this action, a, t, and we'll observe
the next reward and the next state. So r, t and s, t plus one.
And then we'll take this and we'll store this
transition in our replay memory that we're building up.
And then we're going to take, we're
going to train a network a little bit.
So we're going to do experience replay
and we'll take a sample of a random mini-batches of transitions that we have
from the replay memory, and then we'll perform a gradient descent step on this.
Right, so this is going to
be our full training loop.
We're going to be continuously playing this game and then also sampling minibatches, using
experienced replay to update our weights of our Q-network and then continuing in this fashion.
Okay, so let's see. Let's see if I can, is this playing? Okay, so let's take a look at
this deep Q-learning algorithm from Google DeepMind, trained on an Atari game of Breakout.
Alright, so it's saying here that our input is
just going to be our state are raw game pixels.
And so here we're looking at what's
happening at the beginning of training.
So we've just started training a bit. And right, so it's going to look to it's learned
to kind of hit the ball, but it's not doing a very good job of sustaining it.
But it is looking for the ball.
Okay, so now after some more training,
it looks like a couple hours.
Okay, so now it's learning
to do a pretty good job here.
So it's able to continuously follow this ball
and be able to to remove most of the blocks.
Right, so after 240 minutes. Okay, so
here it's found the pro strategy, right?
You want to get all the way to the top
and then have it go by itself. Okay, so
this is an example of using deep Q-learning in order
to train an agent to be able to play Atari games.
It's able to do this on many Atari games and
so you can check out some more of this online.
Okay, so we've talked about Q-learning. But
there is a problem with Q-learning, right?
It can be challenging and what's the problem? Well, the
problem can be that the Q-function is very complicated.
Right, so we have to, we're saying that we want
to learn the value of every state action pair.
So, if, let's say you have something, for example,
a robot grasping, wanting to grasp an object.
Right, you're going to have a
really high dimensional state.
You have, I mean, let's say you have all of your
even just joint, joint positions, and angles.
Right, and so learning the exact value of every state action
pair that you have, right, can be really, really hard to do.
But on the other hand, your
policy can be much simpler.
Right, like what you want this robot to do maybe just to
have this simple motion of just closing your hand, right?
Just, move your fingers in this
particular direction and keep going.
And so, that leads to the question of
can we just learn this policy directly?
Right, is it possible, maybe, to just find the
best policy from a collection of policies,
without trying to go through this process of estimating
your Q-value and then using that to infer your policy.
So, this is an approach that oh, so, okay, this is an
approach that we're going to call policy gradients.
And so, formally, let's define a
class of parametrized policies.
Parametrized by weights theta,
and so for each policy
let's define the value of the policy.
So, J, our value J, given parameters theta, is going to be, or
expected some cumulative sum of future rewards that we care about.
So, the same reward that we've been using.
And so our goal then, under this setup
is that we want to find an optimal policy, theta star, which
is the maximum, right, arg max over theta of J of theta.
So we want to find the policy, the policy
parameters that gives our best expected reward.
So, how can we do this?
Any ideas?
Okay, well, what we can do is just a gradient
assent on our policy parameters, right?
We've learned that given some objective that we have,
some parameters we can just use gradient asscent
and gradient assent in order
to continuously improve our parameters.
And so let's talk more specifically about how we can do this,
which we're going to call here the reinforce algorithm.
So, mathematically, we can write out our expected future
reward over trajectories, and so we're going to sample
these trajectories of experience, right, like for example
episodes of game play that we talked about earlier.
S-zero, a-zero, r-zero, s-one,
a-one, r-one, and so on.
Using some policy pi of theta.
Right, and then so, for each trajectory we
can compute a reward for that trajectory.
It's the cumulative reward that we
got from following this trajectory.
And then the value of a policy, pi sub theta, is going to be just the expected
reward of these trajectories that we can get from the following pi sub theta.
So that's here, this expectation over trajectories that
we can get, sampling trajectories from our policy.
Okay.
So, we want to do gradient ascent, right?
So let's differentiate this.
Once we differentiate this, then we can
just take gradient steps, like normal.
So, the problem is that now if we try and just
differentiate this exactly, this is intractable, right?
So, the gradient of an expectation is problematic
when p is dependent on theta here, because here
we want to take this gradient
of p of tau, given theta,
but this is going to be, we want to take this
integral over tau. Right, so this is intractable.
However, we can use a trick
here to get around this.
And this trick is taking this gradient that we want, of
p. We can rewrite this by just multiplying this by one,
by multiplying top and bottom,
both by p of tau given theta.
Right, and then if we look at these terms that we have now here, in the way that I've written this, on the left and the
right, this is actually going to be equivalent to p of tau times our gradient with respect to theta, of log, of p.
Right, because the gradient of the log of p is
just going to be one over p times gradient of p.
Okay, so if we then inject this back into our
expression that we had earlier for this gradient,
we can see that, what this
will actually look like,
right, because now we have a gradient of log p times our probabilities of
all of these trajectories and then taking this integral here, over tau.
This is now going to be an expectation over our
trajectories tau, and so what we've done here
is that we've taken a
gradient of an expectation
and we've transformed it into
an expectation of gradients.
Right, and so now we can use sample trajectories
that we can get in order to estimate our gradient.
And so we do this using Monte Carlo sampling,
and this is one of the core ideas of reinforce.
Okay, so looking at this
expression that we want to compute,
can we compute these quantities that we had here
without knowing the transition probabilities?
Alright, so we have that p of tau is going
to be the probability of a trajectory.
It's going to be the product of all of our transition probabilities
of the next state that we get, given our current state and action
as well as our probability of the actions
that we've taken under our policy pi.
Right, so we're going to multiply all of these
together, and get our probability of our trajectory.
So this log of p of tau that we want to compute is going to be we just take
this log and this will separate this out into a sum of pushing the logs inside.
And then here, when we differentiate this, we can see we want to
differentiate with respect to theta, but this first term that we have here,
log p of the state transition probabilities
there's no theta term here, and so
the only place where we have theta is the second
term that we have, of log of pi sub theta,
of our action, given our state, and so this is the only term that we keep in our gradient
estimate, and so we can see here that this doesn't depend on the transition probabilities,
right, so we actually don't need to know our transition
probabilities in order to computer our gradient estimate.
And then, so, therefore when we're sampling these, for any given
trajectory tau, we can estimate J of theta using this gradient estimate.
This is here shown for a single trajectory
from what we had earlier,
and then we can also sample over multiple
trajectories to get the expectation.
Okay, so given this gradient estimator that we've derived,
the interpretation that we can make from this here, is that
if our reward for a trajectory is high, if the reward
that we got from taking the sequence of actions was good,
then let's push up the probabilities
of all the actions that we've seen.
Right, we're just going to say that
these were good actions that we took.
And then if the reward is low,
we want to push down these probabilities.
We want to say these were bad actions,
let's try and not sample these so much.
Right and so we can see that's what's happening here, where we have pi
of a, given s. This is the likelihood of the actions that we've taken
and then we're going to scale this, we're going to take the gradient and the gradient is going to tell
us how much should we change the parameters in order to increase our likelihood of our action, a, right?
And then we're going to take this and scale it by how much reward we
actually got from it, so how good were these actions, in reality.
Okay, so this might seem simplistic to say that, you know, if a trajectory
is good, then we're saying here that all of its actions were good. Right?
But, in expectation, this
actually averages out.
So we have an unbiased estimator here,
and so if you have many samples of this, then we
will get an accurate estimate of our gradient.
And this is nice because we can just take gradient steps and we know
that we're going to be improving our loss function and getting closer
to, at least some local optimum of our
policy parameters theta.
Alright, but there is a problem with this, and the
problem is that this also suffers from high variance.
Because this credit
assignment is really hard.
Right, we're saying that given a reward that we got, we're going
to say all of the actions were good, we're just going to hope
that this assignment of which actions were actually the best
actions, that mattered, are going to average out over time.
And so this is really hard and we need a lot
of samples in order to have a good estimate.
Alright, so this leads to the question of, is there anything
that we can do to reduce the variance and improve the estimator?
And so variance reduction is an important
area of research in policy gradients,
and in coming up with ways in order to improve
the estimator and require fewer samples.
Alright, so let's look at a couple
of ideas of how we can do this.
So given our gradient estimator,
so the first idea is that we can push up the probabilities of an
action only by it's affect on future rewards from that state, right?
So, now with instead of scaling this likelihood, or pushing up this
likelihood of this action by the total reward of its trajectory,
let's look more specifically at just the sum of rewards
coming from this time step on to the end, right?
And so, this is basically saying that how good an action is,
is only specified by how much future reward it generates.
Which makes sense.
Okay, so a second idea that we can also use is using a
discount factor in order to ignore delayed effects.
Alright so here we've added back in this discount
factor, that we've seen before, which is saying that
we are, you know, our discount factor's going to tell us how much we care about
just the rewards that are coming up soon, versus rewards that came much later on.
Right, so we were going to now say how good or bad an action is, looking more at the local neighborhood of action set it generates in the immediate near future
and down weighting the the
ones that come later on.
Okay so these are some straightforward
ideas that are generally used in practice.
So, a third idea is this idea of using a
baseline in order to reduce your variance.
And so, a problem with just using the
raw value of your trajectories, is that
this isn't necessarily meaningful, right?
So, for example, if your rewards are all positive, then you're just
going to keep pushing up the probabilities of all your actions.
And of course, you'll push
them up to various degrees,
but what's really important is whether a reward is better
or worse than what you're expecting to be getting.
Alright, so in order to address this, we can introduce
a baseline function that's dependent on the state.
Right, so this baseline function tell us what's, how much we, what's
our guess and what we expect to get from this state, and then
our reward or our scaling factor that we're going
to use to be pushing up or down our probabilities,
can now just be our expected sum of future rewards,
minus this baseline, so now it's the relative of how
much better or worse is the reward
that we got from what we expected.
And so how can we choose this baseline?
Well,
a very simple baseline, the
most simple you can use,
is just taking a moving average
of rewards that you've experienced so far.
So you can even do this overall trajectories, and this is just an average of what rewards
have I been seeing as I've been training, and as I've been playing these episodes?
Right, and so this gives some idea of whether the reward
that I currently get was relatively better or worse.
And so there's some variance on this that you can use but so far the variance reductions that
we've seen so far are all used in what's typically called "vanilla REINFORCE" algorithm.
Right, so looking at the cumulative future reward,
having a discount factor, and some simple baselines.
Now let's talk about how we can think about this idea
of baseline and potentially choose better baselines.
Right, so if we're going to think about
what's a better baseline that we can choose,
what we want to do is we want to push up the probability of an action from a state, if
the action was better than the expected value of what we should get from that state.
So, thinking about the value of what we're going to
expect from the state, what does this remind you of?
Does this remind you of anything that
we talked about earlier in this lecture?
Yes. [inaudible from audience]
Yeah, so the value functions, right?
The value functions that we talked about with Q-learning.
So, exactly. So Q-functions and value functions
and so, the intuition is that well, we're happy
with an action, taking an action in a state s, if
our Q-value of taking a specific
action from this state is larger than
the value function or expected value of the cumulative
future reward that we can get from this state.
Right, so this means that this action was better
than other actions that we could've taken.
And on the contrary, we're unhappy if this action, if
this value or this difference is negative or small.
Right, so now if we plug this in, in order to, as our scaling factor of how much we want
to push up or down, our probabilities of our actions, then we can get this estimator here.
Right, so, it's going to be
exactly the same as before, but now where
we've had before our cumulative expected reward, with our various reduction,
variance reduction techniques and baselines in, here we can just plug in now
this difference of how much better our current action was, based
on our Q-function minus our value function from that state.
Right, but what we talked about so far with our REINFORCE
algorithm, we don't know what Q and V actually are.
So can we learn these?
And the answer is yes, using Q-learning.
What we've already talked about before.
So we can combine policy gradients while we've
just been talking about, with Q-learning,
by training both an actor, which is the policy,
as well as a critic, right, a Q-function,
which is going to tell us how good we
think a state is, and an action in a state.
Right, so using this in approach, an actor
is going to decide which action to take
and then the critic, or Q-function, is going to tell the
actor how good its action was and how it should adjust.
And so, and this also alleviates a little bit of the
task of this critic compared to the Q-learning problems
that we talked about earlier of having to have this
learning a Q-value for every state, action pair,
because here it only has to learn this for the
state-action pairs that are generated by the policy.
It only needs to know this where it
matters for computing this scaling factor.
Right, and then we can also, as we're learning this, incorporate all of
the Q-learning tricks that we saw earlier, such as experience replay.
And so, now I'm also going to just
define this term that we saw earlier,
Q of s of a, how much, how good was an action in a given state, minus V of s?
Our expected value of how good the state is by this term advantage function.
Right, so the advantage function is how much
advantage did we get from playing this action?
How much better the
action was than expected.
So, using this, we can put together
our full actor-critic algorithm.
And so what this looks like,
is that we're going to start
off with by initializing our policy parameters theta,
and our critic parameters that we'll call phi.
And then for each, for iterations of training, we're going
to sample M trajectories, under the current policy.
Right, we're going to play our policy and get these
trajectories as s-zero, a-zero, r-zero, s-one and so on.
Okay, and then we're going to compute
the gradients that we want.
Right, so for each of these trajectories and in each time step, we're going to compute
this advantage function, and then we're going to use this advantage function, right?
And then we're going to use that in our gradient estimator that we showed
earlier, and accumulate our gradient estimate that we have for here.
And then we're also going to train our critic
parameters phi by exactly the same way,
so as we saw earlier, basically trying to enforce this
value function, right, to learn our value function,
which is going to be pulled into, just minimizing this advantage function and this
will encourage it to be closer to this Bellman equation that we saw earlier, right?
And so, this is basically just iterating between learning and
optimizing our policy function, as well as our critic function.
And so then we're going to update the gradients and then we're
going to go through and just continuously repeat this process.
Okay, so now let's look at
some examples of REINFORCE
in action, and let's look first here at something called
the Recurrent Attention Model, which is something that,
which is a model also referred to as hard attention, but you'll see
a lot in, recently, in computer vision tasks for various purposes.
Right, and so the idea behind this is here, I've talked about the original
work on hard attention, which is on image classification, and your goal is
to still predict the image class, but now you're going to
do this by taking a sequence of glimpses around the image.
You're going to look at local
regions around the image
and you're basically going to selectively focus on these
parts and build up information as you're looking around.
Right, and so the reason that we want to do this is, well, first of all
it has some nice inspiration from human perception in eye movement.
Let's say we're looking at a complex image and
we want to determine what's in the image.
Well, you know, we might, maybe look at a low-resolution of it first, and then look
specifically at parts of the image that will give us clues about what's in this image.
And then, this approach of just looking at, looking around at an image at
local regions, is also going to help you save computational resources, right?
You don't need to process the full image.
In practice, what usually happens is you look at a low-resolution image first, of a full image,
to decide how to get started, and then you look at high-res portions of the image after that.
And so this saves a lot of computational resources and you can think about, then, benefits of
this to scalability, right, being able to, let's say process larger images more efficiently.
And then, finally, this could also actually
help with actual classification performance,
because now you're able to ignore clutter
and irrelevant parts of the image.
Right? Like, you know, instead of always putting
through your ConvNet, all the parts of your image,
you can use this to, maybe, first prune out what are the relevant
parts that I actually want to process, using my ConvNet.
Okay, so what's the reinforcement learning
formulation of this problem?
Well, our state is going to be the glimpses that we've seen
so far, right? Our what's the information that we've seen?
Our action is then going to be where
to look next in the image.
Right, so in practice, this can be something like the x, y-coordinates, maybe
centered around some fixed-sized glimpse that you want to look at next.
And then the reward for the classification problem is going to be one, at the
final time step, if our image is correctly classified, and zero otherwise.
And so, because this glimpsing, taking these glimpses around the image is a
non-differentiable operation, this is why we need to use reinforcement learning formulation,
and learn policies for how to take these glimpse
actions and we can train this using REINFORCE.
So, given the state of glimpses so far, the core of our model is
going to be this RNN that we're going to use to model the state,
and then we're going to use our policy
parameters in order to output the next action.
Okay, so what this model looks like
is we're going to take an input image.
Right, and then we're going to take a glimpse at this image. So here,
this glimpse is the red box here, and this is all blank, zeroes.
And so we'll pass what we see so far into some neural network,
and this can be any kind of network depending on your task.
In the original experiments that I'm showing here, on MNIST, this is very
simple, so you can just use a couple of small, fully-connected layers,
but you can imagine for more complex images and
other tasks you may want to use fancier ConvNets.
Right, so you've passed this
into some neural network,
and then, remember I said we're also going to be integrating our state
of, glimpses that we've seen so far, using a recurrent network.
So, I'm just going to we'll see that later
on, but this is going to go through that,
and then it's going to output my x,
y-coordinates, of where I'm going to see next.
And in practice, this is going to be We
want to output a distribution over actions,
right, and so, what this is going to be it's going to be a
gaussian distribution and we're going to output the mean.
You can also output a mean and variance of this
distribution in practice. The variance can also be fixed.
Okay, so we're going to take this action that we're now going
to sample a specific x, y location from our action distribution
and then we're going to put this in to get the
next, extract the next glimpse from our image.
Right, so here we've moved to the end
of the two, this tail part of the two.
And so now we're actually starting to get
some signal of what we want to see, right?
Like, what we want to do is we want to look at the relevant
parts of the image that are useful for classification.
So we pass this through, again, our neural
network layers, and then also through
our recurrent network, right, that's taking this input as well as this previous hidden
state, and we're going to use this to get a, so this is representing our policy,
and then we're going to use this to output our distribution
for the next location that we want to glimpse at.
So we can continue doing this,
you can see in this next glimpse here,
we've moved a little bit more
toward the center of the two.
Alright, so it's probably learning that, you know, once I've seen this tail part of the two, that looks like this, maybe moving
in this upper left-hand direction will get you more towards a center, which will also have a value, valuable information.
And then we can keep doing this.
And then finally, at the end, at our last time step, so we can have a
fixed number of time steps here, in practice something like six or eight.
And then at the final time step, since we want
to do classification, we'll have our standard
Softmax layer that will produce a
distribution of probabilities for each class.
And then here the max class was a two,
so we can predict that this was a two.
Right, and so this is going to be the set up of
our model and our policy, and then we have our
estimate for the gradient of this policy that we've said earlier we could
compute by taking trajectories from here and using those to do back prop.
And so we can just do this in order to train this model and learn the
parameters of our policy, right? All of the weights that you can see here.
Okay, so here's an example of
a policies trained on MNIST,
and so you can see that, in general, from wherever it's starting, usually learns to go closer to where
the digit is, and then looking at the relevant parts of the digit, right? So this is pretty cool and
this you know, follows kind of
what you would expect, right,
if you were to choose places to look next in order
to most efficiently determine what digit this is.
Right, and so this idea of hard attention, of recurrent attention models,
has also been used in a lot of tasks in computer vision in the last
couple of years, so you'll see this, used,
for example, fine-grained image recognition.
So, I mentioned earlier that one of the
useful benefits of this can be also to
both save on computational efficiency as well as to ignore clutter
and irrelevant parts of the image, and when you have fine-grained
image classification problems,
you usually want both of these.
You want to keep high-resolution, so that you can look at, you know, important differences.
And then you also want to focus on these differences and ignore irrelevant parts.
Yeah, question.
[inaudible question from audience]
Okay, so yeah, so the question is how is there is computational
efficiency, because we also have this recurrent neural network in place.
So that's true, it depends on exactly what's your,
what is your problem, what is your network, and so on,
but you can imagine that if you had
some really hi- resolution image
and you don't want to process the entire parts of this image with some huge
ConvNet or some huge, you know, network, now you can get some savings by just
focusing on specific
smaller parts of the image.
You only process those parts of the image.
But, you're right, that it depends on
exactly what problem set-up you have.
This has also been used
in image captioning,
so if we're going to produce
an caption for an image,
we can choose, you know, we can have the image use
this attention model to generate this caption
and what it usually ends up learning is these policies
where it'll focus on specific parts of the image,
in sequence, and as it focuses on each part, it'll generate some words
or the part of the caption referring to that part of the image.
And then it's also been used, also
tasks such as visual question answering,
where we ask a question about the image and you want the model to
output some answer to your question, for example, I don't know,
how many chairs are around the table?
And so you can see how this attention mechanism might be a
good type of model for learning how to answer these questions.
Okay, so that was an example of policy
gradients in these hard attention models.
And so, now I'm going to talk about one more
example, that also uses policy gradients,
which is learning how to play Go.
Right, so DeepMind had this agent
for playing Go, called AlphGo,
that's been in the news a lot
in the past, last year and this year.
So, sorry?
[inaudible comment from audience]
And yesterday, yes, that's correct. So
this is very exciting, recent news as well.
So last year, a first version of AlphaGo was put into a competition against one of the best Go players
of recent years, Lee Sedol, and the agent was able to beat him four to one, in a game of five matches.
And actually, right now, just there's another match with Ke Jie, which is
current world number one, and so it's best of three in China right now.
And so the first game was yesterday.
AlphaGo won.
I think it was by just half a point, and so, so there's
two more games to watch. These are all live-stream, so
you guys, should also go online and watch these games.
It's pretty interesting to hear the commentary.
But, so what is this AlphaGo
agent, right, from DeepMind?
And it's based on a lot of what we've
talked about so far in this lecture.
And what it is it's a mixed of supervised
learning and reinforcement learning,
as well as a mix of some older methods for Go, Monte
Carlo Tree Search, as well as recent deep RL approaches.
So, okay, so how does AlphaGo
beat the Go world champion?
Well, what it first does is to train AlphaGo, what it takes as input is going to be a few featurization
of the board. So it's basically, right, your board and the positions of the pieces on the board.
That's your natural state representation.
And what they do in order to improve performance a
little bit is that they featurize this into some
more channels of one is all the different stone colors,
so this is kind of like your configuration of your board.
Also some channels, for example, where, which moves
are legal, some bias channels, some various things
and then, given this state, right,
it's going to first train a network
that's initialized with supervised
training from professional Go games.
So, given the current board configuration or features,
featurization of this, what's the correct next action to take?
Alright, so given examples of professional games
played, you know, just collected over time,
we can just take all of these professional Go moves, train a
standard, supervised mapping, from board state to action to take.
Alright, so they take this,
which is a pretty good start,
and then they're going to use this
to initialize a policy network.
Right, so policy network, it's just going to take the exact same structure of input
is your board state and your output is the actions that you're going to take.
And this was the set-up for the policy
gradients that we just saw, right?
So now we're going to just continue
training this using policy gradients.
And it's going to do this reinforcement learning training
by playing against itself for random, previous iterations.
So self play, and the reward it's going to get is
one, if it wins, and a negative one if it loses.
And what we're also going to do is we're also going to
learn a value network, so, something like a critic.
And then, the final AlphaGo is going to be combining all of these together, so policy and value networks
as well as with a Monte Carlo Tree Search algorithm, in order to select actions by look ahead search.
Right, so after putting all this together, a value of a node, of where you are in play, and what you do next, is going to be a
combination of your value function, as well as roll at outcome that you're computing from standard Monte Carlo Tree Search roll outs.
Okay, so, yeah, so this is basically
the various, the components of AlphaGo.
If you're interested in reading more about this,
there's a nature paper about this in 2016,
and they trained this, I think, over, the version of AlphaGo that's being used in these matches is,
like, I think a couple thousand CPUs plus a couple hundred GPUs, putting all of this together,
so it's a huge amount of
training that's going on, right.
And yeah, so you guys should, follow the
game this week. It's pretty exciting.
Okay, so in summary, today we've talked about
policy gradients, right, which are general.
They, you're just directly taking gradient
descent or ascent on your policy parameters,
so this works well for a large class of problems,
but it also suffers from high variance,
so it requires a lot of samples, and
your challenge here is sample efficiency.
We also talked about Q-learning, which doesn't
always work, it's harder to sometimes get it to work
because of this problem that we talked earlier where you are trying to compute this
exact state, action value for many, for very high dimensions, but when it does work,
for problems, for example, the Atari we saw earlier, then
it's usually more sample efficient than policy gradients.
Right, and one of the challenges in Q-learning is that you
want to make sure that you're doing sufficient exploration.
Yeah?
[inaudible question from audience]
Oh, so for Q-learning can you do this process where you're, okay,
where you're trying to start this off by some supervised training?
So, I guess the direct
approach for Q-learning doesn't
do that because you're
trying to regress to these
Q-values, right, instead of policy gradients over this distribution, but I think there are ways in which you can, like, massage this type
of thing to also bootstrap. Because I think bootstrapping in general or like behavior cloning is a good way to warm start these policies.
Okay, so, right, so we've talked about policy gradients
and Q-learning, and just another look at some of these,
some of the guarantees that you have,
right, with policy gradients.
One thing we do know that's really nice is that this
will always converge to a local minimum of J of theta,
because we're just directly doing gradient ascent, and so this is
often, and this local minimum is often just pretty good, right.
And in Q-learning, on the other hand, we don't have any
guarantees because here we're trying to approximate
this Bellman equation with a complicated function
approximator and so, in this case, this is the problem
with Q-learning being a little bit trickier to train
in terms of applicability to a wide range of problems.
Alright, so today you got basically very, brief, kind of high-level overview
of reinforcement learning and some major classes of algorithms in RL.
And next time we're going to have a guest
lecturer from, Song Han, who's done a lot
of pioneering work in model compression
and energy efficient deep learning,
and so he's going to talk some
of this, about some of this.
Thank you.