- Okay, sounds like it is.
I'll be telling you about
adversarial examples
and adversarial training today.
Thank you.
As an overview, I will
start off by telling you
what adversarial examples are,
and then I'll explain why they happen,
why it's possible for them to exist.
I'll talk a little bit about
how adversarial examples
pose real world security threats,
that they can actually
be used to compromise
systems built on machine learning.
I'll tell you what the
defenses are so far,
but mostly defenses are
an open research problem
that I hope some of you
will move on to tackle.
And then finally I'll tell you
how to use adversarial examples
to improve other machine
learning algorithms
even if you want to build a
machine learning algorithm
that won't face a real world adversary.
Looking at the big picture and
the context for this lecture,
I think most of you are probably here
because you've heard
how incredibly powerful
and successful machine learning is,
that very many different tasks
that could not be solved
with software before
are now solvable thanks to deep learning
and convolutional networks
and gradient descent.
All of these technologies
that are working really well.
Until just a few years ago,
these technologies didn't really work.
In about 2013, we started to see
that deep learning achieved
human level performance
at a lot of different tasks.
We saw that convolutional nets
could recognize objects and images
and score about the same as
people in those benchmarks,
with the caveat that
part of the reason that
algorithms score as well as people
is that people can't tell
Alaskan Huskies from
Siberian Huskies very well,
but modulo the strangeness
of the benchmarks
deep learning caught up to
about human level performance
for object recognition in about 2013.
That same year, we also
saw that object recognition
applied to human faces caught
up to about human level.
That suddenly we had computers
that could recognize
faces about as well as
you or I could recognize
faces of strangers.
You can recognize the faces
of your friends and family
better than a computer,
but when you're dealing
with people that you haven't
had a lot of experience with
the computer caught up
to us in about 2013.
We also saw that computers caught up
to humans for reading type
written fonts in photos
in about 2013.
It even got the point that we
could no longer use CAPTCHAs
to tell whether a user of
a webpage is human or not
because the convolutional network
is better at reading obfuscated
text than a human is.
So with this context today
of deep learning working really well
especially for computer vision
it's a little bit unusual to think about
the computer making a mistake.
Before about 2013,
nobody was ever surprised
if the computer made a mistake.
That was the rule not the exception,
and so today's topic which is all about
unusual mistakes that deep
learning algorithms make
this topic wasn't really
a serious avenue of study
until the algorithms started
to work well most of the time,
and now people study
the way that they break
now that that's actually the
exception rather than the rule.
An adversarial example is an example
that has been carefully
computed to be misclassified.
In a lot of cases we're
able to make the new image
indistinguishable to a human observer
from the original image.
Here, I show you one where
we start with a panda.
On the left this is a panda
that has not been modified in any way,
and the convolutional
network trained on the image
in that dataset is able to
recognize it as being a panda.
One interesting thing is that the model
doesn't have a whole lot of
confidence in that decision.
It assigns about 60% probability
to this image being a panda.
If we then compute exactly the way
that we could modify the image
to cause the convolutional
network to make a mistake
we find that the optimal direction
to move all the pixels is given
by this image in the middle.
To a human it looks a lot like noise.
It's not actually noise.
It's carefully computed as a function
of the parameters of the network.
There's actually a lot of structure there.
If we multiply that image
of the structured attack
by a very small coefficient and
add it to the original panda
we get an image that a human can't tell
from the original panda.
In fact, on this slide
there is no difference
between the panda on the left
and the panda on the right.
When we present the image
to convolutional network
we use 32-bit floating point values.
The monitor here can
only display eight bits
of color resolution, and
we have made a change
that's just barely too small
to affect the smallest
of those eight bits,
but it effects the other 24
of the 32-bit floating
point representation,
and that little tiny change is enough
to fool the convolutional network
into recognizing this image
of a panda as being a gibbon.
Another interesting thing is that
it doesn't just change the class.
It's not that we just barely
found the decision boundary
and just barely stepped across it.
The convolutional network
actually has much more confidence
in its incorrect prediction,
that the image on the right is a gibbon,
than it had for the
original being a panda.
On the right, it believes that the image
is a gibbon with 99.9% probability,
so before it thought that there was about
1/3 chance that it was
something other than a panda,
and now it's about as
certain as it can possibly be
that it's a gibbon.
As a little bit of history,
people have studied ways
of computing attacks to fool
different machine learning models
since at least about
2004, and maybe earlier.
For a long time this
was done in the context
of fooling spam detectors.
In about 2013, Battista Biggio found
that you could fool neural
networks in this way,
and around the same time my
colleague, Christian Szegedy,
found that you could
make this kind of attack
against deep neural networks
just by using an optimization algorithm
to search on the input of the image.
A lot of what I'll be
telling you about today
is my own follow-up work on this topic,
but I've spent a lot of my
career over the past few years
understanding why these
attacks are possible
and why it's so easy to fool
these convolutional networks.
When my colleague, Christian,
first discovered this phenomenon
independently from Battista
Biggio but around the same time,
he found that it was actually a result
of a visualization he was trying to make.
He wasn't studying security.
He wasn't studying how
to fool a neural network.
Instead, he had a convolutional network
that could recognize objects very well,
and he wants to understand how it worked,
so he thought that maybe he
could take an image of a scene,
for example a picture of a ship,
and he could gradually
transform that image
into something that the
network would recognize
as being an airplane.
Over the course of that transformation,
he could see how the
features of the input change.
You might expect that maybe the background
would turn blue to look like
the sky behind an airplane,
or you might expect that the ship
would grow wings to look
more like an airplane.
You could conclude from
that that the convolution
uses the blue sky or uses the
wings to recognize airplanes.
That's actually not really
what happened at all.
Each of these panels
here shows an animation
that you read left to
right, top to bottom.
Each panel is another
step of gradient ascent
on the log probability that
the input is an airplane
according to a convolutional net model,
and then we follow the gradient
on the input to the image.
You're probably used to
following the gradient
on the parameters of a model.
You can use the back propagation algorithm
to compute the gradient on the input image
using exactly the same procedure
that you would use to compute the gradient
on the parameters.
In this animation of the
ship in the upper left,
we see five panels that all
look basically the same.
Gradient descent doesn't seem
to have moved the image at all,
but by the last panel the
network is completely confident
that this is an airplane.
When you first code up
this kind of experiment,
especially if you don't
know what's going to happen,
it feels a little bit like
you have a bug in your script
and you're just displaying
the same image over and over again.
The first time I did it,
I couldn't believe it was happening,
and I had to open up the images in NumPy,
and take the difference of them,
and make sure that there was actually
a non-zero difference
in there, but there is.
I show several different animations here
of a ship, a car, a cat, and a truck.
The only one where I actually
see any change at all
is the image of the cat.
The color of the cat's
face changes a little bit,
and maybe it becomes a little bit more
like the color of a metal airplane.
Other than that, I don't see any changes
in any of these animations,
and I don't see anything very
suggestive of an airplane.
So gradient descent, rather
than turning the input
into an example of an airplane,
has found an image that fools the network
into thinking that the
input is an airplane.
And if we were malicious attackers
we didn't even have to work
very hard to figure out
how to fool the network.
We just asked the network
to give us an image of an airplane,
and it gave us something
that fools it into thinking
that the input is an airplane.
When Christian first published this work,
a lot of articles came
out with titles like,
The Flaw Looking At Every
Deep Neural Network,
or Deep Learning has Deep Flaws.
It's important to remember
that these vulnerabilities
apply to essentially every
machine learning algorithm
that we've studied so far.
Some of them like RBF networks
and partisan density estimators
are able to resist this effect somewhat,
but even very simple
machine learning algorithms
are highly vulnerable
to adversarial examples.
In this image, I show an animation
of what happens when we
attack a linear model,
so it's not a deep algorithm at all.
It's just a shallow softmax model.
You multiply by a matrix, you
add a vector of bias terms,
you apply the softmax function,
and you've got your
probability distribution
over the 10 MNIST classes.
At the upper left, I start
with an image of a nine,
and then as we move left
to right, top to bottom,
I gradually transform it to be a zero.
Where I've drawn the yellow box,
the model assigns high
probability to it being a zero.
I forget exactly what my threshold
was for high probability,
but I think it was around 0.9 or so.
Then as we move to the second row,
I transform it into a one,
and the second yellow box indicates
where we've successfully fooled the model
into thinking it's a one
with high probability.
And then as you read the
rest of the yellow boxes
left to right, top to bottom,
we go through the twos,
threes, fours, and so on,
until finally at the lower right
we have a nine that has
a yellow box around it,
and it actually looks like a nine,
but in this case the only reason
it actually looks like a nine
is that we started the
whole process with a nine.
We successfully swept through
all 10 classes of MNIST
without substantially changing
the image of the digit
in any way that would interfere
with human recognition.
This linear model was actually
extremely easy to fool.
Besides linear models, we've also seen
that we can fool many different
kinds of linear models
including logistic regression and SVMs.
We've also found that we
can fool decision trees,
and to a lesser extent,
nearest neighbors classifiers.
We wanted to explain
exactly why this happens.
Back in about 2014, after we'd
published the original paper
where we'd said that these problems exist,
we were trying to figure
out why they happen.
When we wrote our first paper,
we thought that basically
this is a form of overfitting,
that you have a very
complicated deep neural network,
it learns to fit the training set,
its behavior on the test
set is somewhat undefined,
and then it makes random mistakes
that an attacker can exploit.
Let's walk through what
that story looks like
somewhat concretely.
I have here a training
set of three blue X's
and three green O's.
We want to make a classifier
that can recognize X's and recognize O's.
We have a very complicated classifier
that can easily fit the training set,
so we represent everywhere it believes
X's should be with blobs of blue color,
and I've drawn a blob of blue
around all of the training set X's,
so it correctly classifies
the training set.
It also has a blob of green
mass showing where the O's are,
and it successfully fits all
of the green training set O's,
but then because this is a
very complicated function
and it has just way more parameters
than it actually needs to
represent the training task,
it throws little blobs of probability mass
around the rest of space randomly.
On the left there's a blob of green space
that's kind of near the training set X's,
and I've drawn a red X there to show
that maybe this would be
an adversarial example
where we expect the
classification to be X,
but the model assigns O.
On the right, I've shown
that there's a red O
where we have another adversarial example.
We're very near the other O's.
We might expect the model to
assign this class to be an O,
and yet because it's drawn blue mass there
it's actually assigning it to be an X.
If overfitting is really the story
then each adversarial
example is more or less
the result of bad luck and
also more or less unique.
If we fit the model again
or we fit a slightly different model
we would expect to make
different random mistakes
on this points that are
off the training set,
but that was actually
not what we found at all.
We found that many different
models would misclassify
the same adversarial examples,
and they would assign
the same class to them.
We also found that if
we took the difference
between an original example
and an adversarial example
then we had a direction in input space
and we could add that same offset vector
to any clean example, and
we would almost always
get an adversarial example as a result.
So we started to realize
that there was systematic
effect going on here,
not just a random effect.
That led us to another idea
which is that adversarial examples
might actually be more like underfitting
rather than overfitting.
They might actually come from
the model being too linear.
Here I draw the same task again
where we have the same manifold of O's
and the same line of X's,
and this time I fit a
linear model to the data set
rather than fitting a high
capacity, non-linear model to it.
We see that we get a dividing hyperplane
running in between the two classes.
This hyperplane doesn't really capture
the true structure of the classes.
The O's are clearly arranged
in a C-shaped manifold.
If we keep walking past
the end of the O's,
we've crossed the decision
boundary and we've drawn a red O
where even though we're very
near the decision boundary
and near other O's we
believe that it is now an X.
Similarly we can take
steps that go from near X's
to just over the line that
are classified as O's.
Another thing that's somewhat
unusual about this plot
is that if we look at the lower
left or upper right corners
these corners are very
confidently classified
as being X's on the lower
left or O's on the upper right
even though we've never seen
any data over there at all.
The linear model family forces the model
to have very high
confidence in these regions
that are very far from
the decision boundary.
We've seen that linear
models can actually assign
really unusual confidence
as you move very far
from the decision boundary,
even if there isn't any data there,
but are deep neural networks actually
anything like linear models?
Could linear models
actually explain anything
about how it is that
deep neural nets fail?
It turns out that modern deep neural nets
are actually very piecewise linear,
so rather than being a
single linear function
they are piecewise linear
with maybe not that many linear pieces.
If we use rectified linear units
then the mapping from the input
image to the output logits
is literally a piecewise linear function.
By the logits I mean the
un-normalized log probabilities
before we apply the softmax
op at the output of the model.
There are other neural networks
like maxout networks that are also
literally piecewise linear.
And then there are several
that become very close to it.
Before rectified linear
units became popular
most people used to use sigmoid
units of one form or another
either logistic sigmoid or
hyperbolic tangent units.
These sigmoidal units have
to be carefully tuned,
especially at initialization
so that you spend most of your time
near the center of the sigmoid
where the sigmoid is approximately linear.
Then finally, the LSTM, a
kind of recurrent network
that is one of the most popular
recurrent networks today,
uses addition from one
time step to the next
in order to accumulate and
remember information over time.
Addition is a particularly
simple form of linearity,
so we can see that the interaction
from a very distant time step
in the past and the present
is highly linear within an LSTM.
Now to be clear, I'm
speaking about the mapping
from the input of the model
to the output of the model.
That's what I'm saying
is close to being linear
or is piecewise linear
with relatively few pieces.
The mapping from the
parameters of the network
to the output of the network is non-linear
because the weight matrices
at each layer of the network
are multiplied together.
So we actually get extremely
non-linear reactions
between parameters and the output.
That's what makes training a
neural network so difficult.
But the mapping from
the input to the output
is much more linear and predictable,
and it means that optimization problems
that aim to optimize
the input to the model
are much easier than optimization problems
that aim to optimize the parameters.
If we go and look for
this happening in practice
we can take a convolutional network
and trace out a one-dimensional path
through its input space.
So what we're doing here is
we're choosing a clean example.
It's an image of a white
car on a red background,
and we are choosing a direction
that will travel through space.
We are going to have a coefficient epsilon
that we multiply by this direction.
When epsilon is negative 30,
like at the left end of the plot,
we're subtracting off a lot
of this unit vector direction.
When epsilon is zero, like
in the middle of the plot,
we're visiting the original
image from the data set,
and when epsilon is positive 30,
like at the right end of the plot,
we're adding this
direction onto the input.
In the panel on the left,
I show you an animation
where we move from
epsilon equals negative 30
as up to epsilon equals positive 30.
You read the animation left
to right, top to bottom,
and everywhere that there's a yellow box
the input has correctly
recognized as being a car.
On the upper left, you see
that it looks mostly blue.
On the lower right, it's
hard to tell what's going on.
It's kind of reddish and so on.
In the middle row, just after
where the yellow boxes end
you can see pretty clearly
that it's a car on a red background,
though the image is small on these slides.
What's interesting to
look at here is the logits
that the model outputs.
This is a deep convolutional
rectified linear unit network.
Because it uses rectified linear units,
we know that the output is
a piecewise linear function
of the input to the model.
The main question we're
asking by making this plot
is how many different pieces
does this piecewise linear function have
if we look at one
particular cross section.
You might think that maybe a deep net
is going to represent some extremely
wiggly complicated
function with lots and lots
of linear pieces no matter
which cross section you look in.
Or we might find that it
has more or less two pieces
for each function we look at.
Each of the different curves on this plot
is the logits for a different class.
We see that out at the tails of the plot
that the frog class is the most likely,
and the frog class basically looks like
a big v-shaped function.
The logits for the frog
class become very high
when epsilon is negative
30 or positive 30,
and they drop down and
become a little bit negative
when epsilon is zero.
The car class, listed as automobile here,
it's actually high in the middle,
and the car is correctly recognized.
As we sweep out to very negative epsilon,
the logits for the car class do increase,
but they don't increase nearly as quickly
as the logits for the frog class.
So, we've found a direction
that's associated with the frog class
and as we follow it out to a
relatively large perturbation,
we find that the model
extrapolates linearly
and begins to make a very
unreasonable prediction
that the frog class is extremely likely
just because we've moved for a long time
in this direction that
was locally associated
with the frog class being more likely.
When we actually go and
construct adversarial examples,
we need to remember that we're able to get
quite a large perturbation
without changing the image very much
as far as a human being is concerned.
So here I show you a
handwritten digit three,
and I'm going to change it
in several different ways,
and all of these changes have
the same L2 norm perturbation.
In the top row, I'm going to
change the three into a seven
just by looking for the nearest
seven in the training set.
The difference between those two
is this image that looks a
little bit like the seven
wrapped in some black lines.
So here white pixels in the middle image
in the perturbation column,
the white pixels
represent adding something
and black pixels represent
subtracting something
as you move from the left
column to the right column.
So when we take the three and
we apply this perturbation
that transforms it into a seven,
we can measure the L2
norm of that perturbation.
And it turns out to
have an L2 norm of 3.96.
That gives you kind of a reference
for how big these perturbations can be.
In the middle row, we apply a perturbation
of exactly the same size,
but with the direction chosen randomly.
In this case we don't actually change
the class of the three at all,
we just get some random noise
that didn't really change the class.
A human could still easily
read it as being a three.
And then finally at the very bottom row,
we take the three and we
just erase a piece of it
with a perturbation of the same norm
and we turn it into something
that doesn't have any class at all.
It's not a three, it's not a seven,
it's just a defective input.
All of these changes can happen
with the same L2 norm perturbation.
And actually a lot of the time
with adversarial examples,
you make perturbations that
have an even larger L2 norm.
What's going on is that
there are several different
pixels in the image,
and so small changes to individual pixels
can add up to relatively large vectors.
For larger datasets like ImageNet,
where there's even more pixels,
you can make very small
changes to each pixel
that travel very far in vector space
as measured by the L2 norm.
That means that you can
actually make changes
that are almost imperceptible
but actually move you really far
and get a large dot product
with the coefficients
of the linear function
that the model represents.
It also means that when
we're constructing adversarial examples,
we need to make sure that the
adversarial example procedure
isn't able to do what happened
in the top row of this slide here.
So in the top row of this slide,
we took the three and we actually
just changed it into a seven.
So when the model says that the image
in the upper right is a
seven, it's not a mistake.
We actually just changed the input class.
When we build adversarial examples,
we want to make sure that
we're measuring real mistakes.
If we're experimenters studying
how easy a network is to fool,
we want to make sure that
we're actually fooling it
and not just changing the input class.
And if we're an attacker, we
actually want to make sure
that we're causing
misbehavior in the system.
To do that, when we build
adversarial examples,
we use the maxnorm to
constrain the perturbation.
Basically this says
that no pixel can change
by more than some amount epsilon.
So the L2 norm can get really big,
but you can't concentrate all the changes
for that L2 norm to erase
pieces of the digit,
like in the bottom row here
we erased the top of a three.
One very fast way to build
an adversarial example
is just to take the gradient of the cost
that you used to train the network
with respect to the input,
and then take the sign of that gradient.
The sign is essentially
enforcing the maxnorm constraint.
You're only allowed to change the input by
up to epsilon at each pixel,
so if you just take the sign it tells you
whether you want to add
epsilon or subtract epsilon
in order to hurt the network.
You can view this as
taking the observation
that the network is more or less linear,
as we showed on this slide,
and using that to motivate
building a first order
Taylor series approximation
of the neural network's cost.
And then subject to that
Taylor series approximation,
we want to maximize the cost
following this maxnorm constraint.
And that gives us this
technique that we call
the fast gradient sign method.
If you want to just get your hands dirty
and start making adversarial
examples really quickly,
or if you have an algorithm
where you want to train
on adversarial examples in
the inner loop of learning,
this method will make
adversarial examples for you
very, very quickly.
In practice you should
also use other methods,
like Nicholas Carlini's attack based on
multiple steps of the Adam optimizer,
to make sure that you
have a very strong attack
that you bring out when
you think you have a model
that might be more powerful.
A lot of the time people
find that they can defeat
the fast gradient sign method
and think that they've
built a successful defense,
but then when you bring
out a more powerful method
that takes longer to evaluate,
they find that they can't overcome
the more computationally expensive attack.
I've told you that
adversarial examples happen
because the model is very linear.
And then I told you that we could
use this linearity assumption
to build this attack, the
fast gradient sign method.
This method, when applied
to a regular neural network
that doesn't have any special defenses,
will get over a 99% attack success rate.
So that seems to confirm, somewhat,
this hypothesis that adversarial examples
come from the model being far too linear
and extrapolating in linear
fashions when it shouldn't.
Well we can actually go
looking for some more evidence.
My friend David Warde-Farley
and I built these maps
of the decision boundaries
of neural networks.
And we found that they are consistent
with the linearity hypothesis.
So the FGSM is that attack method
that I described in the previous slide,
where we take the sign of the gradient.
We'd like to build a map
of a two-dimensional cross
section of input space
and show which classes are assigned
to the data at each point.
In the grid on the right,
each different cell,
each little square within the grid,
is a map of a CIFAR-10
classifier's decision boundary,
with each cell
corresponding to a different
CIFAR-10 testing sample.
On the left I show you a little legend
where you can understand
what each cell means.
The very center of each
cell corresponds to
the original example
from the CIFAR-10 dataset
with no modification.
As we move left to right in the cell,
we're moving in the direction
of the fast gradient sign method attack.
So just the sign of the gradient.
As we move up and down within the cell,
we're moving in a random
direction that's orthogonal to
the fast gradient sign method direction.
So we get to see a cross
section, a 2D cross section
of CIFAR-10 decision space.
At each pixel within this map,
we plot a color that tells us
which class is assigned there.
We use white pixels to indicate that
the correct class was chosen,
and then we used different
colors to represent
all of the other incorrect classes.
You can see that in nearly all
of the grid cells on the right,
roughly the left half
of the image is white.
So roughly the left half of the image
has been correctly classified.
As we move to the right, we
see that there is usually
a different color on the right half.
And the boundaries between these regions
are approximately linear.
What's going on here is that
the fast gradient sign method
has identified a direction
where if we get a large dot
product with that direction
we can get an adversarial example.
And from this we can see
that adversarial examples
live more or less in linear subspaces.
When we first discovered
adversarial examples,
we thought that they might
live in little tiny pockets.
In the first paper we
actually speculated that
maybe they're a little bit
like the rational numbers,
hiding out finely tiled
among the real numbers,
with nearly every real number
being near a rational number.
We thought that because
we were able to find
an adversarial example corresponding
to every clean example that
we loaded into the network.
After doing this further analysis,
we found that what's happening
is that every real example
is near one of these
linear decision boundaries
where you cross over into
an adversarial subspace.
And once you're in that
adversarial subspace,
all the other points nearby
are also adversarial examples
that will be misclassified.
This has security implications
because it means you only need
to get the direction right.
You don't need to find an
exact coordinate in space.
You just need to find a direction
that has a large dot product
with the sign of the gradient.
And once you move more
or less approximately
in that direction, you can fool the model.
We also made another cross section
where after using the left-right axis
as the fast gradient sign method,
we looked for a second direction
that has high dot
product with the gradient
so we could make both axes adversarial.
And in this case you see that we get
linear decision boundaries.
They're now oriented diagonally
rather than vertically,
but you can see that there's actually
this two-dimensional subspace
of adversarial examples
that we can cross into.
Finally it's important to remember
that adversarial examples are not noise.
You can add a lot of noise
to an adversarial example
and it will stay adversarial.
You can add a lot of
noise to a clean example
and it will stay clean.
Here we make random cross sections
where both axes are
randomly chosen directions.
And you see that on CIFAR-10,
most of the cells are completely white,
meaning that they're correctly
classified to start with,
and when you add noise they
stay correctly classified.
We also see that the
model makes some mistakes
because this is the test set.
And generally if a test example
starts out misclassified,
adding the noise doesn't change it.
There are a few exceptions where,
if you look in the
third row, third column,
noise actually can make the
model misclassify the example
for especially large noise values.
And there's even some where,
in the top row there's one
example you can see where
the model is misclassifying
the test example to start with
but then noise can change it
to be correctly classified.
For the most part, noise
has very little effect
on the classification decision
compared to adversarial examples.
What's going on here is that
in high dimensional spaces,
if you choose some reference vector
and then you choose a random vector
in that high dimensional space,
the random vector will, on average,
have zero dot product
with the reference vector.
So if you think about making
a first order Taylor series
approximation of your cost,
and thinking about how your
Taylor series approximation
predicts that random vectors
will change your cost.
You see that random vectors on average
have no effect on the cost.
But adversarial examples
are chosen to maximize it.
In these plots we looked
in two dimensions.
More recently, Florian
Tramer here at Stanford
got interested in finding out
just how many dimensions
there are to these subspaces
where the adversarial examples
lie in a thick contiguous region.
And we came up with an algorithm together
where you actually look for
several different orthogonal vectors
that all have a large dot
product with the gradient.
By looking in several different
orthogonal directions simultaneously,
we can map out this kind of polytope
where many different
adversarial examples live.
We found out that this adversarial region
has on average about 25 dimensions.
If you look at different
examples you'll find
different numbers of
adversarial dimensions.
But on average on MNIST
we found it was about 25.
So what's interesting
here is the dimensionality
actually tells you something about
how likely you are to find
an adversarial example
by generating random noise.
If every direction were adversarial,
then any change would
cause a misclassification.
If most of the directions
were adversarial,
then random directions would
end up being adversarial
just by accident most of the time.
And then if there was only
one adversarial direction,
you'd almost never find that direction
just by adding random noise.
When there's 25 you have a
chance of doing it sometimes.
Another interesting thing
is that different models
will often misclassify the
same adversarial examples.
The subspace dimensionality
of the adversarial subspace
relates to that transfer property.
The larger the dimensionality
of the subspace,
the more likely it is that the subspaces
for two models will intersect.
So if you have two different models
that have a very large
adversarial subspace,
you know that you can probably transfer
adversarial examples
from one to the other.
But if the adversarial
subspace is very small,
then unless there's some kind
of really systematic effect
forcing them to share
exactly the same subspace,
it seems less likely that
you'll be able to transfer
examples just due to the
subspaces randomly aligning.
A lot of the time in
the adversarial example
research community,
we refer back to the story of Clever Hans.
This comes from an essay
by Bob Sturm called
Clever Hans, Clever Algorithms.
Because Clever Hans is
a pretty good metaphor
for what's happening with
machine learning algorithms.
So Clever Hans was a horse
that lived in the early 1900s.
His owner trained him to
do arithmetic problems.
So you could ask him, "Clever Hans,
"what's two plus one?"
And he would answer by tapping his hoof.
And after the third tap,
everybody would start
cheering and clapping and looking excited
because he'd actually done
an arithmetic problem.
Well it turned out that
he hadn't actually
learned to do arithmetic.
But it was actually
pretty hard to figure out
what was going on.
His owner was not trying
to defraud anybody,
his owner actually believed
he could do arithmetic.
And presumably Clever Hans himself
was not trying to trick anybody.
But eventually a psychologist examined him
and found that if he
was put in a room alone
without an audience,
and the person asking the
questions wore a mask,
he couldn't figure out
when to stop tapping.
You'd ask him, "Clever Hans,
"what's one plus one?"
And he'd just [knocking]
keep staring at your face, waiting for you
to give him some sign
that he was done tapping.
So everybody in this situation
was trying to do the right thing.
Clever Hans was trying
to do whatever it took
to get the apple that
his owner would give him
when he answered an arithmetic problem.
His owner did his best
to train him correctly
with real arithmetic questions
and real rewards for correct answers.
And what happened was that Clever Hans
inadvertently focused on the wrong cue.
He found this cue of
people's social reactions
that could reliably help
him solve the problem,
but then it didn't
generalize to a test set
where you intentionally
took that cue away.
It did generalize to a
naturally occurring test set,
where he had an audience.
So that's more or less what's happening
with machine learning algorithms.
They've found these very linear patterns
that can fit the training data,
and these linear patterns even
generalize to the test data.
They've learned to handle
any example that comes from
the same distribution
as their training data.
But then if you shift the distribution
that you test them on,
if a malicious adversary
actually creates examples
that are intended to fool them,
they're very easily fooled.
In fact we find that modern
machine learning algorithms
are wrong almost everywhere.
We tend to think of them as
being correct most of the time,
because when we run them on
naturally occurring inputs
they achieve very high
accuracy percentages.
But if we look instead
of as the percentage
of samples from an IID test set,
if we look at the percentage
of the space in RN
that is correctly classified,
we find that they
misclassify almost everything
and they behave reasonably
only on a very thin manifold
surrounding the data
that we train them on.
In this plot, I show you
several different examples
of Gaussian noise
that I've run through
a CIFAR-10 classifier.
Everywhere that there is a pink box,
the classifier thinks
that there is something
rather than nothing.
I'll come back to what
that means in a second.
Everywhere that there is a yellow box,
one step of the fast gradient sign method
was able to persuade the
model that it was looking
specifically at an airplane.
I chose the airplane class
because it was the one with
the lowest success rate.
It had about a 25% success rate.
That means an attacker
would need four chances
to get noise recognized as
an airplane on this model.
An interesting thing,
and appropriate enough
given the story of Clever Hans,
is that this model found
that about 70% of RN
was classified as a horse.
So I mentioned that this model will say
that noise is something
rather than nothing.
And it's actually kind of
important to think about
how we evaluate that.
If you have a softmax classifier,
it has to give you a distribution
over the n different classes
that you train it on.
So there's a few ways that you can argue
that the model is telling you
that there's something
rather than nothing.
One is you can say, if it
assigns something like 90%
to one particular class,
that seems to be voting
for that class being there.
We'd much rather see it give us
something like a uniform
distribution saying
this noise doesn't look like
anything in the training set
so it's equally likely
to be a horse or a car.
And that's not what the model does.
It'll say, this is very
definitely a horse.
Another thing that you
can do is you can replace
the last layer of the model.
For example, you can use a
sigmoid output for each class.
And then the model is actually
capable of telling you
that any subset of classes is present.
It could actually tell you that an image
is both a horse and a car.
And what we would like
it to do for the noise
is tell us that none of
the classes is present,
that all of the sigmoids
should have a value
of less than 1/2.
And 1/2 isn't even
particularly a low threshold.
We could reasonably expect that
all of the sigmoids would be
less than 0.01 for such a
defective input as this.
But what we find instead
is that the sigmoids
tend to have at least one class present
just when we run Gaussian noise
of sufficient norm through the model.
We've also found that we
can do adversarial examples
for reinforcement learning.
And there's a video for this.
I'll upload the slides after the talk
and you can follow the link.
Unfortunately I wasn't able
to get the WiFi to work
so I can't show you the video animated.
But I can describe
basically what's going on
from this still here.
There's a game Seaquest on Atari
where you can train
reinforcement learning agents
to play that game.
And you can take the raw input pixels
and you can take the
fast gradient sign method
or other attacks that use other
norms besides the max norm,
and compute perturbations
that are intended
to change the action that
the policy would select.
So the reinforcement learning policy,
you can think of it as just
being like a classifier
that looks at a frame.
And instead of categorizing the input
into a particular category,
it gives you a softmax
distribution over actions to take.
So if we just take that and
say that the most likely action
should have its accuracy be
decreased by the adversary.
Sorry, to have its probability
be decreased by the adversary,
you'll get these
perturbations of input frames
that you can then apply
and cause the agent
to play different actions
than it would have otherwise.
And using this you can make the agent
play Seaquest very, very badly.
It's maybe not the most
interesting possible thing.
What we'd really like is an environment
where there are many different
reward functions available
for us to study.
So for example, if you had a robot
that was intended to cook scrambled eggs,
and you had a reward function measuring
how well it's cooking scrambled eggs,
and you had another reward function
measuring how well it's
cooking chocolate cake,
it would be really
interesting if we could make
adversarial examples that cause the robot
to make a chocolate cake
when the user intended for
it to make scrambled eggs.
That's because it's very
difficult to succeed at something
and it's relatively straightforward
to make a system fail.
So right now, adversarial examples for RL
are very good at showing that
we can make RL agents fail.
But we haven't yet been
able to hijack them
and make them do a complicated task
that's different from
what their owner intended.
Seems like it's one of the next steps
in adversarial example research though.
If we look at high-dimension
linear models,
we can actually see that a lot of this
is very simple and straightforward.
Here we have a logistic regression model
that classifies sevens and threes.
So the whole model can be
described just by a weight vector
and a single scalar bias term.
We don't really need to see the
bias term for this exercise.
If you look on the left
I've plotted the weights
that we used to discriminate
sevens and threes.
The weights should look a
little bit like the difference
between the average seven
and the average three.
And then down at the bottom we've taken
the sign of the weights.
So the gradient for a
logistic regression model
is going to be proportional
to the weights.
And then the sign of the weights gives you
essentially the sign of the gradient.
So we can do the fast gradient sign method
to attack this model just
by looking at its weights.
In the examples in the panel
that's the second column from the left
we can see clean examples.
And then on the right we've
just added or subtracted
this image of the sign of
the weights off of them.
To you and me as human observers,
the sign of the weights
is just like garbage
that's in the background,
and we more or less filter it out.
It doesn't look particularly
interesting to us.
It doesn't grab our attention.
To the logistic regression model
this image of the sign of the weights
is the most salient thing
that could ever appear in the image.
When it's positive it looks like
the world's most quintessential seven.
When it's negative it looks like
the world's most quintessential three.
And so the model makes its decision
almost entirely based on this perturbation
we added to the image, rather
than on the background.
You could also take this same procedure,
and my colleague Andrej at
OpenAI showed how you can
modify the image on ImageNet
using this same approach,
and turn this goldfish into a daisy.
Because ImageNet is
much higher dimensional,
you don't need to use quite
as large of a coefficient
on the image of the weights.
So we can make a more
persuasive fooling attack.
You can see that this
same image of the weights,
when applied to any different input image,
will actually reliably
cause a misclassification.
What's going on is that there
are many different classes,
and it means that if
you choose the weights
for any particular class,
it's very unlikely that a new test image
will belong to that class.
So on ImageNet, if we're using
the weights for the daisy class,
and there are 1,000 different classes,
then we have about a 99.9% chance
that a test image will not be a daisy.
If we then go ahead and add the weights
for the daisy class to that image,
then we get a daisy,
and because that's not
the correct class, it's
a misclassification.
So there's a paper at CVPR this year
called Universal Adversarial Perturbations
that expands a lot more
on this observation
that we had going back in 2014.
But basically these weight vectors,
when applied to many different images,
can cause misclassification
in all of them.
I've spent a lot of time telling you
that these linear models
are just terrible,
and at some point you've
probably been hoping
I would give you some sort
of a control experiment
to convince you that there's another model
that's not terrible.
So it turns out that some quadratic models
actually perform really well.
In particular a shallow RBF network
is able to resist adversarial
perturbations very well.
Earlier I showed you an animation
where I took a nine and I turned it into
a zero, one, two, and so on,
without really changing
its appearance at all.
And I was able to fool
a linear softmax regression classifier.
Here I've got an RBF network
where it outputs a separate probability
of each class being absent or present,
and that probability is given
by e to the negative square
of the difference between a template image
and the input image.
And if we actually follow the
gradient of this classifier,
it does actually turn the image into
a zero, a one, a two, a three, and so on,
and we can actually
recognize those changes.
The problem is, this
classifier does not get
very good accuracy on the training set.
It's a shallow model.
It's basically just a template matcher.
It is literally a template matcher.
And if you try to make
it more sophisticated
by making it deeper,
it turns out that the gradient
of these RBF units is zero,
or very near zero, throughout most of RN.
So they're extremely difficult to train,
even with batch normalization
and methods like that.
I haven't managed to train
a deep RBF network yet.
But I think if somebody comes
up with better hyperparameters
or a new, more powerful
optimization algorithm,
it might be possible to solve
the adversarial example problem
by training a deep RBF network
where the model is so nonlinear
and has such wide flat areas
that the adversary is not
able to push the cost uphill
just by making small changes
to the model's input.
One of the things that's the most alarming
about adversarial examples
is that they generalize
from one dataset to another
and one model to another.
Here I've trained two different models
on two different training sets.
The training sets are tiny in both cases.
It's just MNIST three
versus seven classification,
and this is really just for
the purpose of making a slide.
If you train a logistic regression model
on the digits shown in the left panel,
you get the weights shown on
the left in the lower panel.
If you train a logistic regression model
on the digits shown in the upper right,
you get the weights shown on
the right in the lower panel.
So you've got two different training sets
and we learn weight vectors that look
very similar to each other.
That's just because machine
learning algorithms generalize.
You want them to learn a function that's
somewhat independent of the
data that you train them on.
It shouldn't matter which particular
training examples you choose.
If you want to generalize
from the training set to the test set,
you've also got to expect
that different training sets
will give you more or
less the same result.
And that means that
because they've learned
more or less similar functions,
they're vulnerable to
similar adversarial examples.
An adversary can compute
an image that fools one
and use it to fool the other.
In fact we can actually
go ahead and measure
the transfer rate between
several different machine
learning techniques,
not just different data sets.
Nicolas Papernot and his collaborators
have spent a lot of time exploring
this transferability effect.
And they found that for example,
logistic regression makes
adversarial examples
that transfer to decision
trees with 87.4% probability.
Wherever you see dark
squares in this matrix,
that shows that there's a
high amount of transfer.
That means that it's very
possible for an attacker
using the model on the left
to create adversarial examples
for the model on the right.
The procedure overall is that,
suppose the attacker wants to fool a model
that they don't actually have access to.
They don't know the
architecture that's used
to train the model.
They may not even know which
algorithm is being used.
They may not know
whether they're attacking
a decision tree or a deep neural net.
And they also don't know the parameters
of the model that they're going to attack.
So what they can do is
train their own model
that they'll use to build the attack.
There's two different ways
you can train your own model.
One is you can label your own training set
for the same task that you want to attack.
Say that somebody is using
an ImageNet classifier,
and for whatever reason you
don't have access to ImageNet,
you can take your own
photos and label them,
train your own object recognizer.
It's going to share adversarial examples
with an ImageNet model.
The other thing you can do is,
say that you can't afford to
gather your own training set.
What you can do instead is if you can get
limited access to the model
where you just have the ability
to send inputs to the model
and observe its outputs,
then you can send those
inputs, observe the outputs,
and use those as your training set.
This'll work even if the output
that you get from the target model
is only the class label that it chooses.
A lot of people read this and assume that
you need to have access
to all the probability values it outputs.
But even just the class
labels are sufficient.
So once you've used one
of these two methods,
either gather your own training set
or observing the outputs
of a target model,
you can train your own model
and then make adversarial
examples for your model.
Those adversarial examples
are very likely to transfer
and affect the target model.
So you can then go and
send those out and fool it,
even if you didn't have
access to it directly.
We've also measured the transferability
across different data sets,
and for most models we find that they're
kind of in an intermediate zone
where different data sets will result
in a transfer rate of, like, 60% to 80%.
There's a few models like SVMs
that are very data dependent
because SVMs end up focusing
on a very small subset
of the training data to form
their final decision boundary.
But most models that we care about
are somewhere in the intermediate zone.
Now that's just assuming that you rely
on the transfer happening naturally.
You make an adversarial example
and you hope that it will
transfer to your target.
What if you do something to
stack the deck in your favor
and improve the odds that you'll get
your adversarial examples to transfer?
Dawn Song's group at UC
Berkeley studied this.
They found that if they take
an ensemble of different models
and they use gradient
descent to search for
an adversarial example that will fool
every member of their ensemble,
then it's extremely likely
that it will transfer
and fool a new machine learning model.
So if you have an ensemble of five models,
you can get it to the point where
there's essentially a 100% chance
that you'll fool a sixth model
out of the set of models
that they compared.
They looked at things like
ResNets of different depths,
VGG, and GoogLeNet.
So in the labels for each
of the different rows
you can see that they
made ensembles that lacked
each of these different models,
and then they would test it on
the different target models.
So like if you make an
ensemble that omits GoogLeNet,
you have only about a
5% chance of GoogLeNet
correctly classifying
the adversarial example
you make for that ensemble.
If you make an ensemble
that omits ResNet-152,
in their experiments they found that
there was a 0% chance of
ResNet-152 resisting that attack.
That probably indicates
they should have run
some more adversarial examples
until they found a non-zero success rate,
but it does show that the
attack is very powerful.
And then when you go look into
intentionally cause the transfer effect,
you can really make it quite strong.
A lot of people often
ask me if the human brain
is vulnerable to adversarial examples.
And for this lecture I can't
use copyrighted material,
but there's some really
hilarious things on the Internet
if you go looking for, like,
the fake CAPTCHA with
images of Mark Hamill,
you'll find something
that my perception system
definitely can't handle.
So here's another one
that's actually published
with a license where I was
confident I'm allowed to use it.
You can look at this image
of different circles here,
and they appear to be intertwined spirals.
But in fact they are concentric circles.
The orientation of the
edges of the squares
is interfering with the edge
detectors in your brain,
making it look like the
circles are spiraling.
So you can think of
these optical illusions
as being adversarial
examples in the human brain.
What's interesting is that
we don't seem to share
many adversarial examples in common
with machine learning models.
Adversarial examples
transfer extremely reliably
between different machine learning models,
especially if you use that ensemble trick
that was developed at UC Berkeley.
But those adversarial
examples don't fool us.
It tells us that we must be using
a very different algorithm or model family
than current convolutional networks.
We don't really know what
the difference is yet,
but it would be very
interesting to figure that out.
It seems to suggest that
studying adversarial examples
could tell us how to significantly improve
our existing machine learning models.
Even if you don't care
about having an adversary,
we might figure out
something or other about
how to make machine learning algorithms
deal with ambiguity and unexpected inputs
more like a human does.
If we actually want to go out
and do attacks in practice,
there's started to be a body
of research on this subject.
Nicolas Papernot showed that he could use
the transfer effect to fool classifiers
hosted by MetaMind, Amazon, and Google.
So these are all just
different machine learning APIs
where you can upload a dataset
and the API will train the model for you.
And then you don't actually
know, in most cases,
which model is trained for you.
You don't have access to its
weights or anything like that.
So Nicolas would train
his own copy of the model
using the API,
and then build a model on
his own personal desktop
where he could fool the API hosted model.
Later, Berkeley showed you
could fool Clarifai in this way.
Yeah?
- [Man] What did you mean when you said
machine having adversarial
models don't generally fool us?
Because I thought that
was part of the point
that we generally do
machine-generated adversarial models
where just a few pixels change.
- Oh, so if we look at, for example,
like this picture of the panda.
To us it looks like a panda.
To most machine learning
models it looks like a gibbon.
And so this change isn't
interfering with our brains,
but it fools reliably
with lots of different
machine learning models.
I saw somebody actually took
this image of the perturbation
out of our paper, and they pasted it
on their Facebook profile picture
to see if it could interfere
with Facebook recognizing them.
And they said that it did.
I don't think that Facebook
has a gibbon tag though,
so we don't know if they managed to
make it think that they were a gibbon.
And one of the other
things that you can do
that's of fairly high
practical significance
is you can actually
fool malware detectors.
Catherine Gross at the
University of Saarland
wrote a paper about this.
And there's starting to be a few others.
There's a model called MalGAN
that actually uses a GAN
to generate adversarial
examples for malware detectors.
Another thing that matters
a lot if you are interested
in using these attacks in the real world
and defending against
them in the real world
is that a lot of the
time you don't actually
have access to the
digital input to a model.
If you're interested in
the perception system
for a self-driving car or a robot,
you probably don't get to
actually write to the buffer
on the robot itself.
You just get to show the robot objects
that it can see through a camera lens.
So my colleague Alexey
Kurakin and Samy Bengio and I
wrote a paper where we studied
if we can actually fool
an object recognition
system running on a phone,
where it perceives the
world through a camera.
Our methodology was
really straightforward.
We just printed out several pictures
of adversarial examples.
And we found that the
object recognition system
run by the camera was fooled by them.
The system on the camera
is actually different
from the model that we used
to generate the adversarial examples.
So we're showing not just transfer across
the changes that happen
when you use the camera,
we're also showing that
those transfer across
the model that you use.
So the attacker could conceivably fool
a system that's deployed
in a physical agent,
even if they don't have access
to the model on that agent
and even if they can't interface
directly with the agent
but just subtly modify
objects that it can
see in its environment.
Yeah?
- [Man] Why does the,
for the low quality camera image noise
not affect the adversarial example?
Because that's what one would expect.
- Yeah, so I think a lot of that
comes back to the maps
that I showed earlier.
If you cross over the
boundary into the realm
of adversarial examples,
they occupy a pretty wide space
and they're very densely packed in there.
So if you jostle around a little bit,
you're not going to recover
from the adversarial attack.
If the camera noise, somehow or other,
was aligned with the negative
gradient of the cost,
then the camera could take a
gradient descent step downhill
and rescue you from the uphill
step that the adversary took.
But probably the camera's
taking more or less
something that you could
model as a random direction.
Like clearly when you use
the camera more than once
it's going to do the same thing each time,
but from the point of
view of how that direction
relates to the image
classification problem,
it's more or less a random
variable that you sample once.
And it seems unlikely to align exactly
with the normal to this class boundary.
There's a lot of different
defenses that we'd like to build.
And it's a little bit disappointing
that I'm mostly here to
tell you about attacks.
I'd like to tell you how to
make your systems more robust.
But basically every attack we've tried
has failed pretty badly.
And in fact, even when
people have published
that they successfully defended.
Well, there's been several papers on arXiv
over the last several months.
Nicholas Carlini at Berkeley
just released a paper
where he shows that 10 of
those defenses are broken.
So this is a really, really hard problem.
You can't just make it go away by using
traditional regularization techniques.
Particular, generative
models are not enough
to solve the problem.
A lot of people say, "Oh the
problem that's going on here
"is you don't know anything
about the distribution
"over the input pixels.
"If you could just tell
"whether the input is realistic or not
"then you'd be able to resist it."
It turns out that what's going on here is
what matters more than getting
the right distributions
over the inputs x,
is getting the right
posterior distribution
over the class of labels y given inputs x.
So just using a generative model
is not enough to solve the problem.
I think a very carefully
designed generative model
could possibly do it.
Here I show two different modes
of a bimodal distribution,
and we have two different
generative models
that try to capture these modes.
On the left we have a
mixture of two Gaussians.
On the right we have a
mixture of two Laplacians.
You can not really tell
the difference visually
between the distribution
they impose over x,
and the difference in the
likelihood they assign
to the training data is negligible.
But the posterior distribution
they assign over classes
is extremely different.
On the left we get a logistic
regression classifier
that has very high confidence
out in the tails of the distribution
where there is never any training data.
On the right, with the
Laplacian distribution,
we level off to more or less 50-50.
Yeah?
[speaker drowned out]
The issue is that it's a
nonstationary distribution.
So if you train it to recognize
one kind of adversarial example,
then it will become
vulnerable to another kind
that's designed to fool its detector.
That's one of the category of
defenses that Nicholas broke
in his latest paper that he put out.
So here basically the choice of exactly
the family of generative
model has a big effect
in whether the posterior becomes
deterministic or uniform,
as the model extrapolates.
And if we could design a really
rich, deep generative model
that can generate
realistic ImageNet images
and also correctly calculate
its posterior distribution,
then maybe something like
this approach could work.
But at the moment it's
really difficult to get
any of those probabilistic
calculations correct.
And what usually happens is,
somewhere or other we
make an approximation
that causes the posterior distribution
to extrapolate very linearly again.
It's been a difficult
engineering challenge
to build generative models
that actually capture these
distributions accurately.
The universal approximator
theorem tells us that
whatever shape we would like
our classification function to have,
a neural net that's big enough
ought to be able to represent it.
It's an open question whether
we can train the neural net
to have that function,
but we know that we should be able to
at least give the right shape.
So so far we've been getting neural nets
that give us these very
linear decision functions,
and we'd like to get something
that looks a little bit
more like a step function.
So what if we actually just
train on adversarial examples?
For every input x in the training set,
we also say we want you to
train x plus an attack to map
to the same class label as the original.
It turns out that this sort of works.
You can generally resist
the same kind of attack that you train on.
And an important consideration
is making sure that you could
run your attack very quickly
so that you can train on lots of examples.
So here the green curve at the very top,
the one that doesn't
really descend much at all,
that's the test set error
on adversarial examples
if you train on clean examples only.
The cyan curve that descends
more or less diagonally
through the middle of the plot,
that's the tester on adversarial examples
if you train on adversarial examples.
You can see that it does
actually reduce significantly.
It gets down to a little
bit less than 1% error.
And the important thing to
keep in mind here is that
this is fast gradient sign
method adversarial examples.
It's much harder to resist
iterative multi-step adversarial examples
where you run an optimizer for a long time
searching for a vulnerability.
And another thing to keep in mind
is that we're testing on
the same kind of adversarial
examples that we train on.
It's harder to generalize
from one optimization
algorithm to another.
By comparison, if you look at
what happens on clean examples,
the blue curve shows what happens
on the clean test set error rate
if you train only on clean examples.
The red curve shows what happens
if you train on both clean
and adversarial examples.
We see that the red curve
actually drops lower than the blue curve.
So on this task, training
on adversarial examples
actually helped us to do
the original task better.
This is because in the original
task we were overfitting.
Training on adversarial
examples is good regularizer.
If you're overfitting it
can make you overfit less.
If you're underfitting it'll
just make you underfit worse.
Other kinds of models
besides deep neural nets
don't benefit as much
from adversarial training.
So when we started this
whole topic of study
we thought that deep neural nets
might be uniquely vulnerable
to adversarial examples.
But it turns out that actually
they're one of the few models that has
a clear path to resisting them.
Linear models are just
always going to be linear.
They don't have much hope of
resisting adversarial examples.
Deep neural nets can be
trained to be nonlinear,
and so it seems like there's
a path to a solution for them.
Even with adversarial training,
we still find that we aren't able to
make models where if
you optimize the input
to belong to different classes,
you get examples in those classes.
Here I start with a CIFAR-10
truck and I turn it into
each of the 10 different CIFAR-10 classes.
Toward the middle of the plot
you can see that the truck has started
to look a little bit like a bird.
But the bird class is the only one
that we've come anywhere near hitting.
So even with adversarial training,
we're still very far from
solving this problem.
When we do adversarial training,
we rely on having labels
for all the examples.
We have an image that's labeled as a bird.
We make a perturbation that's designed
to decrease the probability
of the bird class,
and we train the model
that the image should still be a bird.
But what if you don't have labels?
It turns out that you can
actually train without labels.
You ask the model to predict
the label of the first image.
So if you've trained for a little while
and your model isn't perfect yet,
it might say, oh, maybe this
is a bird, maybe it's a plane.
There's some blue sky there,
I'm not sure which of
these two classes it is.
Then we make an adversarial perturbation
that's intended to change the guess
and we just try to make it
say, oh this is a truck,
or something like that.
It's not whatever you
believed it was before.
You can then train it to say
that the distribution of our classes
should still be the same as it was before,
but this should still be considered
probably a bird or a plane.
This technique is called
virtual adversarial training,
and it was invented by Takeru Miyato.
He was my Intern at Google
after he did this work.
At Google we invited him to
come and apply his invention
to text classification,
because this ability to
learn from unlabeled examples
makes it possible to do
semi-supervised learning
where you learn from both
unlabeled and labeled examples.
And there's quite a lot of
unlabeled text in the world.
So we were able to bring
down the error rate
on several different
text classification tasks
by using this virtual
adversarial training.
Finally, there's a lot of problems where
we'd like to use neural nets
to guide optimization procedures.
If we want to make a very, very fast car,
we could imagine a neural net that looks
at the blueprints for a car
and predicts how fast it will go.
If we could then optimize
with respect to the
input of the neural net
and find the blueprint
that it predicts would go the fastest,
we could build an incredibly fast car.
Unfortunately, what we get right now
is not a blueprint for a fast car.
We get an adversarial
example that the model
thinks is going to be very fast.
If we're able to solve the
adversarial example problem,
we'll be able to solve
this model-based optimization problem.
I like to call model-based optimization
the universal engineering machine.
If we're able to do
model-based optimization,
we'll be able to write down
a function that describes
a thing that doesn't exist
yet but we wish that we had.
And then gradient descent and neural nets
will figure out how to build it for us.
We can use that to design
new genes and new molecules
for medicinal drugs,
and new circuits
to make GPUs run faster
and things like that.
So I think overall, solving this problem
could unlock a lot of potential
technological advances.
In conclusion, attacking
machine learning models
is extremely easy,
and defending them is extremely difficult.
If you use adversarial training
you can get a little bit of a defense,
but there's still many caveats
associated with that defense.
Adversarial training and
virtual adversarial training
also make it possible
to regularize your model
and even learn from unlabeled data
so you can do better on
regular test examples,
even if you're not concerned
about facing an adversary.
And finally, if we're able to
solve all of these problems,
we'll be able to build a black
box model-based optimization
system that can solve all
kinds of engineering problems
that are holding us back
in many different fields.
I think I have a few
minutes left for questions.
[audience applauds]
[speaker drowned out]
Yeah.
Oh, so,
there's some determinism
to the choice of those 50 directions.
Oh right, yeah.
So repeating the questions.
I've said that the same perturbation
can fool many different models
or the same perturbation can be applied
to many different clean examples.
I've also said that the subspace
of adversarial perturbations
is only about 50 dimensional,
even if the input dimension
is 3,000 dimensional.
So how is it that these
subspaces intersect?
The reason is that the choice
of the subspace directions
is not completely random.
It's generally going to be something like
pointing from one class centroid
to another class centroid.
And if you look at that vector
and visualize it as an image,
it might not be meaningful to a human
just because humans aren't very good
at imagining what class
centroids look like.
And we're really bad at imagining
differences between centroids.
But there is more or less
this systematic effect
that causes different models to learn
similar linear functions,
just because they're trying
to solve the same task.
[speaker drowned out]
Yeah, so the question is,
is it possible to identify
which layer contributes
the most to this issue?
One thing is that if you,
the last layer is somewhat important.
Because, say that you
made a feature extractor
that's completely robust to
adversarial perturbations
and can shrink them to
be very, very small,
and then the last layer is still linear.
Then it has all the problems
that are typically associated
with linear models.
And generally you can
do adversarial training
where you perturb all
the different layers,
all the hidden layers
as well as the input.
In this lecture I only
described perturbing the input
because it seems like that's where
most of the benefit comes from.
The one thing that you can't
do with adversarial training
is perturb the very last
layer before the softmax,
because that linear layer at the end
has no way of learning to
resist the perturbations.
Doing adversarial training at that layer
usually just breaks the whole process.
But other than that, it
seems very problem dependent.
There's a paper by Sara
Sabour and her collaborators
called Adversarial Manipulation
of Deep Representations,
where they design adversarial examples
that are intended to fool
different layers of the net.
They report some things about, like,
how large of a perturbation
is needed at the input
to get different sizes of perturbation
at different hidden layers.
I suspect that if you trained the model
to resist perturbations at one layer,
then another layer would
become more vulnerable
and it would be like a moving target.
[speaker drowned out]
Yes, so the question is,
how many adversarial examples are needed
to improve the misclassification rate?
Some of our plots we
include learning curves.
Or some of our papers we
include learning curves,
so you can actually see,
like in this one here.
Every time we do an epoch
we've generated the same
number of adversarial examples
as there are training examples.
So every epoch here is
50,000 adversarial examples.
You can see that adversarial
training is a very
data hungry process.
You need to make new adversarial examples
every time you update the weights.
And they're constantly
changing in reaction to
whatever the model has
learned most recently.
[speaker drowned out]
Oh, the model-based optimization, yeah.
Yeah, so the question is just to
elaborate further on this problem.
So most of the time that we
have a machine learning model,
it's something like a
classifier or a regression model
where we give it an
input from the test set
and it gives us an output.
And usually that input
is randomly occurring
and comes from the same
distribution as the training set.
We usually just run the
model, get its prediction,
and then we're done with it.
Sometimes we have feedback loops,
like for recommender systems.
If you work at Netflix and you recommend
a movie to a viewer,
then they're more likely
to watch that movie and then rate it,
and then there's going
to be more ratings of it
in your training set
so you'll recommend it to
more people in the future.
So there's this feedback loop
from the output of your
model to the input.
Most of the time when we
build machine vision systems,
there's no feedback loop from
their output to their input.
If we imagine a setting
where we start using an
optimization algorithm
to find inputs that maximize
some property of the output,
like if we have a model that looks
at the blueprints of a car
and outputs the expected speed of the car,
then we could use gradient ascent
to look for the blueprints that correspond
to the fastest possible car.
Or for example if we're
designing a medicine,
we could look for the molecular structure
that we think is most likely
to cure some form of cancer,
or the least likely to cause
some kind of liver toxicity effect.
The problem is that once
we start using optimization
to look for these inputs
that maximize the output of the model,
the input is no longer
an independent sample
from the same distribution
as we used at the training set time.
The model is now guiding the process
that generates the data.
So we end up finding essentially
adversarial examples.
Instead of the model telling us
how we can improve the input,
what we usually find in practice
is that we've got an
input that fools the model
into thinking that the input
corresponds to something great.
So we'd find molecules that are very toxic
but the model thinks
they're very non-toxic.
Or we'd find cars that are very slow
but the model thinks are very fast.
[speaker drowned out]
Yeah, so the question is,
here the frog class is boosted by going
in either the positive or
negative adversarial direction.
And in some of the other
slides, like these maps,
you don't get that effect
where subtracting epsilon off
eventually boosts the adversarial class.
Part of what's going on is
I think I'm using larger epsilon here.
And so you might
eventually see that effect
if I'd made these maps wider.
I made the maps narrower because
it's like quadratic time to build a 2D map
and it's linear time to
build a 1D cross section.
So I just didn't afford the GPU time
to make the maps quite as wide.
I also think that this might just be
a weird effect that happened
randomly on this one example.
It's not something that I
remember being used to seeing
a lot of the time.
Most things that I observe
don't happen perfectly consistently.
But if they happen, like, 80% of the time
then I'll put them in my slide.
A lot of what we're doing is
trying trying to figure out
more or less what's going on,
and so if we find that something
happens 80% of the time,
then I consider it to be
the dominant phenomenon
that we're trying to explain.
And after we've got a
better explanation for that
then I might start to try to explain
some of the weirder things that happen,
like the frog happening
with negative epsilon.
[speaker drowned out]
I didn't fully understand the question.
It's about the dimensionality
of the adversarial?
Oh, okay.
So the question is, how is the dimension
of the adversarial subspace related
to the dimension of the input?
And my answer is somewhat embarrassing,
which is that we've only run
this method on two datasets,
so we actually don't have a good idea yet.
But I think it's something
interesting to study.
If I remember correctly, my
coauthors open sourced our code.
So you could probably run it on ImageNet
without too much trouble.
My contribution to that paper was in
the week that I was unemployed
between working at OpenAI
and working at Google,
so I had access to no GPUS
and I ran that experiment
on my laptop on CPU,
so it's only really small
datasets. [chuckles]
[speaker drowned out]
Oh, so the question is,
do we end up perturbing
clean examples to low
confidence adversarial examples?
Yeah, in practice we usually find that
we can get very high confidence
on the output examples.
One thing in high dimensions
that's a little bit unintuitive
is that just getting the sign right
on very many of the input pixels
is enough to get a really strong response.
So the angle between the weight vector
matters a lot more than
the exact coordinates
in high dimensional systems.
Does that make enough sense?
Yeah, okay.
- [Man] So we're actually
going to [mumbles].
So if you guys need to leave, that's fine.
But let's thank our speaker one more time
for getting--
[audience applauds]